Unknown

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 21 — #21 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 1.2 Propositional Logic 21 Example 1.9 In Section 1.1, we used truth tables to show that a statement islogically equivalent to itscontrapositive. In thisexample we will construct a proof sequence for one direction of this logical equivalence: p→q ⇒¬q →¬p Solution: We apply the forward–backward approach. The only given statement is p → q, so we search our derivation rules for something that follows from thisstatement. The only candidate is ¬p∨q, by the implication rule, so we tentatively use this as the second step of the proof sequence. Now we consider the statement we are trying to prove, ¬q →¬p, and we look backward for a statement from which this statement follows. Since implication is an equivalence rule, we can also use it to move backward to the statement ¬(¬q)∨¬p, which we propose as the second-to-last statement of our proof. By moving forward one step from the given and backward one step from the goal, we have reduced the task of proving p→q ⇒¬q →¬p to the (hopefully) simpler task of proving ¬p∨q ⇒¬(¬q)∨¬p. Now it is fairly easy to see how to ﬁnish the proof: we can switch the∨statement around using commutativity and simplify using double negation. We can now write down the proof sequence. Statements Reasons 1. p→q given 2. ¬p∨q implication 3. q∨¬p commutativity 4. ¬(¬q)∨¬p double negation 5. ¬q →¬p implication We used the forward–backward approach to move forward from step 1 to step 2, and again to move backward from step 5 to step 4. Then we connected step 2 to step 4 with a simple proof sequence. ♦ You may have noticed that in Section 1.1, we proved the stronger statement p→q ⇔¬q →¬p using truth tables; the above example only proves the “⇒” direction of this equivalence. To prove the other direction, we need another proof sequence. However, in this case, this other proof sequence is easy to write down, because all of the derivation rules we used were reversible. Implication, commutativity,

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 22 — #22 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 22 Chapter 1 a73 Logical Thinking and double negation are all equivalence rules, so we could write down a new proof sequence with the order of the steps reversed, and we would have a valid proof of the “⇐” direction. Exercises 1.2 1. Use truth tables to establish the modustollens tautology: ¬q p→q bracerightBigg ⇒¬p 2. Fill in the reasons in the following proof sequence. Make sure you indicate which step(s) each derivation rule refers to. Statements Reasons 1. p∧(q∨r) given 2. ¬(p∧q) given 3. ¬p∨¬q 4. ¬q∨¬p 5. q →¬p 6. p 7. ¬(¬p) 8. ¬q 9. q∨r 10. r∨q 11. ¬(¬r)∨q 12. ¬r →q 13. ¬(¬r) 14. r 15. p∧r 3. Justify each conclusion with a derivation rule. (a) Someone who is artistic must also be creative. Joe is not creative. Therefore, Joe isnot artistic. (b) Lingli isboth athletic and intelligent. Therefore, Lingli isathletic.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 23 — #23 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 1.2 Propositional Logic 23 (c) If you are 18 yearsold, then you may vote. Monique is18 yearsold. Therefore, Monique may vote. (d) Marianne has never been north of Saskatoon or south of Santo Domingo. In other words, she has never been north of Saskatoon and she has never been south of Santo Domingo. 4. Let x and y be integers. Given the statement x>yor x isodd. what statement follows by the implication rule? 5. Let Q be a quadrilateral. Given the statements If Q isa rhombus, then Q isa parallelogram. Q isnot a parallelogram. what statement follows by modustollens? 6. Let x and y be numbers. Simplify the following statement using De Mor- gan’slawsand double negation. It isnot the case that x isnot greater than 3 and y isnot found. 7. Write a statement that follows from the statement It issunny and warm today. by the simpliﬁcation rule. 8. Write a statement that follows from the statement This soup tastes funny. by the addition rule. 9. Recall Exercise 1.1.27. Suppose that all of the following status reports are correct: • Processor B is not working and processor C isworking. • Processor A is working if and only if processor B isworking. • At least one of the two processors A, B isnot working. Let a =“A isworking,” b =“B isworking,” and c =“C isworking.” (a) If you haven’t already done so, write each status report in terms of a, b, and c, using the symbols of formal logic. (b) How would you justify the conclusion that B isnot working? (In other words, given the statements in part (a), which derivation rule allowsyou to conclude ¬b?)

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 24 — #24 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 24 Chapter 1 a73 Logical Thinking (c) How would you justify the conclusion that C isworking? (d) Write a proof sequence to conclude that A isnot working. (In other words, given the statements in part (a), write a proof sequence to conclude ¬a.) 10. Write a proof sequence for the following assertion. Justify each step. p→¬q r → (p∧q) bracerightBigg ⇒¬r 11. Write a proof sequence for the following assertion. Justify each step. p p→r q →¬r      ⇒¬q 12. Write a proof sequence for the following assertion. Justify each step. p→q p∧r bracerightBigg ⇒q∧r 13. Write a proof sequence for the following assertion. Justify one of the steps in your proof using the result of Example 1.8. ¬(a∧¬b) ¬b bracerightBigg ⇒¬a 14. Write a proof sequence to establish that p⇔p∧p isa tautology. 15. Write a proof sequence to establish that p ⇔ p∨p isa tautology. (Hint: Use De Morgan’slawsand Exercise 14.) 16. Write a proof sequence for the following assertion. Justify each step. ¬(¬p→q)∨(¬p∧¬q) ⇒¬p∧¬q 17. Write a proof sequence for the following assertion. Justify each step. (p∨q)∨(p∨r) ⇒¬r → (p∨q) 18. Consider the following assertion. ¬(¬p∨q) ⇒ p∨q

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 25 — #25 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 1.2 Propositional Logic 25 (a) Find a statement that is one step forward from the given. (b) Find a statement that is one step backward from the goal. (Use the addition rule—in reverse—to ﬁnd a statement from which the goal will follow.) (c) Give a proof sequence for the assertion. (d) Isyour proof reversible? Why or why not? 19. Use a truth table to show that p→q ¬p bracerightBigg ? ⇒¬q is not a tautology. (This example shows that substitution isn’t valid for inference rules, in general. Substituting the weaker statement, q, for the stronger statement, p, in the expression “¬p” doesn’t work.) 20. (a) Fill in the reasons in the following proof sequence. Make sure you indicate which step(s) each derivation rule refers to. Statements Reasons 1. p→ (q →r) given 2. ¬p∨(q →r) 3. ¬p∨(¬q∨r) 4. (¬p∨¬q)∨r 5. ¬(p∧q)∨r 6. (p∧q) →r (b) Explain why the proof in part (a) isreversible. (c) The proof in part (a) (along with its reverse) establishes the following tautology: p→ (q →r) ⇔ (p∧q) →r Therefore, to prove an assertion of the form A ⇒ B → C,itis suﬃcient to prove A B bracerightBigg ⇒C instead. Use this fact to rewrite the tautology p∧(q →r) ⇒ q → (p∧r) asa tautology of the form A B bracerightBigg ⇒C,

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 26 — #26 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 26 Chapter 1 a73 Logical Thinking where C doesnot contain the → connective. (The process of rewrit- ing a tautology thisway iscalled the deductionmethod.) (d) Give a proof sequence for the rewritten tautology in part (c). 21. Thisexercise will lead you through a proof of the distributiveproperty of ∧ over ∨. We will prove: p∧(q∨r) ⇒ (p∧q)∨(p∧r). (a) The above assertion is the same as the following: p∧(q∨r) ⇒¬(p∧q) → (p∧r). Why? (b) Use the deduction method to rewrite the tautology from part (b). (c) Prove your rewritten tautology. 22. Use a truth table to show that (a→b)∧(a∧¬b) isa contradiction. 23. Is a→¬a a contradiction? Why or why not? 1.3 PredicateLogic When we deﬁned statements, we said that a sentence of the form x iseven is not a statement, because its T/F value depends on x. Mathematical writing, however, almost alwaysdealswith sentencesof thistype; we often express mathematical ideasin termsof some unknown variable. Thissection explains how to extend our formal system of logic to deal with this situation. 1.3.1 Predicates Deﬁnition 1.3 Apredicate is a declarative sentence whose T/F value depends on one or more variables. In other words, a predicate is a declarative sentence with variables, and after those variables have been given speciﬁc values, the sentence becomes a statement. We use function notation to denote predicates. For example, P(x)=“x iseven,” and Q(x,y)=“x isheavier than y”

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 27 — #27 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 1.3 Predicate Logic 27 are predicates. The statement P(8) istrue, while the statement Q(feather,brick) isfalse. Implicit in a predicate isthe domain (or universe) of valuesthat the vari- able(s) can take. For P(x), the domain could be the integers; for Q(x,y), the domain could be some collection of physical objects. We will usually state the domain along with the predicate, unless it is clear from the context. Equationsare predicates. For example, if E(x) stands for the equation x 2 −x−6=0, thenE(3) istrue and E(4) is false. We regard equations as declarative sentences, where the = sign plays the role of a verb. 1.3.2 Quantiﬁers By themselves, predicates aren’t statements because they contain free variables. We can make them into statements by plugging in speciﬁc values of the domain, but often we would like to describe a range of valuesfor the variablesin a predicate. A quantiﬁer modiﬁes a predicate by describing whether some or all elements of the domain satisfy the predicate. We will need only two quantiﬁers: universal and existential. The universal quantiﬁer “for all” isdenoted by ∀. So the statement (∀x)P(x) says that P(x) istrue forall x in the domain. Theexistentialquantiﬁer “there exists” is denoted by ∃. The statement (∃x)P(x) says that thereexists an element x of the domain such that P(x) istrue; in other words, P(x) istrue forsome x in the domain. For example, if E(x) isthe real number equation x 2 −x−6 = 0, then the expression (∃x)E(x) says, “There is some real number x such that x 2 −x−6 = 0,” or more simply, “The equation x 2 −x− 6 = 0 hasa solution.” The variable x isno longer a free variable, since the ∃ quantiﬁer changesthe role it playsin the sentence. If Z(x) represents the real number equation x·0 = 0, the expression (∀x)Z(x)

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 28 — #28 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 28 Chapter 1 a73 Logical Thinking means“For all real numbers x, x·0 = 0.” Again, thisisa sentence without free variables, since the range of possible values for x isclearly speciﬁed. When we put a quantiﬁer in front of a predicate, we form a quantiﬁed statement. Since the quantiﬁer restrictsthe range of valuesfor the variablesin the predicate, the quantiﬁed statement is either true or false (but not both). In the above examples, (∃x)E(x) and (∀x)Z(x) are both true, while the statement (∀x)E(x) is false, since there are some real numbers that do not satisfy the equation x 2 −x−6=0. The real power of predicate logic comesfrom combining quantiﬁers, predi- cates, and the symbols of propositional logic. For example, if we would like to claim that there isa negative number that satisﬁesthe equation x 2 −x−6=0, we could deﬁne a new predicate N(x)=“x isnegative.” Then the statement (∃x)(N(x)∧E(x)) translatesas“There existssome real number x such that x isnegative and x 2 −x−6=0.” The scope of a quantiﬁer isthe part of the formula to which the quantiﬁer refers. In a complicated formula in predicate logic, it is important to use paren- theses to indicate the scope of each quantiﬁer. In general, the scope is what lies inside the set of parentheses right after the quantiﬁer: (∀x)(...scope of ∀...), (∃x)(...scope of ∃...). In the statement (∃x)(N(x)∧E(x)), the scope of the ∃ quantiﬁer isthe expres- sion N(x)∧E(x). 1.3.3 Translation There are lotsof diﬀerent waysto write quantiﬁed statementsin English. Trans- lating back and forth between English statements and predicate logic is a skill that takespractice. Example 1.10 Using all carsasa domain, if P(x)=“x getsgood mileage.” Q(x)=“x islarge.”

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 29 — #29 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 1.3 Predicate Logic 29 then the statement (∀x)(Q(x) →¬P(x)) could be translated very literally as “For all cars x,ifx islarge, then x doesnot get good mileage.” However, a more natural translation of the same statement is “All large carsget bad mileage.” or “There aren’t any large carsthat get good mileage.” If we wanted to say the opposite, that is, that there are some large cars that get good mileage, we could write the following. (∃x)(P(x)∧Q(x)) We’ll give a formal proof that thisnegation iscorrect in Example 1.13. The next example shows how a seemingly simple mathematical statement yieldsa rather complicated formula in predicate logic. The careful use of pred- icatescan help reveal the logical structure of a mathematical claim. Example 1.11 In the domain of all integers, let P(x)=“x iseven.” We can express the fact that the sum of an even number with an odd number is odd asfollows. (∀x)(∀y)[(P(x)∧¬P(y)) → (¬P(x+y))] Of course, the literal translation of this quantiﬁed statement is “For all integers x and for all integers y,ifx iseven and y isnot even, then x+y isnot even,” but we normally say something informal like “An even plus an odd is odd.” This last example used two universal quantiﬁers to express a fact about an arbitrary pair x,y of integers. The next example shows what can happen when you combine universal and existential quantiﬁers in the same statement. Example 1.12 In the domain of all real numbers, let G(x,y) be the predicate “x>y.” The statement (∀y)(∃x)G(x,y) says literally that “For all numbers y, there exists some number x such that x>y,” or more simply, “Given any number y, there issome number that is greater than y.” Thisstatement isclearly true: the number y + 1 isalways greater than y, for example. However, the statement (∃x)(∀y)G(x,y) translates literally as “There exists a number x such that, for all numbers y, x>y.” In simpler language, this statement says, “There is some number that is

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 30 — #30 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 30 Chapter 1 a73 Logical Thinking greater than any other number.” This statement is clearly false, because there isno largest number. The order of the quantiﬁers matters. In both of these statements, a claim ismade that x isgreater than y. In the ﬁrst statement, you are ﬁrst given an arbitrary number y, then the claim is that it is possible to ﬁnd some x that is greater than it. However, the second statement claims there is some number x, such that, given any other y, x will be the greater number. In the second statement, you must decide on what x isbefore you pick y. In the ﬁrst statement, you pick y ﬁrst, then you can decide on x. 1.3.4 Negation The most important thing you need to be able to do with predicate logic is to write down the negation of a quantiﬁed statement. As with propositional logic, there are some formal equivalences that describe how negation works. Table 1.5 lists two important rules for forming the opposite of a quantiﬁed statement. It is easy to see the formal pattern of these two rules: to negate a quantiﬁed statement, bring the negation inside the quantiﬁer, and switch the quantiﬁer. Let’sinterpret the negation rulesin the context of an example. In the domain of all people, let L(x) stand for “x isa liar.” The universal negation rule says that the negation of “All people are liars” is “There exists a person who is not a liar.” In symbols, ¬[(∀x)L(x)] ⇔ (∃x)(¬L(x)). Similarly, the existential negation rule says that the negation of “There exists a liar” is“There are no liars.” Example 1.13 In Example 1.10, we discussed what the negation of the state- ment “All large carsget bad mileage.” should be. We can answer this question by negating the formal statement (∀x)(Q(x) →¬P(x)) (1.3.1) Equivalence Name ¬[(∀x)P(x)] ⇔ (∃x)(¬P(x)) universal negation ¬[(∃x)P(x)] ⇔ (∀x)(¬P(x)) existential negation Table 1.5 Negation rulesfor predicate logic.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 31 — #31 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 1.3 Predicate Logic 31 using a proof sequence. We’ll suppose as given the negation of statement 1.3.1, and deduce an equivalent statement. Statements Reasons 1. ¬[(∀x)(Q(x) →¬P(x))] given 2. (∃x)¬(Q(x) →¬P(x)) universal negation 3. (∃x)¬(¬Q(x)∨¬P(x)) implication 4. (∃x)(¬(¬Q(x))∧¬(¬P(x))) De Morgan’slaw 5. (∃x)(Q(x)∧P(x)) double negation 6. (∃x)(P(x)∧Q(x)) commutativity Notice that the result of our formal argument agrees with the intuitive negation we did in Example 1.10: There exists some car that is both large and gets good mileage. Example 1.14 Let the domain be all facesof the following truncated icosa- hedron (also known as a soccer ball). Consider the following predicates. P(x)=“x isa pentagon.” H(x)=“x isa hexagon.” B(x,y)=“x borders y.” Here we say that two polygons border each other if they share an edge. Conﬁrm that the following observations are true for any truncated icosahedron. 1. No two pentagonsborder each other. 2. Every pentagon borderssome hexagon. 3. Every hexagon bordersanother hexagon.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 32 — #32 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 32 Chapter 1 a73 Logical Thinking Write these statements in predicate logic, and negate them. Simplify the negated statements so that no predicate lies withing the scope of a negation. Translate your negated statement back into English. Solution: The formalizations of these statements are as follows. 1. (∀x)(∀y)((P(x)∧P(y)) →¬B(x,y)) 2. (∀x)(P(x) → (∃y)(H(y)∧B(x,y))) 3. (∀x)(H(x) → (∃y)(H(y)∧B(x,y)) We’ll negate (2), and leave the othersasexercises. See if you can ﬁgure out the reasons for each equivalence. ¬[(∀x)(P(x) → (∃y)(H(y)∧B(x,y)))] ⇔ (∃x)[¬(P(x) → (∃y)(H(y)∧B(x,y)))] ⇔ (∃x)[¬(¬P(x)∨(∃y)(H(y)∧B(x,y)))] ⇔ (∃x)[¬¬(P(x)∧¬(∃y)(H(y)∧B(x,y)))] ⇔ (∃x)[¬¬(P(x)∧(∀y)¬(H(y)∧B(x,y)))] ⇔ (∃x)(P(x)∧(∀y)¬(H(y)∧B(x,y))) ⇔ (∃x)(P(x)∧(∀y)(¬H(y)∨¬B(x,y))) ⇔ (∃x)(P(x)∧(∀y)(H(y) →¬B(x,y))) This last statement says that there exists an x such that x isa pentagon and, for any y,ify isa hexagon, then x doesnot border y. In other words, there is some pentagon that borders no hexagon. If you found a solid with this property, it couldn’t be a truncated icosahedron. ♦ 1.3.5 TwoCommonConstructions There are two expressions that come up often, and knowing the predicate logic for these expressions makes translation much easier. The ﬁrst is the statement All 〈blanks〉 are 〈something〉. For example, “All baseball players are rich,” or “All oysters taste funny.” In gen- eral, if P(x) and Q(x) are the predicates“x is 〈blank〉” and “x is 〈something〉” respectively, then the predicate logic expression (∀x)(P(x) →Q(x)) translates as “For all x,ifx is 〈blank〉, then x is 〈something〉.” Put more simply, “All x’swith property 〈blank〉 must have property 〈something〉,” or

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 33 — #33 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 1.3 Predicate Logic 33 even simpler, “All 〈blanks〉 are 〈something〉.” In the domain of all people, if R(x) stands for “x isrich” and B(x) stands for “x isa baseball player,” then (∀x)(B(x) →R(x)) is the statement “All baseball players are rich.” The second construction is of the form There isa 〈blank〉 that is 〈something〉. For example, “There isa rich baseball player,” or “There isa funny-tasting oyster.” This expression has the following form in predicate logic. (∃x)(P(x)∧Q(x)) Note that thistranslatesliterally as“There issome x such that x is 〈blank〉 and x is 〈something〉,” which is what we want. In the domain of shellﬁsh, if O(x)is the predicate “x isan oyster” and F(x) isthe predicate “x tastes funny,” then (∃x)(F(x)∧O(x)) would translate as “There is a funny-tasting oyster.” Note that you could also say “There is an oyster that tastes funny,” “Some oysters taste funny,” or, more awkwardly, “There is a funny-tasting shellﬁsh that is an oyster.” These statements all mean the same thing. Exercises 1.3 1. In the domain of integers, let P(x,y) be the predicate “x·y = 12.” Tell whether each of the following statementsistrue or false. (a) P(3,4) (b) P(3,5) (c) P(2,6)∨P(3,7) (d) (∀x)(∀y)(P(x,y) →P(y,x)) (e) (∀x)(∃y)P(x,y) 2. In the domain of all penguins, let D(x) be the predicate “x isdanger- ous.” Translate the following quantiﬁed statements into simple, everyday English.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 34 — #34 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 34 Chapter 1 a73 Logical Thinking (a) (∀x)D(x) (b) (∃x)D(x) (c) ¬(∃x)D(x) (d) (∃x)¬D(x) 3. In the domain of all movies, let V(x) be the predicate “x isviolent.” Write the following statements in the symbols of predicate logic. (a) Some moviesare violent. (b) Some moviesare not violent. (c) No moviesare violent. (d) All moviesare violent. 4. In the domain of all books, consider the following predicates. H(x)=“x isheavy.” C(x)=“x isconfusing.” Translate the following statements in predicate logic into ordinary En- glish. (a) (∀x)(H(x) →C(x)) (b) (∃x)(C(x)∧H(x)) (c) (∀x)(C(x)∨H(x)) (d) (∃x)(H(x)∧¬C(x)) 5. The domain of the following predicatesisthe set of all plants. P(x)=“x is poisonous.” Q(x) = “Jeﬀ haseaten x.” Translate the following statements into predicate logic. (a) Some plants are poisonous. (b) Jeﬀ hasnever eaten a poisonousplant. (c) There are some nonpoisonous plants that Jeﬀ has never eaten. 6. In the domain of nonzero integers, let I(x,y) be the predicate “x/y isan integer.” Determine whether the following statements are true or false, and explain why. (a) (∀y)(∃x)I(x,y) (b) (∃x)(∀y)I(x,y)

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 35 — #35 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 1.3 Predicate Logic 35 7. The domain of the following predicatesisthe set of all traderswho work at the Tokyo Stock Exchange. P(x,y)=“x makesmore money than y.” Q(x,y)=“xnegationslash= y” Translate the following predicate logic statements into ordinary,every- day English. (Don’t simply give a word-for-word translation; try to write sentences that make sense.) (a) (∀x)(∃y)P(x,y) (b) (∃y)(∀x)(Q(x,y) →P(x,y)) (c) Which statement is impossible in this context? Why? 8. Translate the following statements into predicate logic using the two com- mon constructions in Section 1.3.5. State what your predicates are, along with the domain of each. (a) All natural numbersare integers. (b) Some integersare natural numbers. (c) All the streets in Cozumel, Mexico are one-way. (d) Some streets in London don’t have modern curb cuts. 9. Write the following statements in predicate logic. Deﬁne what your pred- icates are. Use the domain of all quadrilaterals. (a) All rhombuses are parallelograms. (b) Some parallelograms are not rhombuses. 10. Let the following predicatesbe given. The domain isall people. R(x)=“x isrude.” ¬R(x)=“x ispleasant.” C(x)=“x isa child.” (a) Write the following statement in predicate logic. There isat least one rude child. (b) Formally negate your statement from part (a). (c) Write the English translation of your negated statement. 11. In the domain of all people, consider the following predicate. P(x,y)=“x needsto love y.”

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 36 — #36 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 36 Chapter 1 a73 Logical Thinking (a) Write the statement “Everybody needs somebody to love” in predi- cate logic. (b) Formally negate your statement from part (a). (c) Write the English translation of your negated statement. 12. The domain for this problem is some unspeciﬁed collection of numbers. Consider the predicate P(x,y)=“x isgreater than y.” (a) Translate the following statement into predicate logic. Every number hasa number that isgreater than it. (b) Negate your expression from part (a), and simplify it so that no quantiﬁer lieswithin the scope of a negation. (c) Translate your expression from part (b) into understandable English. Don’t use variables in your English translation. 13. Any equation or inequality with variablesin it isa predicate in the domain of real numbers. For each of the following statements, tell whether the statement is true or false. (a) (∀x)(x 2 >x) (b) (∃x)(x 2 −2=1) (c) (∃x)(x 2 +2=1) (d) (∀x)(∃y)(x 2 +y =4) (e) (∃y)(∀x)(x 2 +y =4) 14. The domain of the following predicatesisall integersgreater than 1. P(x)=“x isprime.” Q(x,y)=“x divides y.” Consider the following statement. For every x that isnot prime, there issome prime y that divides it. (a) Write the statement in predicate logic. (b) Formally negate the statement. (c) Write the English translation of your negated statement. 15. Write the following statement in predicate logic, and negate it. Say what your predicatesare, along with the domains. Let x and y be real numbers. If x isrational and y isirrational, then x+y isirrational.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 37 — #37 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 1.3 Predicate Logic 37 16. Refer to Example 1.14. (a) Give the reasons for each ⇔ step in the simpliﬁcation of the formal negation of statement (2). (b) Give the formal negation of statement (1). Simplify your answer so that no quantiﬁer lies within the scope of a negation. Translate your negated statement back into English. (c) Give the formal negation of statement (3). Simplify your answer. Translate your negated statement back into English. 17. Let the following predicatesbe given in the domain of all triangles. R(x)=“x isa right triangle.” B(x)=“x hasan obtuse angle.” Consider the following statements. S 1 = ¬(∃x)(R(x)∧B(x)) S 2 =(∀x)(R(x) →¬B(x)) (a) Write a proof sequence to show that S 1 ⇔S 2 . (b) Write S 1 in ordinary English. (c) Write S 2 in ordinary English. 18. Let the following predicatesbe given. The domain isall computer science classes. I(x)=“x isinteresting.” U(x)=“x isuseful.” H(x,y)=“x isharder than y.” M(x,y)=“x hasmore studentsthan y.” (a) Write the following statements in predicate logic. i. All interesting CS classes are useful. ii. There are some useful CS classes that are not interesting. iii. Every interesting CS class has more students than any non- interesting CS class. (b) Write the following predicate logic statement in everyday English. Don’t just give a word-for-word translation; your sentence should make sense. (∃x)[I(x)∧(∀y)(H(x,y) →M(y,x))]

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 38 — #38 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 38 Chapter 1 a73 Logical Thinking (c) Formally negate the statement from part (b). Simplify your negation so that no quantiﬁer lies within the scope of a negation. State which derivation rulesyou are using. (d) Give a translation of your negated statement in everyday English. 19. Let the following predicatesbe given. The domain isall cars. F(x)=“x isfast.” S(x)=“x isa sportscar.” E(x)=“x isexpensive.” A(x,y)=“x issafer than y.” (a) Write the following statements in predicate logic. i. All sports cars are fast. ii. There are fast cars that aren’t sports cars. iii. Every fast sports car is expensive. (b) Write the following predicate logic statement in everyday English. Don’t just give a word-for-word translation; your sentence should make sense. (∀x)[S(x) → (∃y)(E(y)∧A(y,x))] (c) Formally negate the statement from part (b). Simplify your negation so that no quantiﬁer lies within the scope of a negation. State which derivation rulesyou are using. (d) Give a translation of your negated statement in everyday English. 20. (a) Give an example of a pair of predicates P(x) and Q(x) in some domain to show that the ∃ quantiﬁer doesnot distribute over the ∧ connective. That is, give an example to show that the statements (∃x)(P(x)∧Q(x)) and (∃x)P(x)∧(∃x)Q(x) are not logically equivalent. (b) It istrue, however, that ∃ distributes over ∨. That is, (∃x)(P(x)∨Q(x)) ⇔ (∃x)P(x)∨(∃x)Q(x) isan equivalence rule for predicate logic. Verify that your example from part (a) satisﬁes this equivalence. 21. (a) Give an example to show that ∀ doesnot distribute over ∨. (b) It isa fact that ∀ distributes over ∧. Check that your example from part (a) satisﬁes this equivalence rule.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 39 — #39 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 1.4 Logic in Mathematics 39 1.4 LogicinMathematics There is much more that we could say about symbolic logic; we have only scratched the surface. But we have developed enough tools to help us think carefully about the typesof language mathematiciansuse. Thissection provides an overview of the basic mathematical “parts of speech.” Most mathematicstextbooks(including thisone) label important state- mentswith a heading, such as“Theorem,” “Deﬁnition,” or “Proof.” The name of each statement describes the role it plays in the logical development of the subject. Therefore it is important to understand the meanings of these diﬀerent statement labels. 1.4.1 TheRoleofDeﬁnitionsinMathematics When we call a statement a “deﬁnition” in mathematics, we mean something diﬀerent from the usual everyday notion. Everyday deﬁnitions are descriptive. The thing being deﬁned already exists, and the purpose of the deﬁnition is to describe the thing. When a dictionary deﬁnes some term, it is characterizing the way the term iscommonly used. For example, if we looked up the deﬁnition of “mortadella” in the OxfordEnglishDictionary (OED), we would read the following. Any of several types of Italian (esp. Bolognese) sausage; (now) spec. a thick smooth-textured pork sausage containing pieces of fat and typically served in slices. The authors of the OED have done their best to describe what is meant by the term “mortadella.” A good dictionary deﬁnition isone that doesa good job describing something. In mathematics, by contrast, a deﬁnition is a statement that stipulates the meaning of a new term, symbol, or object. For example, a plane geometry textbook may deﬁne parallel linesasfollows. Deﬁnition 1.4 Two linesare parallel if they have no pointsin common. The job of this deﬁnition is not to describe parallel lines, but rather to specify exactly what we mean when we use the word “parallel.” Once parallel lines have been deﬁned in thisway, the statement “ l and m are parallel” means“l and m have no pointsin common.” We may have some intuitive idea of what l and m might look like (e.g., they must run in the same direction), but for the purposes of any future arguments, the only thing we really know about l and m isthat they don’t intersect each other. In a sense, a mathematical deﬁnition calls into being the object it deﬁnes. Without a deﬁnition of parallel lines, there can be no mathematical discussion of parallel lines. A dictionary deﬁnition, by contrast, doesn’t create anything

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 40 — #40 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 40 Chapter 1 a73 Logical Thinking new; we don’t imagine that the writers of the OED are in the business of making sausage (and everything else, for that matter). Why isthisdistinction important? It meansthat the whole meaning of a mathematical statement dependson the deﬁnitionsof the termsinvolved. If you don’t understand a mathematical statement, start looking at the deﬁnitions of all the terms. These deﬁnitions stipulate the meanings of the terms. The statement won’t make sense without them. For example, suppose we want to state and prove some facts about even and odd numbers. We already know what even and odd numbers are; we all come to this task with a previously learnedconceptimage of “even” and “odd.” Our concept image iswhat we think of when we hear the term: an even number ends in an even digit, an odd number can’t be divided in half evenly, “2, 4, 6, 8; who do we appreciate,” etc. When writing mathematically, however, it isimportant not to rely too heavily on these concept images. Any mathematical statement about even and odd numbersderivesitsmeaning from from deﬁnitions. We specify these as follows. Deﬁnition 1.5 An integer n is even if n =2k for some integer k. Deﬁnition 1.6 An integer n is odd if n =2k + 1 for some integer k. Given these deﬁnitions, we can justify the statement “17 is odd” by noting that 17=2·8+1. In fact, this equation is precisely the meaning of the statement that “17 isodd;” there issome integer k (in thiscase, k = 8) such that 17 = 2k+1. You already “knew” that 17 isodd, but in order to mathematically prove that 17 isodd, you need to use the deﬁnition. Mathematical deﬁnitions must be extremely precise, and this can make them somewhat limited. Often our concept image contains much more infor- mation than the deﬁnition supplies. For example, we probably all agree that it is impossible for a number to be both even and odd, but this fact doesn’t follow immediately from Deﬁnitions 1.5 and 1.6. To say that some given number n iseven meansthat n =2k 1 for some integer k 1 , and to say that it is odd is to say that n =2k 2 + 1 for some integer k 2 . (Note that k 1 and k 2 may be diﬀerent.) Now, isthispossible? It would imply that 2 k 1 =2k 2 +1, which says that 1 = 2(k 1 −k 2 ), showing that 1 is even, by Deﬁnition 1.5. At this point we might object that 1 isodd, so it can’t be even, but thisreasoning iscircular: we were trying to show that a number cannot be both even and odd. We haven’t yet shown this fact, so we can’t use this fact in our argument. It turns out that Deﬁnitions1.5 and 1.6 alone are not enough to show that a number can’t be both even and odd; to do so requires more facts about integers, as we will see in Section 1.5. One reasonable objection to the above discussion is that our deﬁnition of odd integerswastoo limiting; why not deﬁne an odd integer to be an integer

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 41 — #41 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 1.4 Logic in Mathematics 41 that isn’t even? This is certainly permissible, but then it would be hard 4 to show that an odd integer n can be written as2k +1 for some integer k. And we can’t have two deﬁnitions for the same term. Stipulating a deﬁnition usually involvesa choice on the part of the author, but once thischoice ismade, we are stuck with it. We have chosen to deﬁne odd integers as in Deﬁnition 1.6, so thisiswhat we mean when we say “odd.” Since deﬁnitions are stipulative, they are logically “if and only if” state- ments. However, it iscommon to write deﬁnitionsin the form [Object] x is[deﬁned term] if [deﬁning property about x]. The foregoing examplesall take thisform. In predicate logic, if D(x)=x is[deﬁned term] P(x) = [deﬁning property about x] then the above deﬁnition really meansthe following. (∀x)(P(x) ↔D(x)) However, thisisnot what the deﬁnition saysat face value. Deﬁnitionslook like “if ...then” statements, but we interpret them as “if and only if” statements because they are deﬁnitions. For example, Deﬁnition 1.4 is stipulating the prop- erty that deﬁnes all parallel lines, not just a property some parallel lines might have. Strictly speaking, we really should use “if and only if” instead of “if” in our deﬁnitions. But the use of “if” is so widespread that most mathematicians would ﬁnd a deﬁnition like Two linesare parallel if and only if they have no pointsin common. awkward to read. Since thisstatement isa deﬁnition, it isredundant to say “if and only if.” 1.4.2 OtherTypesofMathematicalStatements Deﬁnitionsare a crucial part of mathematics, but there are other kindsof statements that occur frequently in mathematical writing. Any mathematical system needs to start with some assumptions. Without any statements to build on, we would never be able to prove any new statements. Statements that are assumed without proof are called postulates or axioms. For example, the following is a standard axiom about the natural numbers. If n isa natural number, so is n+1. 4. Actually, it would be impossible, without further information.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 42 — #42 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 42 Chapter 1 a73 Logical Thinking Axiomsare typically very basic, fundamental statementsabout the objectsthey describe. Any theorem in mathematics is based on the assumption of some set of underlying axioms. So to say theorems are “true” is not to say they are true in any absolute sense, only that they are true, given that some speciﬁed set of axiomsistrue. Atheorem is a statement that follows logically from statements we have al- ready established or taken as given. Before a statement can be called a theorem, we must be able to prove it. Aproof is a valid argument, based on axioms, deﬁ- nitions, and proven theorems, that demonstrates the truth of a statement. The derivation sequences that we did in Section 1.2 were very basic mathematical proofs. We will see more interesting examples of proofs in the next section. We also use the termslemma,proposition, andcorollary to refer to speciﬁc kinds of theorems. Usually authors will label a result a lemma if they are using it to prove another result. Some authors make no distinction between a theorem and a proposition, but the latter often refers to a result that is perhaps not assigniﬁcant asa full-ﬂedged theorem. A corollary isa theorem that follows immediately from another result via a short argument. One last word on terminology: A statement that we intend to prove is called aclaim. A statement that we can’t yet prove but that we suspect is true iscalled a conjecture. 1.4.3 Counterexamples Often mathematical statements are of the form (∀x)P(x). (1.4.1) We saw in the previous section that the negation of statement 1.4.1 is (∃x)¬P(x). (1.4.2) So either statement 1.4.1 is true, or statement 1.4.2 is true, but not both. If we can ﬁnd a single value for x that makes ¬P(x) true, then we know that statement 1.4.2 is true, and therefore we also know that statement 1.4.1 is false. For example, we might be tempted to make the following statement. Every prime number isodd. (1.4.3) But 2 isan example of a prime number that isnot odd, so statement 1.4.3 is false. A particular value that shows a statement to be false is called a coun- terexample to the statement. Another common logical form in mathematics is the universal if–then state- ment. (∀x)(P(x) →Q(x))

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 43 — #43 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 1.4 Logic in Mathematics 43 To ﬁnd a counterexample to a statement of this form, we need to ﬁnd some x that satisﬁes the negation (∃x)¬(P(x) →Q(x)). This last statement is equivalent (using implication and De Morgan’s law) to (∃x)(P(x)∧¬Q(x)). So a counterexample is something that satisﬁes P and violates Q. Example 1.15 Find a counterexample to the following statement. For all sequences of numbers a 1 ,a 2 ,a 3 ,...,ifa 1 <a 2 <a 3 < ···, then some a i must be positive. Solution: By the above discussion, we need an example of a sequence that satisﬁes the “if” part of the statement and violates the “then” part. In other words, we need to ﬁnd an increasing sequence that is always negative. Some- thing with a horizontal asymptote will work: a n = −1/n isone example. Note that −1 <−1/2 <−1/3 <···, but all the termsare lessthan zero. ♦ 1.4.4 AxiomaticSystems In rigorous, modern treatments of mathematics, any system (e.g., plane geom- etry, the real numbers) must be clearly and unambiguously deﬁned from the start. The deﬁnitions should leave nothing to intuition; they mean what they say and nothing more. It is important to be clear about the assumptions, or ax- ioms, for the system. Every theorem in the system must be proved with a valid argument, using only the deﬁnitions, axioms, and previously proved theorems of the system. This sounds good, but it is actually impossible. It is impossible because we can’t deﬁne everything; before we write the ﬁrst deﬁnition we have to have some words in our vocabulary. These starting words are calledundeﬁnedterms. An undeﬁned term hasno meaning—it isan abstraction—itsmeaning comes from the role it plays in the axioms of the system. A collection of undeﬁned termsand axiomsiscalled an axiomaticsystem. Axiomatic systems for familiar mathematics such as plane geometry and the real number system are actually quite complicated and beyond the scope of an introductory course. Here we will look at some very simple axiomatic systems to get a feel for how they work. This will also give us some experience with logic in mathematics. The ﬁrst example deﬁnes a “ﬁnite geometry,” that is, a system for geometry with a ﬁnite number of points. Although this system speaks of “points” and

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 44 — #44 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 44 Chapter 1 a73 Logical Thinking “lines,” these terms don’t mean the same thing they meant in high school geometry. In fact, these terms don’t mean anything at all, to begin with at least. The only thing we know about points and lines is that they satisfy the given axioms. Example 1.16 Axiomatic system for a four-point geometry. Undeﬁnedterms: point, line, ison Axioms: 1. For every pair of distinct points x and y, there isa unique line such that x ison l and y ison l. 2. Given a line l and a point x that isnot on l, there isa unique line m such that x ison m and no point on l isalso on m. 3. There are exactly four points. 4. It is impossible for three points to be on the same line. Notice that these axioms use terms from logic in addition to the undeﬁned terms. We are also using numbers (“four” and “three”), even though we haven’t deﬁned an axiomatic system for the natural numbers. In this case, our use of numbersismore a convenient shorthand than anything; we aren’t relying on any propertiesof the natural numberssuch asaddition, ordering, divisibility, etc. It is common to use an existing system to deﬁne a new axiomatic system. For example, some modern treatments of plane geometry use axioms that rely on the real number system. The axioms in Example 1.16 use constructions from predicate logic. In any event, these prerequisite systems can also be deﬁned axiomatically, so systems that use them are still fundamentally axiomatic. Deﬁnitions can help make an axiomatic system more user-friendly. In the four-point geometry of Example 1.16, we could make the following deﬁnitions. In these (and other) deﬁnitions, the word being deﬁned is in italics. Deﬁnition 1.7 A line lpassesthrough a point x if x ison l. Deﬁnition 1.7 givesusa convenient alternative to using the undeﬁned term “is on.” For example, in the ﬁrst axiom, it is a bit awkward to say “x ison l and y ison l,” but Deﬁnition 1.7 allowsusto rephrase thisas“ l passes through x and y.” The deﬁnition doesn’t add any new features to the system; it just helps us describe things more easily. This is basically what any deﬁnition in mathematics does. The following deﬁnition is a slight restatement of Deﬁnition 1.4, modiﬁed to ﬁt the terminology of this system. Deﬁnition 1.8 Two lines, l and m, are parallel if there isno point x, such that x ison l and x ison m.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 45 — #45 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 1.4 Logic in Mathematics 45 Now we could rephrase the second axiom of Example 1.16 as follows. 2. Given a line l and a point x that isnot on l, there isa unique line m passing through x such that m isparallel to l. A simple theorem and proof would look like this. Theorem 1.1 IntheaxiomaticsystemofExample1.16,thereareatleasttwo distinctlines. Proof By Axiom 3, there are distinct points x, y, and z. By Axiom 1, there isa line l 1 through x and y, and a line l 2 through y and z. By Axiom 4, x, y, and z are not on the same line, so l 1 and l 2 must be distinct lines. square A model of an axiomatic system is an interpretation in some context in which all the undeﬁned termshave meaningsand all the axiomshold. Models are important because they show that it is possible for all the axioms to be true, at least in some context. And any theorem that follows from the axioms must also be true for any valid model. Let’s make a model for the system in Example 1.16. Let a “point” be a dot, and let a “line” be a simple closed loop. A point “is on” a line if the dot is inside the loop. Figure 1.3 showsthismodel. Check that all the axiomshold. Thismodel doesn’t really match our concept image of pointsand linesin ordinary geometry, but it’s still a valid model. In an axiomatic system, the propertiesof the objectsare determined by the axiomsand described by the theoremsand deﬁnitions. We may think we know what pointsand linesshould look like, but mathematically speaking we only know whatever we can prove about them. In the exercises you will construct a more intuitive model for this system. The mathematician David Hilbert (1862–1943) was largely responsible for developing the modern approach to axiomatics. Hilbert, reﬂecting on the Figure 1.3 A model for the axiomatic system in Example 1.16 using dots and loops.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 46 — #46 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 46 Chapter 1 a73 Logical Thinking abstract nature of axiomatic systems, remarked, “Instead of points, lines, and planes, one must be able to say at all times tables, chairs, and beer mugs” [24]. If we used a word processor to replace every occurrence of “point” with “table” and every occurrence of “line” with “chair” in the above axioms, deﬁnitions, theorem, and proof, the theorem would still hold, and the proof would still be valid. The next example is referred to in the exercises. The choice of undeﬁned terms emphasizes that these terms, by themselves, carry no meaning. Example 1.17 Badda-Bing axiomatic system. Undeﬁnedterms: badda, bing, hit Axioms: 1. Every badda hitsexactly four bings. 2. Every bing ishit by exactly two baddas. 3. If x and y are distinct baddas, each hitting bing q, then there are no other bingshit by both x and y. 4. There isat least one bing. One possible model for the Badda-Bing system is shown in Figure 1.4. The picture shows an inﬁnite collection of squares; the central square connects to Figure 1.4 A fractal model for the Badda-Bing geometry.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 47 — #47 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 1.4 Logic in Mathematics 47 four other squares whose sides are half as long. Each of these squares connects to three other smaller squares, and each of those connects to three others, and so on. Thisisan example of a fractal—a shape with some sort of inﬁnitely repetitive geometric structure. (We’ll say more about fractals in Chapter 3.) In thismodel, a “badda” isa square, and a “bing” isa corner, or vertex, of a square. A square “hits” a vertex if the vertex belongs to the square. Since every square has four vertices, Axiom 1 is satisﬁed. Axiom 2 holds because every vertex in the model belongs to exactly two squares. Axiom 3 is a little harder to see: if squares x and y share a vertex q, there isno way they can share another vertex. And Axiom 4 is obviously true—there are lots of bings. Exercises 1.4 1. Look up the word “root” in a dictionary. It should have several diﬀerent deﬁnitions. Find a deﬁnition that is (a) descriptive and another deﬁnition that is(b) stipulative. 2. Find another word in the English language that has both descriptive and stipulative deﬁnitions. 3. Use Deﬁnition 1.5 to explain why 104 is an even integer. 4. Let n be an integer. Use Deﬁnition 1.6 to explain why 2n+ 7 isan odd integer. 5. Let n 1 and n 2 be even integers. (a) Use Deﬁnition 1.5 to write n 1 and n 2 in termsof integersk 1 and k 2 , respectively. (b) Write the product n 1 n 2 in termsof k 1 and k 2 . Simplify your answer. (c) Write the sum n 1 +n 2 in termsof k 1 and k 2 . Simplify your answer. 6. There are several diﬀerent modelsfor geometriesin which the pointsare ordered pairs( x,y) of real numbers; we plot these points in the usual way in the xy-plane. In such a geometry, there can be a formula for the distance between two points(x 1 ,y 1 ) and (x 2 ,y 2 ). For example, in Euclidean geometry, distance is given by the usual Euclidean distance formula: Distance = radicalbig (x 2 −x 1 ) 2 +(y 2 −y 1 ) 2 In any geometry with a distance formula, we can deﬁne acircle asfollows.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 48 — #48 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 48 Chapter 1 a73 Logical Thinking Deﬁnition 1.9 A circle centered at (a,b) with radius r isthe collection of all points( x,y) whose distance from (a,b)isr. (a) Use Deﬁnition 1.9 to give an equation for the circle with radius 5 centered at (0,0) in the Euclidean plane. (b) Plot the circle from part (a) in the xy-plane. (c) In the Taxicabgeometry, the distance between two points (x 1 ,y 1 ) and (x 2 ,y 2 ) isgiven by the following formula. Distance = |x 2 −x 1 |+|y 2 −y 1 | (This is called “taxicab” distance because it models the distance you would have to travel if you were restricted to driving on a rectangular city grid.) In thismodel, use Deﬁnition 1.9 to plot the “circle” with radius5 centered at (0 ,0). (d) Which type of circle (Euclidean or taxicab) agreeswith your concept image of circle? 7. Consider the domain of all quadrilaterals. Let A(x)=“x hasfour right angles.” R(x)=“x isa rectangle.” Write the meaning of each mathematical statement in predicate logic, keeping in mind the logical distinction between deﬁnitions and theorems. (a) Deﬁnition. A quadrilateral isa rectangle if it hasfour right angles. (b) Theorem. A quadrilateral isa rectangle if it hasfour right angles. 8. Write Deﬁnition 1.5 in predicate logic. Use the predicate E(x)=“x is even” in the domain of integers. 9. Let the following statements be given. Deﬁnition. A triangle isscalene if all of itssideshave diﬀerent lengths. Theorem. A triangle isscalene if it isa right triangle that is not isosceles. Suppose triangleABC is a scalene triangle. Which of the following conclusions are valid? Why or why not? (a) All of the sides of triangleABC have diﬀerent lengths. (b) triangleABC is a right triangle that is not isosceles.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 49 — #49 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 1.4 Logic in Mathematics 49 10. What isthe diﬀerence between an axiom and a theorem? 11. Let P(n,x,y,z) be the predicate “x n +y n = z n .” (a) Write the following statement in predicate logic, using positive inte- gersasthe domain. For every positive integer n, there exist positive integers x, y, and z such that x n +y n = z n . (b) Formally negate your predicate logic statement from part (a). Sim- plify so that no quantiﬁer lies within the scope of a negation. (c) In order to produce a counterexample to the statement in part (a), what, speciﬁcally, would you have to ﬁnd? 12. Find a counterexample for each statement. (a) If n isprime, then 2 n −1 isprime. (b) Every triangle has at least one obtuse angle. 5 (c) For all real numbers x, x 2 ≥x. (d) For every positive nonprime integer n, if some prime p divides n, then some other prime q (with q negationslash= p) also divides n. (e) If all the sides of a quadrilateral are equal, then the diagonals of the quadrilateral are equal. (f) For every real number N>0, there issome real number x such that Nx>x. (g) Let l, m, and n be linesin the plane. If l ⊥m and n intersect l, then n intersects m. (h) If p isprime, then p 2 + 4 isprime. 13. Which of the statementsin the previousproblem can be proved astheo- rems? 14. Consider the following theorem. Theorem. Let x be a wamel. If x hasbeen schlumpfed, then x isa borﬁn. Answer the following questions. (a) Give the converse of this theorem. (b) Give the contrapositive of this theorem. (c) Which statement, (a) or (b), is logically equivalent to the Theorem? 5. An angle is obtuse if it has measure greater than 90 ◦ .

Unknown

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 50 — #50 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 50 Chapter 1 a73 Logical Thinking 15. Draw a model for the axiomatic system of four-point geometry (Exam- ple 1.16), where a “line” isa line segment, a “point” isan endpoint of a line segment, and a point “ison” a line if it isone of itsendpoints. 16. In four-point geometry, use the axioms to explain why every point is on three diﬀerent lines. 17. In four-point geometry, is it possible for two diﬀerent lines to both pass through two given distinct points? Explain why or why not using the axioms. 18. In four-point geometry, do triangles exist? In other words, is it possible to have three distinct points, not on the same line, such that a line passes through each pair of points? Why or why not? 19. In four-point geometry, state a good deﬁnition to stipulate what it means for two linesto intersect. 20. Consider the following model for four-point geometry. Points:1,2,3,4 Lines: 12, 13, 14, 23, 24, 34 A point “ison” a line if the line’sbox containsthe point. (a) Give a pair of parallel linesin thismodel. (Refer to Deﬁnition 1.8.) (b) Give a pair of intersecting linesin thismodel. (Use your deﬁnition from Exercise 19.) 21. Explain why, in the axiomatic system of Example 1.17, there must be at least seven distinct bings. 22. Consider the following deﬁnition in the system of Example 1.17. Deﬁnition. Let x and y be distinct baddas. We say that a bing q isa boom of x and y,ifx hits q and y hits q. Rewrite Axiom 3 using this deﬁnition. 23. In the context of Example 1.17, consider the following predicates. N(x,y)=“xnegationslash= y.” D(x)=“x isa badda.” G(x)=“x isa bing.” H(x,y)=“x hits y.” Use these predicates to write Axiom 3 in predicate logic.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 51 — #51 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 1.5 Methodsof Proof 51 24. Refer to Example 1.17 and Figure 1.4. Describe a diﬀerent model, using squares and vertices, where all the squares are the same size. 25. In the axiomatic system of Example 1.17, let a “badda” be a line segment, let a “bing” be a point, and say that a line segment “hits” a point if it passes through it. In the diagram below, there are 4 baddas and 12 bings. Isthisa model for the system? Which of the axiomsdoesthismodel satisfy? Explain. 26. Describe a model for Example 1.17 with 10 bings, where a “badda” is a line segment and a “bing” is a point. 1.5 MethodsofProof The typesof proofswe did in Section 1.2 were fairly mechanical. We started with the given and constructed a sequence of conclusions, each justiﬁed by a deduction rule. We were able to write proofsthisway because our mathematical system, propositional logic, was fairly small. Most mathematical contexts are much more complicated; there are more deﬁnitions, more axioms, and more complex statements to analyze. These more complicated situations do not easily lend themselves to the kind of structured proof sequences of Section 1.2. In this section we will look at some of the ways proofs are done in mathematics. 1.5.1 DirectProofs The structure of a proof sequence in propositional logic is straightforward: in order to prove A⇒C, we prove a sequence of results. A⇒B 1 ⇒B 2 ⇒···⇒B n ⇒C A directproof in mathematicshasthe same logic, but we don’t usually write such proofs as lists of statement and reasons. Instead, this linear chain of im- plicationsiscouched in mathematical prose and written in paragraph form.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 52 — #52 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 52 Chapter 1 a73 Logical Thinking Example 1.18 The proof of Theorem 1.1 on page 45 isa direct proof. Al- though thisproof takesthe form of a paragraph, the logical sequence of impli- cationsiseasy to see. There are distinct points x, y, and z. ⇒ There isa line l 1 through x and y, and a line l 2 through y and z. ⇒x, y, and z are not on the same line, so l 1 negationslash= l 2 . These three statements are justiﬁed by Axioms 3, 1, and 4, respectively. Example 1.19 Prove the following statement. For all real numbers x,ifx>1, then x 2 > 1. Proof Let x be a real number, and suppose x>1. Multiplying both sides of this inequality by a positive number preserves the inequality, so we can multiply both sides by x to obtain x 2 >x. Since x>1, we have x 2 >x>1, or x 2 > 1, asrequired. square It isworth looking back at thisproof. The chain of implicationsisasfollows. x>1 ⇒ x 2 >x ⇒ x 2 > 1 (1.5.1) Each conclusion is justiﬁed by an elementary fact from high school algebra, and the results are packaged in paragraph form. More precisely, the statement we were proving wasactually a quantiﬁed statement of the form (∀x)(P(x) →Q(x)) where P(x) means“ x>1” and Q(x) means“ x 2 > 1.” We see that the sequence of implicationsin Equation (1.5.1) istrue no matter what value we initially choose for x. Thisisthe meaning of the introductory phrase “Let x be a real number.” We assume nothing about x other than that it isa real number; it isarbitrary in every other respect. We then treat P(x) asgiven, and try to conclude Q(x). Since x could have been any real number to start with, we have proved the implication for all x. We state this type of proof as our ﬁrst “Rule of Thumb” for proving theo- rems. Rule of Thumb 1.1 To prove a statement of the form (∀x)(P(x) → Q(x)), begin your proof with a sentence of the form Let x be [an element of the domain], and suppose P(x). A direct proof is then a sequence of justiﬁed conclusions culminating in Q(x).

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 53 — #53 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 1.5 Methodsof Proof 53 Before we look at another example of direct proof, we will need some tools for dealing with integers. We’ll start with a deﬁnition for what it means for an integer x to divide another integer y. Deﬁnition 1.10 An integer x divides an integer y if there issome integer k such that y = kx. We write x | y to denote that x divides y. An identical deﬁnition holdsfor natural numbers (i.e., positive integers). Just replace the three occurrences of “integer” in Deﬁnition 1.10 with “natural number.” We are not going to develop a rigorousaxiomatic approach to the integers; such a treatment is beyond the scope of this course. When you deal with inte- ger equations, feel free to use elementary facts from high school algebra. You can add something to both sides of an equation, use the distributive property, combine terms, and so on. However, there are certain facts about the integers that we will state as axioms, because they justify important steps in the proofs that follow. Axiom 1.1 If a and b are integers, so are a+b and a·b. Axiom 1.1 describes theclosure property of the integersunder addition and multiplication. Most number systems are closed under these two operations; you can’t get a new kind of number by adding or multiplying. On the other hand, the integers are not closed under division: 2/3 isnot an integer, even though 2 and 3 are. Example 1.20 Prove the following. For all integers a, b, and c,ifa|b and a|c, then a| (b+c). Proof Let integers a, b, and c be given, and suppose a|b and a|c. Then, by Deﬁnition 1.10, there issome integer k 1 such that b = k 1 a and there issome integer k 2 such that c = k 2 a. Therefore, b+c = k 1 a+k 2 a =(k 1 +k 2 )a. By Axiom 1.1, k 1 +k 2 isan integer, so a| (b+c), again by Deﬁnition 1.10. square Notice that thisproof illustrateshow deﬁnitionsare used in mathematics. We used the deﬁnition of “divides” in order to translate the given statement into an equation, we did some simple algebra on this equation to obtain a new equation, and we used the deﬁnition again to translate the new equation into the statement we were trying to prove. Figure 1.5 shows a “ﬂow chart” for this proof technique.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 54 — #54 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 54 Chapter 1 a73 Logical Thinking Given statement Algebraic formula definition definition Statement to prove New algebraic formula algebra Figure 1.5 The structure of an algebraic proof. 1.5.2 ProofbyContraposition Sometimes it is hard to see how to get a direct proof started. If you get stuck (and you will), try proving the contrapositive. Thisiscertainly permitted, since the contrapositive of a statement is its logical equivalent. We can state this as another rule of thumb. Rule of Thumb 1.2 To prove a statement of the form (∀x)(P(x) → Q(x)), begin your proof with a sentence of the form Let x be [an element of the domain], and suppose ¬Q(x). A proof by contraposition is then a sequence of justiﬁed conclusions culminating in ¬P(x). Example 1.21 Suppose x and y are positive real numbers such that the geo- metric mean √ xy isdiﬀerent from the arithmetic mean x+y 2 . Then xnegationslash= y. Proof (By contraposition.) Let x and y be positive real numbers, and suppose x = y. Then √ xy = √ x 2 since x = y = x since x ispositive = x+x 2 using arithmetic = x+y 2 since x = y square Contraposition isn’t a radically new proof technique; a proof of a statement by contraposition is just a direct proof of the statement’s contrapositive. In Example 1.21, the form of the statement to prove gave a clue that a proof

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 55 — #55 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 1.5 Methodsof Proof 55 by contraposition would work. If A isthe statement “ √ xy = x+y 2 ” and B is the statement “x = y,” then the statement to prove has the form ¬A →¬B. The contrapositive of this statement is B → A, so our proof started with the assumption that x = y and concluded that √ xy = x+y 2 . For the next example we need some facts from the system of plane geometry that you studied in high school. Henceforth, we’ll refer to this type of geometry asEuclidean geometry. The following theorem, which we will not prove, istrue in Euclidean geometry. Theorem 1.2 Thesumofthemeasuresoftheanglesofanytriangleequals 180 ◦ . The deﬁnition of parallel that we used in four-point geometry also works in Euclidean geometry. Although the wording of the following deﬁnition isa little diﬀerent, the content isfundamentally the same. Deﬁnition 1.11 Two linesare parallel if they do not intersect. We’ll use these two statements in the next example. Example 1.22 Prove: If two lines are cut by a transversal such that a pair of interior anglesare supplementary, then the linesare parallel. A BC D Proof (By contraposition.) Suppose we are given two lines cut by a transversal as shown above, and suppose the lines are not parallel. Then, by the deﬁnition of parallel lines, the lines intersect. Without loss of generality, suppose they in- tersect on the right at point X. (If they intersect on the left, the same argument will work.) A B X By Theorem 1.2, the sum of the angles oftriangleXABis180 ◦ . Since∠X hasmeasure greater than 0, the sum of the measures of ∠A and ∠B must be less than 180 ◦ , so ∠A and ∠B can’t be supplementary. square

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 56 — #56 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 56 Chapter 1 a73 Logical Thinking 1.5.3 ProofbyContradiction Sometimes even a simple-looking statement can be hard to prove directly, with or without contraposition. In this case, it sometimes helps to try a proof by contradiction. The idea isa little counterintuitive. To prove statement A, sup- pose its negation ¬A istrue. Then argue, asin a direct proof, until you reach a statement that you know to be false. You will have established the sequence ¬A⇒B 1 ⇒B 2 ⇒···⇒B n ⇒ F where F represents a statement that is always false, that is, a contradiction. Taking contrapositivesof thischain givesusa sequence A⇐¬B 1 ⇐¬B 2 ⇐···⇐¬B n ⇐ T and since T isalwaystrue (i.e., a tautology) it followsthat A istrue also. To sum up: Rule of Thumb 1.3 To prove a statement A by contradiction, begin your proof with the following sentence: Suppose, to the contrary, that ¬A. Then argue, asin a direct proof, until you reach a contradiction. Thisnext example issimilar to Example 1.22. In fact, it isa weaker state- ment, so the proof given in Example 1.22 could also be used to prove it. But it makesa nice example of the contradiction method. Example 1.23 In Euclidean geometry, prove: If two linesshare a common perpendicular, then the linesare par- allel. Before stating the proof, notice that thistheorem isof the following form. (∀x)(∀y)(C(x,y) →P(x,y)) Here C(x,y) means“ x and y share a common perpendicular,” and P(x,y) means“ xbardbly.” You can check that the formal negation of thisstatement isthe following. (∃x)(∃y)(C(x,y)∧¬P(x,y)) The translation of this last statement is “There exist lines who share a common perpendicular but are not parallel.” So we use this statement to start our proof by contradiction.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 57 — #57 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 1.5 Methodsof Proof 57 Proof (By contradiction.) Suppose, to the contrary, that line AB isa com- mon perpendicular to lines AC and BD, and also that AC and BD are not parallel. Then, by Deﬁnition 1.11, AC and BD intersect in some point X. But then triangleABX hastwo right angles(and a third angle of nonzero measure), contradicting Theorem 1.2. square The next results rely on properties of even and odd numbers, so we need to use these deﬁnitions in our arguments. Recall: Deﬁnition 1.5. An integer n iseven if n =2k for some integer k. Deﬁnition 1.6. An integer n isodd if n =2k+1 for some integer k. As we discussed in Section 1.4.1, these deﬁnitions alone don’t imply that every integer iseither even or odd. We’ll state thisfact asan axiom. 6 Axiom 1.2 For all integers n, ¬(n iseven) ⇔ (n isodd). In other words, any integer is either even or odd, but never both. This axiom isthe key to proving the following lemma. Lemma 1.1 Let n be an integer. If n 2 iseven, then n iseven. Proof (By contraposition.) Let n be an integer, and suppose n isnot even. Then n isodd, by Axiom 1.2. So there issome integer k such that n =2k+1. Then n 2 =(2k +1) 2 =4k 2 +4k + 1 = 2(2k 2 +2k)+1 and since (2k 2 +2k) isan integer (by Axiom 1.1), we have shown that n 2 is odd. By Axiom 1.2, n 2 isnot even, asrequired. square Our ﬁnal example is a classic proof by contradiction. Recall that arational number isa number that can be written as a/b, where a and b are integerswith bnegationslash=0. Example 1.24 Prove that √ 2 isirrational. Proof (By contradiction.) Suppose, to the contrary, that √ 2 isrational, so there are integers a and b such that a/b = √ 2, and a and b can be chosen so that 6. Inamorerigoroustreatmentofnumbertheory,thisfactcouldbeprovedusingthedivision algorithm, which would follow from the well-ordering principle.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 58 — #58 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 58 Chapter 1 a73 Logical Thinking the fraction a/b is in lowest terms. Then a 2 /b 2 =2,soa 2 =2b 2 , that is, a 2 iseven. By Lemma 1.1, a iseven. Therefore a =2k for some integer k,so a 2 =4k 2 . But now we have b 2 = a 2 /2=2k 2 ,sob 2 iseven, and therefore, by the lemma again, b iseven aswell. We have shown that a and b are both even, which contradicts the assumption that a/b is in lowest terms. square Exercises 1.5 1. Consider the following statement. For all integers x,if4|x, then x iseven. (a) Write this statement in predicate logic in the domain of integers. Say what your predicatesare. (b) Apply Rule of Thumb 1.1 to write down the ﬁrst sentence of a direct proof of thisstatement. (c) Use Deﬁnition 1.10 to translate your supposition in part (b) into algebra. (d) Finish the proof of the statement. 2. Give a direct proof: Let a, b, and c be integers. If a|b and a|c, then a| (b·c). Remember that you must use the deﬁnition of | in your proof. 3. Prove: Let a, b, and c be integers. If (a·b) |c, then a|c. 4. Give a direct proof. Let a, b, and c be integers. If a|b and b|c, then a|c. 5. Give a direct proof of the following statement in Euclidean geometry. Cite any theoremsyou use. The sum of the measures of the angles of a parallelogram is 360 ◦ . 6. Prove: For all integers n,ifn 2 isodd, then n isodd. Use a proof by contraposition, as in Lemma 1.1.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 59 — #59 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 1.5 Methodsof Proof 59 7. Prove the following statement by contraposition. Let x be an integer. If x 2 +x+ 1 iseven, then x isodd. Make sure that your proof makes appropriate use of Deﬁnitions 1.5 and 1.6. 8. Prove that the sum of two even integersiseven. 9. Prove that the sum of an even integer and an odd integer is odd. 10. Prove that the sum of two odd integers is even. 11. Write a proof by contradiction of the following. Let x and y be integers. If x and y satisfy the equation 3x+5y = 153 then at least one of x and y isodd. 12. Prove the following statement in Euclidean geometry. Use a proof by contradiction. A triangle cannot have more than one obtuse angle. 13. Let “x notbar y” denote “x doesnot divide y.” Prove by any method. Let a and b be integers. If 5 notbar ab, then 5 notbar a and 5 notbar b. 14. Consider the following deﬁnition. Deﬁnition. An integer n is sane if 3 | (n 2 +2n). (a) Give a counterexample to the following: All odd integersare sane. (b) Give a direct proof of the following: If 3 |n, then n issane. (c) Prove by contradiction: If n =3j + 2 for some integer j, then n is not sane. 15. Prove that the rational numbersare closed under multiplication. That is, prove that, if a and b are rational numbers, then a · b isa rational number. 16. Prove that the rational numbersare closed under addition. 17. Prove: Let x and y be real numbers. If x isrational and y isirrational, then x·y isirrational. 18. Prove: Let x and y be real numbers. If x isrational and y isirrational, then x+y isirrational.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH01˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:01 — page 60 — #60 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 60 Chapter 1 a73 Logical Thinking 19. Consider the following deﬁnition. Deﬁnition. A integer n is frumpable if n 2 +2n isodd. Prove: All frumpable numbersare odd. 20. Recall the Badda-Bing axiomatic system of Example 1.17. Prove: If q and r are distinct bings, both of which are hit by baddas x and y, then x = y. 21. Two common axiomsfor geometry are asfollows. The undeﬁned terms are “point,” “line,” and “ison.” 1. For every pair of points x and y, there isa unique line such that x ison l and y ison l. 2. Given a line l and a point x that isnot on l, there isa unique line m such that x ison m and no point on l isalso on m. Recall that two lines l and m are parallel if there isno point on both l and m. In thiscase we write l bardbl m. Use this deﬁnition along with the above two axiomsto prove the following. Let l, m, and n be distinct lines. If l bardblm and mbardbln, then l bardbln. 22. The following axiomscharacterize projective geometry. The undeﬁned termsare “point,” “line,” and “ison.” 1. For every pair of points x and y, there isa unique line such that x ison l and y ison l. 2. For every pair of lines l and m, there isa point x on both l and m. 3. There are (at least) four distinct points, no three of which are on the same line. Prove the following statements in projective geometry. (a) There are no parallel lines. (b) For every pair of lines l and m, there isexactly one point x on both l and m. (c) There are (at least) four distinct lines such that no point is on three of them.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 61 — #1 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ Chapter 2 Relational Thinking Most quantitative problems involve several diﬀerent interrelated objects: mar- ket forces determine the price of a commodity, steps in a manufacturing process depend on other steps, virus-infected computers can slow network traﬃc. In or- dertoanalyzetheserelationships,ithelpstothinkmathematicallyaboutthem. In this chapter we will explore diﬀerent ways that the elements of a set can be related to each other or to the elements of another set. These relationships can be described by mathematical objects such as functions, relations, and graphs. Our goal is to develop the ability to see mathematical relationships between objects, which in turn will enable us to apply tools from discrete mathematics. Figure 2.1 A computer’s circuit board contains an intricate system of math- ematical relationships. Concepts such as connectivity, interdependence, and modularity can be expressed in the language of mathematics. 61

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 62 — #2 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 62 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking 2.1 Graphs When faced with a diﬃcult problem in mathematics, it often helps to draw a picture. If the problem involves a discrete collection of interrelated objects, it is natural to sketch the objects and draw lines between them to indicate the relationships. A graph is the mathematical version of such a sketch. In this section we will study a few basic deﬁnitions about graphs, and then explore some ways to use graphs to model mathematical relationships. Our approach here will be informal; later in the chapter we will look at graphs from a more rigorous point of view. 2.1.1 Edges and Vertices In Section 2.6, we will give a mathematical deﬁnition of a graph, and we will prove several theorems about graphs. For now, however, just think of a graph informally as a diagram of dots, called vertices, connected by lines or curves, called edges. The edges of a graph may have arrows on them; in this case, the graph is called a directed graph. A graph without arrows on the edges is called an undirected graph. When we draw a graph, it doesn’t really matter where we put the vertices or whether we draw the edges as curved or straight—the thing that matters is whether or not two given vertices are connected by an edge (or edges). Example 2.1 The Pregel River divided the Prussian city of K¨onigsberg (now Kaliningrad, Russia) into four sections, as shown in Figure 2.2. These sections were connected by seven bridges. If we draw a vertex for each land mass and an edge for each bridge, we can represent the city as the following graph. C B D A Notice that there are some double edges; these reﬂect the presence of two bridges connecting the same pair of land masses. The bridges of K¨onigsberg inspired the great eighteenth-century mathe- matician Leonhard Euler to think about the kinds of relationships that graphs express. In March of 1736, Euler wrote the following to a colleague: AproblemwasposedtomeaboutanislandinthecityofK¨onigsberg, surrounded by a river spanned by seven bridges, and I was asked whether someone could traverse the separate bridges in a connected

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 63 — #3 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.1 Graphs 63 C B A D ... Figure 2.2 The bridges of K¨onigsberg. walk in such a way that each bridge is crossed only once. I was in- formed that hitherto no one had demonstrated the possibility of doing this, or shown that it is impossible. This question is so banal, butseemedtomeworthyofattentioninthatgeometry,noralgebra, nor even the art of counting was suﬃcient to solve it. [10] Although Euler did not use modern notation and terminology, his paper on the K¨onigsberg bridges is widely regarded as the start of modern graph theory. [16] 2.1.2 Terminology In order to work with graphs, it helps to deﬁne some terms. The degree of a vertex is the number of times an edge touches it. This is diﬀerent than the number of edges touching it, because an edge may form a loop, as in Figure 2.3. In graph H, vertex x has degree 5. In a directed graph, we can speak of the indegree (the number of edges coming in to the vertex) and the outdegree (the number of edges going out). In Figure 2.3, vertex a of graph G has indegree 1 and outdegree 2. A path in a graph is a sequence v 0 ,e 1 ,v 1 ,e 2 ,v 2 ,...,v n−1 ,e n ,v n of vertices v i and edges e j such that edge e i connects vertices v i−1 and v i . Here n≥1. A circuit is a path that ends where it begins, so v 0 = v n . An undirected graph is connected if there is a path connecting any two pairs of vertices. A directed graph is connected if the underlying undirected graph is. In Figure 2.3, graph H is connected, and therefore so is graph G. There is a circuit in graph H going around the large quadrilateral: start at vertex v, follow the edges clockwise through vertices w, x, and z, and return to vertex v. However, the corresponding sequence is not a circuit in graph G because the edge from a to e goes the wrong direction.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 64 — #4 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 64 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking GH b d ae c x w y vz Figure 2.3 Graph H is the underlying undirected graph of the directed graph G. Why do we need all these terms? One reason is that terminology makes it easier to make precise descriptions of the relationships that graphs deﬁne. Let’s take another look at the bridges of K¨onigsberg. In his 1736 paper, Euler made the following observations (quoted in [16]). 1. The number of bridges written next to the letters A, B, C, etc. together add up to twice the total number of bridges. The reason for this is that, in the calculation where every bridge leading to a given area is counted, each bridge is counted twice, once for each of the two areas which it joins. 2. If there are more than two areas to which an odd number of bridges lead, then such a journey is impossible. 3. If, however, the number of bridges is odd for exactly two areas, then the journey is possible if it starts in either of these two areas. 4. If, ﬁnally, there are no areas to which an odd number of bridges lead, then the required journey can be accomplished starting from any area. We can use modern terminology to restate these observations. Let’s deﬁne an Euler path (resp. circuit) as a path (resp. circuit) that uses every edge of the graph exactly once. 1. In any graph, the sum of the degrees of the vertices equals twice the number of edges. 2. If a graph has more than two vertices of odd degree, it does not have an Euler path. 3. If a connected graph has exactly two vertices, v and w, of odd degree, then there is an Euler path from v to w. 4. If all the vertices of a connected graph have even degree, then the graph has an Euler circuit.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 65 — #5 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.1 Graphs 65 The vertices A, B, C, and D of the graph of Example 2.1 have degrees 3, 5, 3, and 3, respectively. Therefore, (if we trust Euler), this graph does not have an Euler path. Note that we haven’t yet given rigorous proofs for any of Euler’s observations, but we have managed to state them a little more clearly and concisely. 2.1.3 Modeling Relationships with Graphs In addition to the “banal” problem of walking over bridges, there are many other applications of graphs for problems involving relationships. Example 2.2 Acollegeregistrarwouldliketoschedulethefollowingcoursesin as few time slots as possible: Physics, Computer Science, Chemistry, Calculus, Discrete Math, Biology, and Psychology. However, from previous experience, the following pairs of classes always have students in common, so they can’t be scheduled in the same time slot: Physics and Computer Science Physics and Chemistry Calculus and Chemistry Calculus and Physics Calculus and Computer Science Calculus and Discrete Math Calculus and Biology Discrete Math and Computer Science Discrete Math and Biology Psychology and Biology Psychology and Chemistry What is the fewest number of time slots needed to schedule all these classes without conﬂicts? Solution: The natural way to model this problem with a graph is to make each course into a vertex and connect any two vertices that represent courses that cannot be scheduled in the same time slot. Figure 2.4 shows this graph. Physics Chem Psych Calc Bio DM CS Figure 2.4 Graph for Example 2.2.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 66 — #6 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 66 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking Let’s start with Calculus: call its time slot A. None of the courses that share an edge with Calculus can be in time slot A, so pick one, say, Computer Science, and call its time slot B. Now Physics shares edges with both Calculus and Computer Science, so this forces us to use a third time slot, C, for Physics. Weshouldnoteatthispointthatallofourchoiceshavebeenforcedsofar— we are going to need at least three time slots. The question remains whether we need more than three slots. Notice that we can assign Chemistry to slot B (since it doesn’t share an edge with Computer Science) and we can assign Discrete Math to slot C (since it doesn’t conﬂict with Physics). This allows us to use B for Biology and either A or C for Psychology, showing that three time slots are suﬃcient. ♦ This scheduling problem is an example of graph coloring. A coloring for a graph is an assignment of diﬀerent values (colors) to each vertex such that no two vertices of the same color share an edge. In Example 2.2, the “colors” were the time slots A, B, and C. We call a graph planar if it can be written down (on a “planar” sheet of paper) without any edges crossing each other. The graph in Figure 2.4 is an example of a planar graph. The famous Four Color Theorem states that any planar graph can be colored with, at most, four colors. 1 A consequence of the Four Color Theorem is that cartographers need only four colors of ink: it is always possible to color the regions of a planar map (e.g., the states in a map of the United States) with, at most, four colors, so that no two adjacent regions have the same color. Example 2.3 Several departments around campus have wireless access points (WAPs), but problems arise if two WAPs within 200 feet of each other are operating on the same frequency. Suppose the departments with WAPs are situated as follows. Department: Is within 200 feet of departments: Math Physics, Psychology, Chemistry, Sociology Sociology History, English, Economics, Math, Chemistry, Psychology Physics Math, Chemistry Psychology Math, Chemistry, Sociology, Economics History Sociology, English English Economics, Sociology, History Economics English, Sociology, Psychology Chemistry Math, Psychology, Sociology, Physics 1.Althoughthisresultisverysimpletostate,theonlyknownproofstodateareextremely complicated.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 67 — #7 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.1 Graphs 67 Physics (1) Math (2) Chem (3) Soc (4) Psych (1) Econ (2)Hist (1) Eng (3) Figure 2.5 Graph for Example 2.3. Colors/frequencies: 1, 2, 3, 4. What is the fewest number of frequencies needed? How could these frequencies be assigned to departments? Solution: Figure 2.5 shows a graph model for this situation, along with a pos- sible coloring. We leave it as an exercise to check that four colors (frequencies) are needed. ♦ In Example 2.3, we modeled the positions of the departments by draw- ing an edge between any two departments that were “close,” i.e., within 200 yards of each other. If we had more speciﬁc data, we could make our model say how close each department is to the others by putting numbers on each edge indicating the distance between two departments. A graph with numerical val- ues, or weights, on its edges is called a network. Networks can be directed or undirected, depending on what they are intended to model. Example 2.4 The following table lists some pairwise driving distances (in miles) on selected routes between some California cities. B E F L N S Barstow Eureka Fresno 245 450 Los Angeles 115 645 220 Needles 145 385 260 San Diego 175 125 320 Figure 2.6 shows the graph for this network. Writing the distance data in this formatmakesiteasiertoanswercertainquestions.HowfarisitfromSanDiego to Fresno (using these routes)? If we travel from Needles to Fresno via Barstow, how much longer will it take? The above examples show how versatile graph models are; often it helps to add extra structure to a graph (for example, colors or weights) to suit a partic-

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 68 — #8 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 68 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking E L F N S B 450 645 220 245 385 145 115 175125 320 260 Figure 2.6 A network showing mileage between cities. ular application. The next example illustrates another way to add information to a graph model by specifying how the graph is drawn. Example 2.5 The custom dictionary in a spell-checker keeps track of words that you don’t want ﬂagged as misspellings but aren’t in the standard dictio- nary. These words get added one at a time, in no particular order, but it is necessary to keep them organized so that searching the list is easy. Suppose your custom dictionary contains the following words: macchiato, poset, phat, complexify, jazzed, sheaﬁfy, clueless What is an eﬃcient way to organize this data? One possible organizational structure is a graph model called a binary search tree. The rules for constructing a binary search tree are simple. Start with an item (chosen arbitrarily) at the top of the tree. This is the root node of the tree. The root has (at most) two edges touching it, one going down to the right, and one going down to the left. These are the children of the root node. In fact, every node in a binary search tree can have up to two children, one on the right, and one on the left. The only condition is that the right child (along with its “descendants”) must come after its parent in alphabetical (or numerical) order, and the left child and its descendants must come before its parent. For example, in the following tree, x has right child r and left child l, so this data must have the order l,x,r. x lr

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 69 — #9 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.1 Graphs 69 Let’s place the data from Example 2.5 into a binary search tree. Start with “macchiato” at the root of the tree. The next word, “poset,” comes after “mac- chiato” in alphabetical order, so “poset” becomes the right child of “macchi- ato.” We would then place the next word, “phat,” to the right of “macchiato,” but since that spot is taken, and since “phat” precedes “poset” in alphabetical order, we make “phat” the left child of “poset.” We continue in this manner, ﬁnding the new position for each new word by moving down the tree. At each branch we move right or left, depending on where the new word falls in the alphabet. Figure 2.7 shows the ﬁrst few steps of this process, along with the ﬁnal result. The reason this graph is called a “search” tree is that it makes ﬁnding an element in the tree easy. If you are looking for a word in a binary search tree, you go through the same procedure as if you were adding the word to the tree; if you don’t come across the word, it isn’t there. For large data sets, this process goes very quickly, since you don’t need to look at every element. For example, to ﬁnd “poset” in the tree in Figure 2.7, we only have to look at two words. To establish that “iPod” is not in the tree, we only need to check three. Each comparison moves the search one level down the tree, and each level contains twice the number of elements as the level before. jazzed phat sheafify poset poset poset poset complexify complexify clueless phat phat macchiato macchiato macchiato macchiatomacchiato . . . Figure 2.7 Constructing the binary search tree for Example 2.5.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 70 — #10 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 70 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking Figure 2.8 A balanced binary search tree with 255 nodes requires, at most, eight comparisons to search it completely. So, for example, a balanced binary search tree with 255=1+2+4+8+16+32+64+128 elements requires, at most, eight comparisons to search it completely. See Fig- ure 2.8. Note that a binary search tree contains more information than its graph structureconveys.Thebranchesofthetreealwaysgodownward,anditmatters whether they go to the left or to the right. Technically, a binary search tree is a directed graph, with all the edges pointing downward, away from the root. But most books (including this one) omit the arrows. Exercises 2.1 1. Consider the following undirected graph. a e d c b

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 71 — #11 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.1 Graphs 71 (a) How many edges are there in this graph? (b) Give the degree of each vertex. (c) Do these numbers agree with Euler’s ﬁrst observation? 2. Consider the following directed graph. a e d c b (a) Give the indegree of each vertex. (b) Give the outdegree of each vertex. (c) Compute sum of the indegrees and the sum of the outdegrees. What do you notice? 3. Draw a connected, undirected graph with seven vertices and no circuits. How many edges does it have? 4. Draw an undirected graph with six vertices, each of degree 3, such that the graph is ... (a) connected. (b) not connected. 5. A graph is called simple if it has no multiple edges or loops. (The graphs in Figures 2.4, 2.5, and 2.6 are simple, but the graphs in Example 2.1 and Figure 2.3 are not simple.) Draw ﬁve diﬀerent connected, simple, undirected graphs with four vertices. 6. Anundirectedgraphiscalledcomplete ifeveryvertexsharesanedgewith every other vertex. Draw a complete graph on ﬁve vertices. How many edges does it have? 7. Figure 2.9 shows the bridge conﬁguration of modern day Kaliningrad. Represent the four land masses and seven bridges as an undirected graph. Is this graph the same as the one in Example 2.1? Why or why not? Is it possible to travel an Euler circuit on this graph?

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 72 — #12 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 72 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking Figure 2.9 Kaliningrad, Russia. 8. Does the following graph have an Euler path? Why or why not? 9. Think of the Internet as one big graph, where each web page is a vertex and each link is an edge. (a) Is this a directed graph? Why or why not? (b) Is this graph connected? Why or why not? (c) Is this graph complete? Why or why not? (d) Is this graph simple? Why or why not? (e) For a given web page p, what does the outdegree of p represent? (f) For a given web page p, what does the indegree of p represent? 10. Find a map of the United States. Draw a graph whose vertices represent the states of Illinois, Missouri, Tennessee, Virginia, West Virginia, Ohio, Indiana, and Kentucky. Draw an edge between any two vertices whose states share a common border. Explain why it takes four colors to color this graph (and hence also to distinguish these states on a map). 11. As in Exercise 10, draw a graph representing the border relationships for the states of Washington, Oregon, Idaho, California, Nevada, and Utah. What is the fewest number of colors needed to color this graph? Justify your answer.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 73 — #13 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.1 Graphs 73 12. Representthe13regionsinSouthAmerica(12countriesplustheterritory ofFrenchGuiana)asagraph.Whatisthefewestnumberofcolorsneeded to color this graph? 13. Using as few groups as possible, put the words fish, sit, stay, play, diet, tree, duck, dog, and hen into groups such that none of the words in a group have any letters in common. Use a graph model and graph coloring. Justify your answer: explain why your grouping uses the fewest groups possible. 14. Give an example of a graph that requires ﬁve colors to make a valid coloring. (Note that, by the Four Color Theorem, your example cannot be planar.) 15. Compute the minimal number of colors needed to color the following graph. Show that your answer is big enough (by describing a coloring), and explain why the graph cannot be colored in fewer colors. 16. Color the vertices of the following graph so that no vertices of the same color share an edge. Use as few colors as possible. Explain why the graph cannot be colored using fewer colors. Be speciﬁc. 17. Around-robintournamentamongfourteams—Canadiens,Canucks,Flames, andOilers—hasthefollowingresults:CanucksdefeatCanadiens;Canucks defeat Flames; Canucks defeat Oilers; Canadiens defeat Oilers; Flames defeat Canadiens; Oilers defeat Flames. (a) Model these results with a directed graph, where each vertex rep- resents a team and each edge represents a game, pointing from the winner to the loser.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 74 — #14 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 74 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking (b) Find a circuit in this graph. (c) Explain why the existence of a circuit in such a graph makes it hard to rank the teams from best to worst. 18. Consider the network in Example 2.4. Plan a round trip starting and ending at San Diego that visits all the other cities in as few miles as possible. In other words, ﬁnd a circuit that contains every vertex and has minimal weight. 19. Construct a directed network whose vertices represent the numbers 11,12,13,15,17 and whose weights tell how much you must add to get from one vertex to another. Include only edges of positive weight. 20. AcarrentalcompanyhasthreelocationsinMexicoCity:theInternational Airport, Oﬁcina Vallejo, and Downtown. Customers can drop oﬀ their vehiclesatanyoftheselocations.Basedonpriorexperience,thecompany expects that, at the end of each day, 40% of the cars that begin the day at the Airport will end up Downtown, 50% will return to the Airport, and 10% will be at Oﬁcina Vallejo. Similarly, 60% of the Oﬁcina Vallejo cars will end up Downtown, with 30% returning to Oﬁcina Vallejo and 10% to the Airport. Finally, 30% of the Downtown cars will end up at each of the other locations, with 40% staying at the Downtown location. Model this situation with a directed network. If the company starts with all of its cars at the Airport, how will the cars be distributed after two days of rentals? 21. Consider the following list of numbers. 123,684,121,511,602,50,43 (a) Place the numbers, in the order given, into a binary search tree. (b) The height of a binary search tree is the maximum number of edges you have to go through to reach the bottom of the tree, starting at the root. What is the height of the tree in part (a)? (c) Reorder the numbers so that when they are put into a binary search tree,theheightoftheresultingtreeislessthantheheightofthetree in part (a). Give both your new list and the search tree it produces. 22. Put the words Cheddar Swiss Brie Panela Stilton Mozzarella Gouda into a binary search tree with the smallest height possible.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 75 — #15 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.2 Sets 75 23. Put the following words into a binary search tree. Add them to the tree in the order given. i will not eat them with a fox 24. Sociologists use graphs to model social relationships. A social network (not to be confused with a network) is a graph where the nodes represent “actors” (e.g., people, companies) and the edges represent relationships, or “ties,” between actors (e.g., friendships, business partnerships). Con- sider the social network in Figure 2.10. A BC D E I G FH Figure 2.10 Social network for Exercise 24. (a) A clique in a social network is a group of actors who all have ties to each other. What is the largest clique in the social network in Figure 2.10? (b) If you had to choose the most important actor in this social network, who would you pick? Why? (c) Suppose the actors represent people and the ties represent acquain- tances.Ifthepeopleinthissocialnetworkcontinuetointeract,which two (currently unacquainted) actors would you most expect to be- come acquainted? Which two actors are the least likely to become acquainted? Why? 2.2 Sets The applications from the previous section should convince you that graphs are a powerful mathematical tool. However, our viewpoint wasn’t very rigorous; in order to prove useful theorems about graphs, we need to consider some more mathematical structures that describe relationships.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 76 — #16 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 76 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking Thesimplestwaytodescribeacollectionofrelatedobjectsisasaset.Think of the set S as a container where an object x is something that S contains. S x We write x ∈ S to denote that x is contained in S. We also say that “x is a member of S,” “x is an element of S,” or more simply, “x is in S.” 2.2.1 Membership and Containment We can describe examples of sets by listing the elements in the set or by de- scribing the properties that an element in the set has. To say that set S consists of the elements x 1 ,x 2 ,...,x n , we write S ={x 1 ,x 2 ,...,x n }. Suppose there is some property p that some of the elements of a set S have. We can describe the set of all elements of S that have property p as {x∈S |x has property p}. This is sometimes called “set builder” notation, because it explains how to build a list of all the elements of a set. Example 2.6 Let A ={1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8}. Then 2∈A and 9negationslash∈A.If B ={x∈A|x is odd}, then the elements of B are 1,3,5,7. Example 2.7 There are some common sets that have speciﬁc names. The set of integers is denoted by Z, and the set of positive integers, or natural numbers is written as N. Note that 0 ∈ Z, but 0 negationslash∈ N. We use R for the set of real numbers, and Q for the set of rational numbers. 2 Example 2.8 Let P be the set of all polygons. So P contains all triangles, squares, pentagons, etc. If c is a circle, then cnegationslash∈P. We could describe the set H of all hexagons in set builder notation as H ={x∈P |x has six sides}. 2.Recallthatarationalnumberisanumberthatcanbewrittenasafraction a/b,where a and b areintegers.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 77 — #17 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.2 Sets 77 The language of sets is convenient for describing groups of objects that are related by some common property. Often some property implies another; for example, all integers are real numbers. In terms of sets, this means that the set Z is contained in the set R. In general, the predicate logic statement that (∀x)(x∈A→x∈B) (2.2.1) is written as A ⊆ B, and we say “A is contained in B,” or “A is a subset of B,” or “B contains A.” We can express this relationship pictorially using the following Venn diagram. B A Example 2.9 In Example 2.6, B ⊆A. We have noted that Z⊆R in Exam- ple 2.7, and we could also say that N⊆Z, Z⊆Q, and Q⊆R. This chain of relationships could also be written as N⊆Z⊆Q⊆R. Example 2.10 In Example 2.8, H ⊆P, but P negationslash⊆H, because not every poly- gon is a hexagon. Example 2.11 Theempty set∅isthesetthatcontainsnoelements.Therefore, the empty set is a subset of any set, that is, ∅⊆X for all X. This is because the statement x∈∅is false for any x, so the implication (∀x)(x∈∅→x∈X) must be true. (See the truth table for the “→” connective on page 6.) 2.2.2 New Sets from Old Sets describe relationships, but the language of sets can also describe the logic of how things are related. We have seen one example of this already: state- ment 2.2.1 shows how to interpret the ⊆ symbol in terms of a predicate logic statementcontainingthe→connective;therelationshipofcontainmenthasthe logic of an implication. The connectives∨,∧,¬, and↔also have set-theoretic counterparts. The union A∪B of two sets A and B is the set containing all the elements of both A and B put together. An element is in the union of two sets A and B if the element is A,orB, or both. In set builder notation, A∪B ={x|(x∈A)∨(x∈B)}.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 78 — #18 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 78 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking This translates to the following equivalence rule in predicate logic. (∀x)[x∈A∪B ⇔(x∈A)∨(x∈B)] The statement x ∈ A∪B is logically equivalent to the statement (x ∈ A)∨ (x ∈ B). This fact is important when writing proofs; one of these statements can always be replaced by the other. Think of “union” as the set-theoretic counterpart of the logical “or.” In the following Venn diagram, A∪B is the shaded area: BA The intersection A∩B is the set containing all the elements that A and B have in common. In order for an element to be in the intersection of A and B, the element must be in both sets. Therefore we write the intersection as A∩B ={x|(x∈A)∧(x∈B)} in set builder notation. This implies the following logical equivalence for all x. x∈A∩B ⇔(x∈A)∧(x∈B) In the following Venn diagram, the shaded area represents A∩B: BA Implicit in the above predicate logic statements is a domain, or universal set U, of which every set is a subset. If we know what the domain U is, we can speak of the complement A prime of A, which is the set A prime ={x∈U |xnegationslash∈A}. We usually draw U as a big rectangle, so the shaded area below represents A prime . U A

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 79 — #19 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.2 Sets 79 Note that we could also write A prime ={x∈U |¬(x∈A)} to make the use of the ¬ connective explicit. We say that two sets are equal if they have the same elements. So the statement “A = B” translates to the following statement in predicate logic: (∀x)(x∈A↔x∈B). This translation is important when it comes to proving that two sets are equal. A proof that A = B usually consists of two direct proofs: given x ∈ A, prove that x ∈ B, and conversely, given x ∈ B, prove that x ∈ A. In other words, showing A = B amounts to showing that A⊆B and B ⊆A. Example 2.12 Let the following sets be given. X ={n∈Z|n =2k for some odd integer k} F ={n∈Z|n =4k for some integer k} E ={n∈Z|n is even} 1. Prove that F ⊆E. 2. Prove that X = E∩F prime . Proof of 1 Let x∈F. By the deﬁnition of F, x =4k for some integer k.We can write this equation as x = 2(2k), so x is even by Deﬁnition 1.5. Therefore x∈E. square Proof of 2 (We ﬁrst show that X ⊆ E∩F prime .) Let x ∈ X. Then x =2k for some odd integer k,sox is even. Therefore x ∈ E. Suppose, to the contrary, that x ∈ F. Then x =4j for some integer j. This implies that 2k =4j,or k =2j, which contradicts that k is odd. Therefore x ∈ F prime . Since x ∈ E and x∈F prime , we have shown that x∈E∩F prime . (We now show that E∩F prime ⊆X.) Suppose x∈E∩F prime ,sox∈E and x∈F prime . Since x ∈ E, x =2k for some integer k. Suppose, to the contrary, that k is even. Then k =2l for some integer l,sox = 2(2l)=4l. But this contradicts that x∈F prime . Therefore k must be odd. This establishes that x∈X. square These proofs illustrate how to translate back and forth between the lan- guageofsetsandthelanguageoflogic.Forexample,thestatement“x∈E∩F prime ” was translated as “x∈E and x∈F prime .” In general, any statement involving sets and the symbols ∩, ∪, ⊆,=,and prime translates into a logical statement using the connectives ∧, ∨, →, ↔, and ¬, respectively. So all the work we did in propositional and predicate logic (Sections 1.2 and 1.3) will now pay oﬀ when dealing with sets.

Unknown

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 80 — #20 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 80 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking Think of the symbols ∩, ∪, ⊆,=,and prime as tools for making new sets from old ones. For example, given two sets, A and B, we can build a new set, A∩B, consisting of all the elements the two sets have have in common. We can also take two sets A and B and form their Cartesian product A×B. The Cartesian product is just the set of all ordered pairs where the ﬁrst item comes from the ﬁrst set and the second item comes from the second set. Formally, A×B ={(a,b)|a∈A and b∈B}. We can also have ordered triples, quadruples, and so on. The set A 1 ×A 2 ×···×A n ={(a 1 ,a 2 ,...,a n )|a i ∈A i } is the set of ordered n-tuples where the ith item comes from set A i . Two ordered pairs are equal if and only if their corresponding parts are equal. In other words, (a,b)=(c,d) ⇔ a = c and b = d. You are already quite familiar with the Cartesian product R×R, the set of all ordered pairs of real numbers. This set is the usual Cartesian plane from high school algebra. One last construction that is sometimes useful is the power set P(S)ofthe set S. The power set of S is the set of all subsets of S: P(S)={X |X ⊆S}. Note that the empty set ∅ is a member of P(S), no matter what S is, because the empty set is a subset of any set. Example 2.13 Suppose you want to form a study group with some of the other students in your class. If S is the set of all students in your class, then P(S) is the set of all possible study groups you could form. (The empty set would represent the decision not to form a study group at all!) Example 2.14 Let A ={1,2,3,4,5}, B ={4,5,6,7,8}, and suppose the uni- versal set is U ={1,2,...10}. Then A∪B ={1,2,...,8} A∩B ={4,5} B prime ={1,2,3,9,10} (A∩B)×A ={(4,1),(4,2),(4,3),(4,4),(4,5),(5,1),(5,2),(5,3),(5,4),(5,5)} P(A∩B)={∅,{4},{5},{4,5}} Notice that, while A and B are sets of numbers, the sets you construct from A and B may have diﬀerent kinds of elements. For example, (A∩B)×A is a set of ordered pairs, and P(A∩B) is a set of sets.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 81 — #21 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.2 Sets 81 2.2.3 Identities Since there is such a direct relationship between logic and set theory, we can write down many facts about sets that follow immediately from things we know from our study of logic. For example, the addition inference rule p⇒p∨q allows us to prove the identity A⊆A∪B in set theory. Proof that A⊆A∪B Let x∈A. By the addition rule, (x∈A)∨(x∈B). By the deﬁnition of set union, x∈A∪B, as required. square De Morgan’s laws for sets follow from the equivalence rule of the same name. Theorem 2.1 Let A and B be sets. Then 1. (A∪B) prime = A prime ∩B prime 2. (A∩B) prime = A prime ∪B prime The proof of this theorem illustrates how to prove set equalities. Proof We will prove part 1. (Part 2 is similar.) Let x ∈ (A∪B) prime . In other words, if P(x) is the statement “x ∈ A” and Q(x) is the statement “x ∈ B,” we are starting with the assumption¬(P(x)∨Q(x)). By De Morgan’s laws for propositional logic, this is equivalent to¬P(x)∧¬Q(x), which, in the language of set theory, is the same as x∈A prime ∩B prime . We have shown that x∈(A∪B) prime ⇔ x∈A prime ∩B prime , hence the sets (A∪B) prime and A prime ∩B prime are equal. square Take a look back at this proof, and notice two things. First, the proof establishes an “if and only if” claim, since all of its deductions are based on logical equivalences. Second, the proof illustrates that the way to show an equality U = V of sets is to show that x∈U ⇔x∈V. The proof of Theorem 2.1 consists of a simple chain of equivalences. When the structure of a proof is this basic, we might opt to write it in the following format.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 82 — #22 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 82 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking Proof of Theorem 2.1, “⇔” version We will prove part 1. (Part 2 is similar.) x∈(A∪B) prime ⇔¬(x∈A∪B) Deﬁnition of prime ⇔¬[(x∈A)∨(x∈B)] Deﬁnition of ∪ ⇔¬(x∈A)∧¬(x∈B) De Morgan’s law (logic) ⇔ (x∈A prime )∧(x∈B prime ) Deﬁnition of prime ⇔ x∈A prime ∩B prime Deﬁnition of ∩ Therefore the sets (A∪B) prime and A prime ∩B prime are equal. square Proofs of identities can often be written in this format. Notice that each “⇔” is justiﬁed by a reason in the rightmost column. Sets that contain a ﬁnite number of elements are called ﬁnite sets.Itis convenient to denote the number of elements in a ﬁnite set S by |S|. For ex- ample, if S is the set containing all the members of the Unites States House of Representatives, then |S|= 435. One handy rule dealing with set sizes is the inclusion–exclusion principle. |A∪B|=|A|+|B|−|A∩B| (2.2.2) It is easy to see why this rule must hold by looking at the Venn diagrams for A∪B and A∩B at the beginning of Section 2.2.2. Counting the elements of A∪B by counting the elements in A and B and adding would double-count the elements that lie in A∩B. This is the reason for the “ −|A∩B|” on the right-hand side of Equation 2.2.2. This equation can help organize counting problems involving sets that overlap. Example 2.15 The Masters of the Universe Society at a certain college ac- cepts members who have 1600 SAT scores or 4.0 GPA scores in high school. Of the 11 members of the society, 8 had 1600 SAT scores, and 5 had 4.0 GPA scores. How many members had both 1600 SAT scores and 4.0 GPA scores? Solution: Let A be the set of members with 1600 SAT scores, and let B be the set of members with 4.0 GPA scores. Then A∩B is the set of members with both. By the inclusion–exclusion principle (Equation 2.2.2), 11=8+5−|A∩B| so there are two members with both 1600 SAT scores and 4.0 GPA scores. ♦ Wewillapplytheinclusion–exclusionprincipletohardercountingproblems in Chapter 4.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 83 — #23 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.2 Sets 83 Exercises 2.2 1. DrawVenndiagramstoillustrateDeMorgan’slawsforsets(Theorem2.1). 2. Draw a Venn diagram to show the region A∩B prime . This region is also denoted A\B, and is called the set diﬀerence, for obvious reasons. 3. Let A = {2,3,4}, B = {3,4,5,6}, and suppose the universal set is U = {1,2,...,9}. List all the elements in the following sets. (a) (A∪B) prime (b) (A∩B)×A (c) P(B\A) 4. Let the following sets be given. G = the set of all good citizens. C = the set of all charitable people. P = the set of all polite people. Write the statement, “Everyone who is charitable and polite is a good citizen,” in the language of set theory. 5. Consider the following sets. The universal set for this problem is N. A = The set of all even numbers. B = The set of all prime numbers. C = The set of all perfect squares. D = The set of all multiples of 10. Usingonlythesymbols3,A,B,C,D,N,∈,⊆,=,negationslash=,∩,∪,×, prime ,∅,(, ),write the following statements in set notation. (a) None of the perfect squares are prime numbers. (b) All multiples of 10 are even numbers. (c) The number 3 is a prime number that is not even. (d) If you take all the prime numbers, all the even numbers, all the perfect squares, and all the multiples of 10, you still won’t have all the natural numbers.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 84 — #24 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 84 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking 6. Consider the following sets. The universal set U for this problem is the set of all residents of India. A = the set of all English speakers. B = the set of all Hindi speakers. C = the set of all Urdu speakers. Express the following sets in the symbols of set theory. (a) Residents of India who speak English, Hindi, and Urdu. (b) Residents of India who do not speak English, Hindi, or Urdu. (c) Residents of India who speak English, but not Hindi or Urdu. 7. Consider the following sets. The universal set for this problem is the set of all quadrilaterals. A = The set of all parallelograms. B = The set of all rhombuses. C = The set of all rectangles. D = The set of all trapezoids. Using only the symbols x,A,B,C,D,∈,⊆,=,negationslash=,∩,∪,×, prime ,∅,(,), write the following statements in set notation. (a) The polygon x is a parallelogram, but it isn’t a rhombus. (b) There are other quadrilaterals besides parallelograms and trape- zoids. (c) Both rectangles and rhombuses are types of parallelograms. 8. Two sets are called disjoint if they have no elements in common, i.e., if their intersection is the empty set. Prove that ﬁnite sets A and B are disjoint if and only if|A|+|B|=|A∪B|. Use the deﬁnition of∅and the inclusion–exclusion principle (Equation 2.2.2) in your proof. 9. In a class of 40 students, everyone has either a pierced nose or a pierced ear. The professor asks everyone with a pierced nose to raise their hands. Nine hands go up. Then the professor asked everyone with a pierced ear to do likewise. This time there are 34 hands raised. How many students have piercings both on their ears and their noses? 10. How many integers in the set {n ∈ Z | 1 ≤ n ≤ 700} are divisible by 2or7?

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 85 — #25 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.2 Sets 85 11. Let A, B, and C be sets, and let X = A∪B. (a) Write |X∩C| in terms of |A∩C|, |B∩C|, and |A∩B∩C|. Hint: In the following Venn diagram, X∩C is the shaded area. AB C (b) Write |A∪B∪C| in terms of A, B, C, |A∩B|, |A∩C|, |B∩C|, and|A∩B∩C|. (The result is the inclusion–exclusion principle for three sets.) 12. How many integers in the set{n∈Z|1≤n≤700}are divisible by 2, 5, or 7? 13. Let S ={a,b,c}. Write down all the elements in the following sets. (a) S×S (b) P(S) 14. An integer solution to the equation 3x +4=7y is an ordered pair of integers (x,y) that satisﬁes the equation. For example, (1,1) is one such solution. Write the set of all integer solutions to the equation 3x+4=7y in set builder notation. 15. Use Deﬁnition 1.6 to write the set of odd integers in set builder notation. 16. List all the elements of P(P({1})). 17. Prove part 2 of Theorem 2.1. 18. Give a direct proof that for any set S,(S prime ) prime = S. (Hint: Follow the format of the proof of Theorem 2.1. You need to show that x∈(S prime ) prime ⇔x∈S for all x in S. Translate this statement into a statement in predicate logic, and use an equivalence rule from Section 1.2.)

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 86 — #26 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 86 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking 19. Let E be the set of all even integers, and let O be the set of all odd integers. (a) Explain why E∪O⊆Z. (b) Explain why Z⊆E∪O. 20. Let X, Y, and Z be sets. Use the distributive property from propositional logic (Exercise 14 in Section 1.1) to prove that X∩(Y ∪Z)=(X∩Y)∪(X∩Z). 21. Let A and B be sets. Prove that A∩B ⊆A∪B. 22. Let X be a ﬁnite set with |X|> 1. What is the diﬀerence between P 1 = X×X and P 2 ={S ∈P(X)||S|=2}? Which set, P 1 or P 2 , has more elements? 23. Draw an undirected graph G with the following properties. The vertices ofGcorrespondtotheelementsofP({0,1}).Twovertices(corresponding to A,B ∈P({0,1})) are connected by an edge if and only if A∩B =∅. 24. Repeat Exercise 23 using P({0,1,2}) instead of P({0,1}). 25. LetX beanyﬁniteset.ConsiderthegraphGdescribedinExercise23,re- placingP({0,1}) withP(X). Explain why G must be a connected graph. 2.3 Functions You have probably seen functions before. For example, in high school algebra, you learned how to graph functions like f(x)=x 2 −3x+2 (2.3.3) and do various calculations. But this is a very speciﬁc kind of function; in this section we will look at functions from a more general perspective, using the language of sets. Like sets, functions describe mathematical relationships. In this type of relationship, the value of one object is completely determined by the value of another. In Equation 2.3.3, the value of f(x) is forced if we know x’s value.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 87 — #27 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.3 Functions 87 2.3.1 Deﬁnition and Examples Deﬁnition 2.1 A function from a set X to a set Y is a well-deﬁned rule that assigns a single element of Y to every element of X.Iff is such a function, we write f: X −→ Y and we denote the element of Y assigned to x∈X by f(x). The set X is called the domain of the function, and the set Y is called the codomain. Example 2.16 Let X = {1,2,3} and Y = {1,2,3,4}. The formula f(x)= x+1 deﬁnes a function f: X −→ Y. For this function, f(1) = 2, f(2) = 3 and f(3) = 4. Figure 2.11 shows one way to represent this function graphically. X Y 11 2 2 3 3 4 Figure 2.11 The function f maps each element of X to an element of Y. Example 2.17 Theformulaf(x)=x 2 −3x+2deﬁnesafunctionf: R−→ R. Example 2.18 Let W be the set of all words in this book, and let L be the set of all letters in the alphabet. Deﬁne a function f: W −→ L by setting f(w) equal to the ﬁrst letter in the word w. Notice that the choice of word w completely determines f(w), the ﬁrst letter in the word. Example 2.19 A propositional statement in two variables deﬁnes a function w: {T,F}×{T,F}−→{T,F} wherew(A,B)isthetruthvalueofthestatementwhenthevariableshavetruth values A and B. For example, the statement A∨B deﬁnes a function whose values are given by the following table. A B w(A,B) T T T T F T F T T F F F

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 88 — #28 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 88 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking Example 2.20 Let F be the set of all nonempty ﬁnite sets of integers, so F ⊆P(Z). Deﬁne a function s: F −→ Z by setting s(X) to be the sum of all the elements of X. For example, s({1,2,3})=6. Anotherwordforfunctionismap.Thisreﬂectsthethinkingthatafunction is a way of describing a route from one set to another. In Example 2.20, we are describing a way to get from a ﬁnite set of integers to a particular integer, i.e., we are describing a map from the set of all ﬁnite sets of integers to the set of integers. This function maps the set {1,2,3} to the integer 6. Wecanrepresentafunctionbyagraph.Theverticesofthegraphrepresent the elements of the domain and codomain of the function. For each element in the domain, there is a directed edge to some element in the codomain. Example 2.21 Let N = {−2,−1,0,1,2}. Deﬁne a function s: N −→ N by s(n)=n 2 −2. Represent this function with a directed graph. Solution: Since the domain and codomain are the same set, we can represent the function with just ﬁve vertices: –1 –2 1 0 2 However, it is often more useful to represent the domain separately from the codomain. And following the s: N −→ N notation, we put the vertices for the domain on the left and the vertices for the codomain on the right. –2 –1 0 1 2 –2 –1 0 1 2 ♦ Notice that the deﬁnition of a function restricts the features of the graph. Every vertex representing an element of the domain must have outdegree 1. As an exercise, think about what a graph representing the following function would look like.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 89 — #29 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.3 Functions 89 Example 2.22 Let X be a set. Then the identity function 1 X : X −→ X is deﬁned by 1 X (x)=x. The f(x) notation suggests the most important aspect of the deﬁnition of function: the value of the function is completely determined by the object you “plug in” to the function. More precisely, the condition that a function must be well deﬁned means that f(x) has a value for every x in the domain, and a = b ⇒ f(a)=f(b) for any a and b in the domain. A proposed function f: X −→ Y can fail to be well deﬁned in two ways: (1) some x in the domain X can fail to have a y in the codomain to which to map, or (2) some x in the domain can be mapped (ambiguously) to two diﬀerent y’s in the codomain. Example 2.23 Let P be the set of all people (alive or dead). Let m: P −→ P be such that m(x) is the birth mother of x. We have to make some reasonable biological assumptions to regard this as a well-deﬁned function: everybody has a birth mother (e.g., no clones) and no person can have two diﬀerent birth mothers. Think of functions as tools for describing relationships between the ele- ments of a set, or the elements of two diﬀerent sets. In our list of functions above, Example 2.23 describes the maternal relationships of all people (alive or dead), while Example 2.20 shows how to describe sets of integers with inte- gers. Example 2.22 is rather trivial and describes a trivial relationship that the elements of any set have. It might seem obvious that functions given by formulas are always well deﬁned, but diﬃculties can arise if there is more than one way to write the same element of the domain, as in the following example. Example 2.24 LetQ ={x/y|x,y∈Z,ynegationslash=0}bethesetofrationalnumbers. Set f(x/y)=x+y for any x/y∈Q. Does this yield a well-deﬁned function f: Q−→ Z?

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 90 — #30 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 90 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking Solution: No. As a counterexample, note that 2/3=4/6, but f(2/3)=2+3=5negationslash= f(4/6)=4+6=10, so f is not well deﬁned. ♦ When deﬁning a function on a domain like this, it is wise to check that your function is well deﬁned. Example 2.25 Show that the function f: Q−→ Q deﬁned by f(x/y)= x+y y is well deﬁned. Proof Let a/b = c/d∈Q. Then f(a/b)= a+b b = a b + b b = c d + d d = c+d d = f(c/d) so f is well deﬁned. square 2.3.2 One-to-One and Onto Functions Just as it is useful to describe diﬀerent properties that relationships have, it is useful to name certain properties of functions. Deﬁnition 2.2 A function f: X −→ Y is injective (or one-to-one) if, for all a and b in X, f(a)=f(b) implies that a = b. In this case we say that f is a one-to-one mapping from X to Y. Deﬁnition 2.3 A function f: X −→ Y is surjective (or onto) if, for all y∈Y, there exists an x∈X such that f(x)=y. In this case we say that f maps X onto Y.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 91 — #31 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.3 Functions 91 X Y f Figure 2.12 A one-to-one function maps each element of X to a diﬀerent element of Y. X Yf Figure 2.13 An onto function maps something onto each element of Y. Fromthispointon,wewillusethelessformaltermsone-to-one andonto to describeinjectiveandsurjectivefunctions. 3 ThegraphsinFigures2.12and2.13 illustrate why these terms are appropriate. A one-to-one function will always map diﬀerent elements of the domain to diﬀerent elements of the codomain. In other words, at most, one element of the domain maps to any one element of the codomain. In terms of graph theory, the indegree of every vertex in the codomain is, at most, 1. We use the term image to describe the set of all values a function can take. An onto function has every element of the codomain in its image. Figure 2.13 illustrates an onto function. Notice that the domain gets mapped onto the entire codomain. In the graph of an onto function, the indegree of every vertex in the codomain is at least 1. Remember(Section1.4.1)howdeﬁnitionsareusedinmathematics:inorder to prove a function is one-to-one or onto, we almost always have to use the deﬁnition. Example 2.26 Prove that the function f: Z−→ Z deﬁned by f(x)=2x+1 is one-to-one. 3.Notethatwearenowusingtheword“onto”asanadjective,aswellasapreposition.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 92 — #32 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 92 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking Proof Let a,b∈Z and suppose f(a)=f(b). Then 2a+1=2b+1 2a =2b a = b We have shown that f(a)=f(b) implies that a = b, i.e., that f is one-to-one. square Letfloorleftxfloorrightdenote the greatest integer less than or equal to x. So, for example, floorleft4.3floorright =4,floorleft−2.1floorright = −3, and floorleft17floorright = 17. The function that maps x to floorleftxfloorright is called the ﬂoor function. Example 2.27 Let f: R−→ Z be deﬁned by f(x)=floorleftxfloorright. Prove that f maps R onto Z. Proof Let n∈Z. Then, since Z⊆R, n∈R as well. But since n is an integer, floorleftnfloorright= n. Therefore f(n)=n. square The proofs in the last two examples are standard. To prove a function f is one-to-one, suppose f(a)=f(b) and show a = b. To show that a function f is onto, let y be some element of the codomain, and ﬁnd some x in the domain such that f(x)=y. To prove that a function is not one-to-one or onto, look for a counterex- ample. The function in Example 2.26 is not onto because, for example, 38∈Z, but there is no integer x such that 2x+1 = 38. Likewise, the function in Ex- ample 2.27 is not one-to-one because floorleft9.3floorright = floorleft9.8floorright, but 9.3 negationslash=9.8. Note that these two examples show that one-to-one is not the same as onto. Of course, it is possible for a function to be both one-to-one and onto; the identity function of Example 2.22 is one example. Such a function is called a one-to-one correspondence,ormoreformally,abijection.Comparethefollowing example to Example 2.26. Example 2.28 Prove that the function f: R−→ R deﬁned by f(x)=2x+1 is a one-to-one correspondence. Proof We need to show that f is both one-to-one and onto. The proof that it is one-to-one is exactly the same as in Example 2.26. To prove that f is onto,

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 93 — #33 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.3 Functions 93 let y∈R be any real number. Set x =(y−1)/2. Then x∈R and f(x)=f((y−1)/2) = 2[(y−1)/2]+1 = y−1+1 = y Thus f is onto as well. square Example 2.29 Let E ={n ∈Z| n is even} and let O ={n ∈Z| n is odd}. Deﬁne a function f: E×O−→ Z by f(x,y)=x+y.Isf one-to-one and/or onto? Prove or disprove. Solution: We ﬁrst show that f is not onto. Suppose, to the contrary, that f is onto. Since 2 ∈ Z is an element of the codomain, there is some ordered pair (x,y)∈E×O such that f(x,y)=x+y =2. But since x is even and y is odd, x+y is odd, by Exercise 9 of Section 1.5. This contradicts that 2 is even. We next show that f is not one-to-one. Notice that f(4,−3) = 1 = f(6,−5) but (4,−3)negationslash=(6,−5). This counterexample shows that f is not one-to-one. ♦ Example 2.30 Let P be a set of n points lying on a circle. Draw lines con- necting every point to every other point. Suppose that the points are arranged so that no three of these lines intersect in a single point inside the circle. (Fig- ure 2.14 shows a possible conﬁguration.) Let X be the set of all points of intersection of the lines in the interior of the circle (note that the points in P are not included in X). Let Y be the set of all sets of four of the points on the circle, that is, Y ={{A,B,C,D}⊆P |A,B,C,D are all distinct}. Describe a one-to-one correspondence f: X −→ Y. Show that your function is both one-to-one and onto. Solution: Let H ∈ X be a point of intersection. Then H lies on exactly two lines, so we can deﬁne f(H) to be the set containing the four distinct endpoints of these two lines.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 94 — #34 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 94 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking Figure 2.14 A possible conﬁguration of points for Example 2.30 with n =8. We prove that f is one-to-one by contraposition. Suppose H and K are two distinct points of intersection, so H negationslash= K.Ifl 1 and l 2 are the two lines intersecting at H, then at least one of the lines intersecting at K must be diﬀerent from l 1 and l 2 , since two lines can intersect in at most one point. Call this third line l 3 . Then f(K) contains the endpoints of l 3 , but f(H) does not. Hence, f(K)negationslash= f(H). To show that f is onto, let {A,B,C,D}⊆P. Without loss of generality, we can relabel these points (if necessary) so that A,B,C,D are in order as you travel clockwise around the circle. Let l 1 be the line through A and C, and let l 2 be the line through B and D. Since B is on the arc going clockwise from A to C, and D is on the arc going counterclockwise from A to C, line l 1 separates B and D, so lines l 1 and l 2 intersect. Call this point of intersection H. Then f(H)={A,B,C,D}, as required. ♦ Think of a one-to-one correspondence f: X −→ Y as a way to assign every element of X to a unique element of Y, and vice versa. We sometimes write X ←→ Y toemphasizethesymmetryoftherelationshipthataone-to-onecorrespondence deﬁnes. Every element of one set has a unique partner in the other set. 2.3.3 New Functions from Old There are some common ways to make new functions out of old ones. One such construction is the composition of two functions. If f: X −→ Y and g: Y −→ Z,theng◦f isafunctionfromX toZ deﬁnedby(g◦f)(x)=g(f(x)). Example 2.31 Let f: R−→ Rbe deﬁned by f(x)=floorleftxfloorright, and let g: R−→ R be deﬁned by g(x)=3x. Then (g◦f)(2.4) = g(f(2.4)) = g(2) =6

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 95 — #35 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.3 Functions 95 and (f ◦g)(2.4) = f(g(2.4)) = f(7.2) =7 This example shows that f ◦g can be diﬀerent from g◦f. And note one potentially confusing thing about the notation: In the composition g◦f,wedo f ﬁrst, and then apply g to the result. Order matters, in general. Sometimes we would like to be able to “undo” a function, so that it maps back to where it came from. If f: X −→ Y is a function, then the inverse of f is the function f −1 : Y −→ X that has the property that f −1 ◦f =1 X and f ◦f −1 =1 Y . Not all functions have inverses. If f: X −→ Y has an inverse, then, for any y ∈ Y, f(f −1 (y)) = y,sof must map X onto Y. In addition, if f(a)=f(b), then we can apply f −1 to both sides of this equation to get a = b,sof must be one-to-one also. So we see that if a function has an inverse, it must be a one-to-one correspondence. Conversely, we can construct the inverse of any one-to-one correspondence f: X −→ Y by taking f −1 (y) to be the unique element of X that maps onto y. We know such an element exists, because f is onto, and we know this element is unique, since f is one-to-one. This is the only choice we have for f −1 ; see Exercise 24. Example 2.32 If f: R −→ {y ∈ R | y>0} is the function f(x)=2 x , then the inverse of f is given by f −1 (x) = log 2 x. In this last example, we could have deﬁned f(x)=2 x as a function from R to R, but then it wouldn’t be invertible because it wouldn’t be onto. One ﬁnal way to construct functions is by restriction.Iff: X −→ Y is some function, and H ⊆X, then the restriction of f to H is the function f| H : H −→ Y deﬁned by taking f| H (x)=f(x). In other words, we just restrict the domain to a smaller set, and use the same rule that assigns an element of the codomain to each element of this smaller domain. Why bother? Sometimes the new, re- stricted function is simpler to describe, or has other desirable properties. Example 2.33 Let D be the unit disk in R 2 , that is, D ={(x,y)∈R 2 |x 2 +y 2 ≤1}

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 96 — #36 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 96 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking and let D ∗ = D\{(0,0)}. Let S 1 = {(x,y) ∈ R 2 | x 2 +y 2 =1} be the unit circle. Deﬁne a function p: D ∗ −→ S 1 by projecting straight out along a radius until you reach the boundary of the disk. See the following picture. (x, y) p (x, y) Getting a formula for p might be a little messy, but things can be cleaner if we consider a restriction. Let H be the circle of radius 1 2 : H ={(x,y)∈R 2 |x 2 +y 2 = 1 4 } We’ll leave it as an exercise to show that p| H (x,y)=(2x,2y). Exercises 2.3 1. Let X be a set with four elements. Represent the identity function 1 X of Example 2.22 with a directed graph in two diﬀerent ways: (a) with four vertices, each representing an element in both the domain and the codomain. (b) with eight vertices, four for the domain and four for the codomain. 2. See Deﬁnitions 2.2 and 2.3. Write the deﬁnitions of one-to-one and onto in terms of predicate logic. 3. Show that the function of Example 2.20 is not one-to-one. 4. Show that the function of Example 2.20 is onto.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 97 — #37 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.3 Functions 97 5. Several languages are spoken in India; let L be the set of all such lan- guages, and let U be the set of all residents of India. Explain why the proposed function f: U −→ L deﬁned by f(u) = the language that u speaks is not well deﬁned. 6. Let P be a set of people, and let Q be a set of occupations. Deﬁne a function f: P −→ Q by setting f(p) equal to p’s occupation. What must be true about the people in P for f to be a well-deﬁned function? 7. Is the function of Example 2.23 onto? Why or why not? Is it one-to-one? Why or why not? 8. Consider Example 2.23. Let y be some person. What is the relationship of (m◦m)(y)toy? 9. Is the function depicted in Figure 2.12 onto? Why or why not? 10. Is the function depicted in Figure 2.13 one-to-one? Why or why not? 11. Explain why the proof in Example 2.28 could not be used to prove that the function in Example 2.26 is onto. 12. Consider the situation of Example 2.30. Describe a diﬀerent one-to-one correspondence g: Y −→ X. Show that your function is both one-to-one and onto. 13. Consider the negation function n: {T,F}−→{T,F}given by n(x)=¬x. Is n a one-to-one correspondence? What is n −1 ? 14. Deﬁne a function f: Z−→ Z×Z by f(x)=(2x+3,x−4). (a) Is f one-to-one? Prove or disprove. (b) Does f map Z onto Z×Z? Prove or disprove. 15. Deﬁne a map t: R×R−→ R×R by t(a,b)=(a+b,a−b). Prove that t is a one-to-one correspondence. 16. Let X be a set. Deﬁne a map d: X −→ X×X by d(x)=(x,x). (a) Is d one-to-one? Prove or disprove. (b) Is d onto? Prove or disprove.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 98 — #38 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 98 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking 17. Let G be a simple, connected, undirected graph. Let V be the set of vertices in G, and let P ={{v 1 ,v 2 }|v 1 ,v 2 ∈V,v 1 negationslash= v 2 } be the set of all unordered pairs of vertices. Let E be the set of all edges in G. Deﬁne a function f: E −→ P as follows: If e∈E is an edge in G, then f(e)={a,b}, where a and b are the vertices that e touches. (a) Explain why f(e) is always a set of size 2. (This better be true, or f is not well deﬁned.) (b) Is f one-to-one? Prove or disprove. (c) Does f map E onto P? Prove or disprove. 18. Let S ={0,1,2,3,4,5}, and letP(S) ∗ be the set of all nonempty subsets of S. Deﬁne a function m: P(S) ∗ −→ S by m(H) = the largest element in H for any nonempty subset H ⊆S. (a) Is m one-to-one? Why or why not? (b) Does m map P(S) ∗ onto S? Why or why not? 19. Let X = {n ∈ N | n divides 30030}, and deﬁne a function f: X −→ X by f(n)= 30030 n . (a) Prove that f is one-to-one. (b) Prove that f is onto. 20. Let f: Z−→ Z be deﬁned as f(x)= braceleftBigg x+3 ifx is odd x−5ifx is even . (a) Show that f is a one-to-one correspondence. (b) Find a formula for f −1 . 21. Deﬁne a function f: N−→ Z by f(n)= braceleftBigg n/2ifn is even (1−n)/2ifn is odd .

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 99 — #39 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.3 Functions 99 (a) Show that f is one-to-one correspondence. (b) Find a formula for f −1 . 22. Deﬁne a function g: Z−→ N,byg(z)=z 2 +1. (a) Prove that g is not one-to-one. (b) Prove that g is not onto. 23. Compute the inverse of f(x)=x 3 + 1. Check your answer by showing that f(f −1 (x)) = x and f −1 (f(x)) = x. 24. Suppose that f: X −→ Y has two inverses, g and h. Prove that g = h, that is, prove that for all y∈Y, g(y)=h(y). 25. Deﬁne functions f,g: N−→ N by f(x)=2x g(x)=floorleftx/2floorright Is f ◦g the same as g◦f? Explain. 26. Let f: X −→ Y and g: Y −→ Z be one-to-one correspondences. Prove that (g◦f) −1 = f −1 ◦g −1 . 27. Complete Example 2.33. That is, show that p| H (x,y)=(2x,2y). 28. Let q: R 2 −→ R 2 be given by q(x,y)=(x,0). Geometrically, q is called the projection onto the x-axis, because it maps any point straight down (or up) to the x-axis. Let q| D ∗ be the restriction of q to the unit disk, and let p be the function deﬁned in Example 2.33. Draw a well-labeled picture to show that p◦q| D ∗ negationslash= q| D ∗ ◦p. 29. Suppose f: X −→ Y and g: Y −→ Z are both onto. Prove that g◦f is onto. *30. Suppose f: X −→ Y and g: Y −→ Z are both one-to-one. Prove that g◦f is one-to-one. *31. Let f: X −→ Y and g: Y −→ Z be functions such that h = g◦f is a one-to-one correspondence. (a) Prove that f is one-to-one. (b) Prove that g is onto. *32. Let f: X −→ Y be a function. For any subset U ⊆ X, deﬁne the set f(U): f(U)={y∈Y |y = f(x) for some x∈U}. In particular, f(X) is the image of f.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 100 — #40 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 100 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking (a) Let A⊆X and B ⊆X.Doesf(A∩B)=f(A)∩f(B) in general? Prove it, or give a counterexample. (b) Let A⊆X and B ⊆X.Doesf(A∪B)=f(A)∪f(B) in general? Prove it, or give a counterexample. Hint: Refer to Exercise 20 of Section 1.3. 2.4 Relations and Equivalences Although functions are used in almost every area of mathematics, many re- lationships are not functional. For example, we could never deﬁne a function b(x) that gives the brother of x, because x might have more than one brother (or no brothers at all). A relation is a more general mathematical object that describes these kind of relationships. 2.4.1 Deﬁnition and Examples Deﬁnition 2.4 A relation on a set S is a subset of S×S.IfR is a relation on S, we say that “a is related to b”if(a,b)∈R, which we sometimes write as aRb.If(a,b)negationslash∈R, then a is not related to b; in symbols, anegationslashRb. Some books call this a “binary relation.” It is easy to see how you could generalize this deﬁnition: you could have a relation between a pair of sets, or a relation among a list of sets, but these other kinds of relations are less commonly seen. Example 2.34 The symbols =, <, >,≤,≥all deﬁne relations onZ(or on any set of numbers). For example, if S = {1,2,3}, then the relation on S deﬁned by < is the set {(1,2),(1,3),(2,3)}. Example 2.35 Let P be the set of all people, living or dead. For any a,b∈P, let aRbif a and b are (or were) brothers. Then R is a relation on P, and the ordered pair (Cain,Abel)∈R. Example 2.36 Let W be the set of all web pages. Then L ={(a,b)∈W ×W|a has a link to b} is a relation on W. In other words, aLbif page a links to page b.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 101 — #41 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.4 Relations and Equivalences 101 Example 2.37 Let a,b∈Z. If, for some n∈Z, n|(a−b), we say that “a is equivalent to b modulo n.” The notation for this relation is a≡b mod n. For example, 1,4,7,10,13,... are all equivalent to modulo 3. Notice that a≡b mod n⇔n|(a−b) ⇔a−b = kn for some k∈Z ⇔a = b+kn for some k∈Z, so adding any multiple of n to a number b gives a number that is equivalent to b modulo n. 2.4.2 Graphs of Relations Relations and graphs are similar concepts. Given a relation, there is a graph that models it. Deﬁnition 2.5 Let R be a relation on a set X. The directed graph associated with (X,R) is the graph whose vertices correspond to the elements of X, with a directed edge from vertex x to vertex y whenever xRy. Example 2.38 Consider the “|” relation on the set X = {2,3,4,6}. Fig- ure 2.15 shows a directed graph of this relation. Often a relation R will have the property that xRyif and only if yRx. Such a relation is called symmetric. For a symmetric relation, the arrows would comeinpairs—oneineachdirection.Inthiscase,wereplacethethetwoarrows by a single edge and omit the arrowheads. 26 34 Figure 2.15 A graph of the “|” relation.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 102 — #42 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 102 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking 2 6 34 Figure 2.16 A graph of the relation in Example 2.39. Deﬁnition 2.6 Let R be a relation on a set X, and suppose xRy⇔yRxfor all x,y ∈ X. The undirected graph associated with (X,R) is the graph whose vertices correspond to the elements of X, with an (undirected) edge joining any two vertices x and y for which xRy. Example 2.39 Deﬁne a relation on the set X = {2,3,4,6} by setting aRb whenever ab < 13. Since ab < 13⇔ ba < 13, this is a symmetric relation. An undirected graph of this relation is shown in Figure 2.16. Every relation yields a graph, but there are graphs that don’t have rela- tions associated to them. One example is the graph of the K¨onigsberg bridges in Example 2.1. The double edges in this graph cannot be represented by a re- lation,becauseanyorderedpair(x,y)canoccur,atmost,onceintheCartesian product X×X. 2.4.3 Relations vs. Functions What’s the diﬀerence between a relation and a function? Strictly speaking, a relation on X is a function X −→ X if each x ∈ X occurs exactly once as the ﬁrst element of an ordered pair. But this description is fairly mechanical; what does it really mean? Think of a function as a way of describing how the elements in one set depend on the elements in another set. When we graph a function y = f(x), we usually say that y is the dependent variable and x is the independent variable. This means we get to pick x, and y depends on what we choose for x. We can’t view relations this way, because any given x may be related to several other elements or none at all. Instead, think of relations as describing comparisons within a set or links between elements of a set.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 103 — #43 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.4 Relations and Equivalences 103 Example 2.40 Let X ={2,3,4,5,6,7,8}, and say that two elements a,b∈X are related if a | b and a negationslash= b. We can represent this relation with a directed graph: the elements of X are the vertices, and there is a directed edge from distinct vertices a and b whenever a|b. 2 3 6 8 5 7 4 This example shows how the relationships described by a relation aren’t con- strained the way relationships described by a function are: the element 2 is related to three other elements, while 5 and 7 aren’t related to anything. Thus this relation does not describe a function on X. 2.4.4 Equivalence Relations Deﬁnition 2.7 A relation R on a set S is an equivalence relation if it satisﬁes all three of the following properties. 1. Reﬂexivity. For any a∈S, aRa. 2. Symmetry. For any a,b∈S, aRb⇔bRa. 3. Transitivity. For any a,b,c∈S,ifaRband bRc, then aRc. Inotherwords,anequivalencerelationisarelationthatisreﬂexive,symmetric, and transitive. Example 2.41 The relation on Z deﬁned by = is an equivalence relation, because equality is reﬂexive, symmetric, and transitive. The idea of an equivalence relation might seem abstract at ﬁrst, but you are already quite familiar with an important example: fractions. In elementary school, you learned that equivalent fractions represent the same number; for instance, 3 6 is the same as 1 2 . The next example shows how to prove that this notion is an equivalence relation on the set S of all symbols of the form x y , where x and y are integers. Be careful: the set S is a set of symbols, not a set of numbers. Two diﬀerent symbols in S can represent the same number; this is the point of the equivalence relation.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 104 — #44 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 104 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking Example 2.42 Let S be the set of all symbols of the form x y , where x and y are integers. In other words, S = braceleftBig x y |x,y∈Z bracerightBig . Deﬁne a relation R on S as follows. For any elements x y and z w in S, x y R z w if xw = yz. The proof that R is an equivalence relation has three parts: Proof 1. Reﬂexivity. Suppose that x y ∈S. Since xy = yx, we have x y R x y . 2. Symmetry. Suppose that x y , z w ∈ S and suppose that x y R z w . By the deﬁnition of R, this means that xw = yz, which is the same thing as saying zy = wx.Thus z w R x y , as required. 3. Transitivity. Let x y , z w , p q ∈S with x y R z w and z w R p q . Then xw = yz and zq = wp. Using substitution, xq =(yz/w)(wp/z)=yp. This shows that x y R p q , as required. square The next example is a little less familiar, but notice that the proof follows the same template. Example 2.43 Given any function f: X →Y, deﬁne a relation on X as fol- lows. For any a,b∈X, aRbif f(a)=f(b). The proof that R is an equivalence relation has three parts: Proof 1. Reﬂexivity.Supposethata∈X.Sincef isawell-deﬁnedfunction,f(a)= f(a), so aRa. 2. Symmetry. Suppose that a,b ∈ X and that aRb. By the deﬁnition of R, this means that f(a)=f(b), which is the same thing as saying f(b)=f(a). Thus bRa, as required. 3. Transitivity. Let a,b,c∈X with aRband bRc. Then f(a)=f(b) and f(b)=f(c), so by substitution, f(a)=f(c). This shows that aRc. square Example 2.44 Saythattwocomputersonanetworkarerelatedifitispossible to establish a network connection between the two (e.g., it is possible to ping one from another). In order for this to be an equivalence relation, any computer must be able to ping itself (reﬂexive), any computer must be able to return a ping (symmetric), and any computer must be able to pass along a ping to any other computer that it can ping (transitive).

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 105 — #45 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.4 Relations and Equivalences 105 S X 1 X 2 X 3 X 4 X 5 X 6 Figure 2.17 The set P ={X 1 ,X 2 ,X 3 ,X 4 ,X 5 ,X 6 }is a partition of the set S. Example 2.45 A partition of a set S is a set P of nonempty subsets of S with the following properties. 1. For any a∈S, there is some set X ∈P such that a∈X. The elements of P are called the blocks of the partition. 2. If X,Y ∈P are distinct blocks, then X∩Y =∅. Informally, a partition is a way of dividing a set into nonoverlapping pieces; in a Venn diagram, a partition looks like an arrangement of walls, where the blocks of the partition are the rooms. See Figure 2.17. Suppose P is a partition of S. Deﬁne a relation on S by setting aRbif a and b belong to the same block. We can prove that R is an equivalence relation. Proof 1. Reﬂexivity. Suppose that a∈S. Then a must be in some block X, and a is evidently in the same block as itself. So aRa. 2. Symmetry. Suppose that a,b∈S and suppose that aRb.Thusa and b are in the same block, which is the same as saying that b and a are in the same block. Therefore, bRa. 3. Transitivity. Let a,b,c∈S with aRband bRc. Then a and b are in the same block, and b and c are in the same block, so a and c are in the same block. Therefore aRc, as required. square Example 2.45 shows that every partition determines an equivalence re- lation. It is also true that every equivalence relation determines a partition. Partitions and equivalence relations are essentially the same thing.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 106 — #46 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 106 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking Theorem 2.2 Let R be an equivalence relation on a set S. For any element x ∈ S, deﬁne R x = {a ∈ X|xRa}, the set of all elements related to x. Let P be the collection of distinct subsets of S formed in this way, that is, P ={R x |x∈S}. Then P is a partition of S. A formal proof of this theorem takes a little bit of work, and we’ll omit the proof for the sake of brevity. Informally, such a proof must show that the two properties of a partition are satisﬁed. The ﬁrst property is easy: for any a∈S, there is a block containing a, namely R a . The second property is the hard part. Roughly speaking, the transitive and symmetric properties guarantee that if two blocks overlap at all, then they must overlap completely. The sets R x are called the equivalence classes formed by the equivalence relation. A set S partitioned into equivalence classes looks like this: S R a R b R c R d R e In this picture, the elements a,b,c,d,e ∈ S are called equivalence class repre- sentatives. As the name suggests, there is usually a choice of representatives for a given equivalence class. By Theorem 2.2, diﬀerent equivalence classes must have inequivalent representatives. Example 2.46 Let W be the set of all words in the sentence, “There are more things in heaven and earth, Horatio, than are dreamt of in your philosophy.” Deﬁne a relation R on W as follows: for any words w 1 ,w 2 ∈W, w 1 Rw 2 if the ﬁrst letter of w 1 is the same as the ﬁrst letter of w 2 , without regard to upper or lower cases. (Exercise: show this is an equivalence relation.) The equivalence classes are the sets of all words beginning with the same letter. For example, R things ={There, things, than}. 2.4.5 Modular Arithmetic Consider the “≡ mod n” relation of Example 2.37. To check that this is an equivalence relation, we need to prove that it is reﬂexive, symmetric, and tran- sitive. We’ll show transitivity, and leave the proofs of the other two properties as exercises. Lemma 2.1 The “≡ mod n” relation on Z is transitive.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 107 — #47 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.4 Relations and Equivalences 107 Proof Let a,b,c∈Z, and suppose that a≡b mod n and b≡c mod n. This means that a = b+kn and b = c+ln for some integers k and l. Substituting the second equation into the ﬁrst, we ﬁnd that a =(c+ln)+kn= c+(l+k)n so a≡c mod n, as required for transitivity. square The set of equivalence classes formed by this equivalence relation is called theintegers modulo n,andisdenotedZ/n.Weuse[k]todenotetheequivalence class of [k]. For example, the elements of Z/3 are [0] ={...,−9,−6,−3,0,3,6,9,...} [1] ={...,−8,−5,−2,1,4,7,10,...} [2] ={...,−7,−4,−1,2,5,8,11,...}. The next result is the basis for modular arithmetic. Proposition 2.1 Let [a] and [b] be equivalence classes in Z/n. Suppose that x∈[a] and y∈[b]. Then x+y∈[a+b] and xy∈[ab]. Proof Let [a],[b] ∈ Z/n, and let x ∈ [a] and y ∈ [b]. By the deﬁnition of ≡ mod n, x = a+kn and y = b+ln for some integers k and l. Therefore x+y =(a+kn)+(b+ln)=(a+b)+(k+l)n and xy =(a+kn)(b+ln)=ab+aln+bkn+kln 2 = ab+(al+bk+kln)n, so x+y≡a+b mod n and xy≡ab mod n, as required. square What’s so important about this proposition? It shows that if we add or multiply equivalence class representatives (no matter which ones we choose), we get a representative of the “right” equivalence class. For example, in Z/3, −6∈[0] and 11∈[2]. Their sum, −6+11 = 5, is in [2], the natural value for the “sum” of [0] and [2]. Inotherwords,theoperationsofadditionandmultiplicationonequivalence classes are well deﬁned: [a]+[b]=[a+b] [a]·[b]=[ab].

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 108 — #48 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 108 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking ThismeanswecanaddandmultiplyelementsinZ/nbyaddingandmultiplying the numbers we use to represent the equivalence class. These are the operations of modular arithmetic. For example, in the modular arithmetic of Z/12, [6]+[8] = [2] because 14≡2 mod 12. We usually represent an equivalence class in Z/n by its least non-negative representative, so the operations of modular arithmetic really are just the or- dinary arithmetic operations followed by taking the remainder upon division by n. Although the elements of Z/n are technically sets of numbers (equivalence classes), we can think of them as a new type of number with new rules for multiplication and addition. Sometimes we’ll even omit the [ ]’s around these numbers if the meaning is clear from the context. Example 2.47 Figure 2.18 shows how to add and multiply in Z/6. Notice the patternsinthesetables.The“numbers”0and1inZ/6addandmultiplyasthey do in standard integer arithmetic, but the other numbers behave diﬀerently. For example, 5∈Z/6 acts like −1, both for addition and multiplication. This reﬂects the fact that [5] = [−1] as equivalence classes in Z/6. Modulararithmeticcancomeinquitehandy.Forexample,ifwewantacounter to keep track of an n-stage process that needs to be repeated several times, we would start at [0] and add [1] inZ/n at each stage, and the counter would cycle throughnvaluesandrepeat.Anotherapplication—ISBNcheckdigits—appears in the exercises. + 012345 0 012345 1 123450 2 234501 3 345012 4 450123 5 501234 · 012345 0 000000 1 012345 2 024024 3 030303 4 042042 5 054321 Figure 2.18 Addition and multiplication tables for Z/6.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 109 — #49 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.4 Relations and Equivalences 109 Exercises 2.4 1. Let X ={0,1,2,3,4}. Draw the graph associated with the < relation on X. Should this graph be directed or undirected? 2. Let X = {0,1,2,3,4}. Deﬁne a relation R on X such that xRyif x + y = 4. Draw the graph associated with this relation. Should this graph be directed or undirected? For Exercises 3–6, deﬁne a relationharpoonleftrighton the set S of all strings of let- ters: two strings are related if you can get one from the other by reversing one pair of adjacent letters. For example, cowharpoonrightleftocw but cownegationslashharpoonrightleft woc. 3. Consider all the strings you can form with the letters c, a, and t (there are six). Draw the graph whose nodes are these six strings and whose edgesrepresenttheharpoonrightleftrelation.Shouldthisbeadirectedoranundirected graph? 4. Find an Euler path in the graph you made in Exercise 3. 5. Consider the graph formed by theharpoonrightleftrelation on the set of all the strings you can form from the letters l, y, n, and x. Does this graph have an Euler path? Why or why not? 6. Does the graph of the harpoonrightleft relation on the set of all strings formed from the letters l, e, o, p, a, r, and d have an Euler path? Why or why not? 7. Supposeyouwantedtomodelanequivalencerelationwithagraph.Would you use a directed or an undirected graph? What would the equivalence classes look like? Explain. 8. Deﬁne a relation on Z by aRbif a 2 = b 2 . (a) Prove that R is an equivalence relation. (b) Describe the equivalence classes. 9. Explain why the web linking relation in Example 2.36 is not an equiv- alence relation. (You only need to give one reason why it fails to be an equivalence relation.) 10. ProvethattherelationdeﬁnedinExample2.46isanequivalencerelation.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 110 — #50 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 110 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking 11. Explain why the relation R on {0,1,2} given by R ={(0,0),(1,1),(2,2),(0,1),(1,0),(1,2),(2,1)} is not an equivalence relation. Be speciﬁc. 12. Let A ={1,2}. Write out the subset of A×A deﬁned by the ≤ relation on A. 13. Let X ={0,1}. (a) List (as subsets of X×X) all possible relations on X. (b) Which of the relations in part (a) are equivalence relations? 14. Let X be a set. Deﬁne a relation R on P(X)by ARB⇔ A∩B =∅ for A,B ∈P(X). Determine whether this relation is reﬂexive, symmetric, and/or transitive. 15. Let S be the set of all provinces in Canada. For a,b ∈ S, let aRbif a and b border each other. Which properties of an equivalence relation (reﬂexive, symmetric, transitive) does the relation R satisfy? 16. Let T be the set of all movie actors and actresses. For x,y ∈ T, deﬁne xRyifthereissomemoviethatbothxandy appearin.Whichproperties of equivalence relations does R satisfy? 17. Let W be the set of words in the English language. Deﬁne a relation R on W by w 1 Rw 2 ⇔ w 1 and w 2 have a letter in common. Which properties of equivalence relations does R satisfy? Explain. 18. Let W be the set of words in the English language. Deﬁne a relation S on W by w 1 Sw 2 ⇔ w 1 has at least as many letters as w 2 . Which properties of equivalence relations does S satisfy? Explain. 19. Let X be a ﬁnite set. For subsets A,B ∈P(X), let ARBif |A| = |B|. This is an equivalence relation on P(X). If X = {1,2,3}, list the equivalence classes.

Unknown

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 111 — #51 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.4 Relations and Equivalences 111 20. A playground consists of several structures, some of which are connected by bridges. The ground is covered with bark chips. Deﬁne a relation on the set of structures on the playground as follows: two structures are related if it is possible for a child to get from one to the other without walking on the bark chips (otherwise known as “hot lava”). (a) Can you imagine a playground for which this would not be an equiv- alence relation? Explain. (b) Suppose this relation is an equivalence. In the language of play- ground equipment, describe the equivalence classes. 21. LetGbeaconnected,undirectedgraph,andletV bethesetofallvertices in G. Deﬁne a relation R on V as follows: for any vertices a,b∈V, aRb if there is a path from a to b with an even number of edges. (A path may use the same edge more than once.) Prove that R is an equivalence relation. 22. Suppose the equivalence relation of Exercise 21 is deﬁned on the vertices of the following graph. What are the equivalence classes? a c e f g b d 23. Recall the deﬁnition of even numbers. Deﬁnition. An integer n is even if n =2k for some integer k. Deﬁne a relation R on Z by xRyif x+y is even. (a) Show that R is an equivalence relation. (b) Describe the equivalence classes formed by this relation. 24. Lemma 2.1 states that the “≡ mod n” relation on Z is transitive. Show that it is also symmetric and reﬂexive. 25. Compute the following arithmetic problems in Z/8. Represent your an- swer with the least positive representative of the appropriate equivalence class. (a) [3]+[7] (b) [2]·([4]+[5]) (c) ([3]+[4])·([5]+[6])

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 112 — #52 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 112 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking 26. For any [x]∈Z/n and any k∈Z, we can deﬁne k[x]by k[x]=[x]+[x]+···+[x] bracehtipupleft bracehtipdownrightbracehtipdownleft bracehtipupright k times where the result is an element of Z/n.Wesayk[x]isamultiple of [x]. (a) List all the multiples of [3] in Z/9. (b) List all the multiples of [3] in Z/8. 27. Consider the function p: Z −→ Z/n deﬁned by p(n)=[n]. Prove that this function is onto but not one-to-one. 28. Construct the addition and multiplication tables for Z/4. 29. Construct the multiplication table for Z/11. Exercises 30–32 deal with the method of using check digits in ISBN numbers. Prior to 2007, every commercially available book was given a 10-digit International Standard Book Number, usually printed on the back cover next to the barcode. The ﬁnal character of this 10-digit string is a special digit used to check for errors in typing the ISBN number. If the ﬁrst nine digits of an ISBN number are a 1 a 2 a 3 a 4 a 5 a 6 a 7 a 8 a 9 , the tenth digit is given by the formula a 10 =(1a 1 +2a 2 +3a 3 +4a 4 +5a 5 +6a 6 +7a 7 +8a 8 +9a 9 )mod11, where a 10 = X if this value is 10. 30. CalculatethetenthdigitoftheISBNwhoseﬁrstninedigitsare039481500. 31. Suppose a 1 a 2 a 3 a 4 a 5 a 6 a 7 a 8 a 9 a 10 is a valid ISBN number. Show that (1a 1 +2a 2 +3a 3 +4a 4 +5a 5 +6a 6 +7a 7 +8a 8 +9a 9 +10a 10 )≡0mod11. 32. Is 0060324814 a valid ISBN number? *33. Showthatthecheckdigitwillalwaysdetecttheerrorofswitchingtwoad- jacentdigits.Thatis,showthata 1 ···a k a k+1 ···a 9 anda 1 ···a k+1 a k ···a 9 have diﬀerent check digits. *34. Show that the check digit will always detect the error of changing a single digit. Hint: The proof has something to do with the multiplication table for Z/11 (Exercise 29).

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 113 — #53 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.5 Partial Orderings 113 *35. Unfortunately,thereweretoomanybooksandnotenoughISBNnumbers; eﬀective January 2007, ISBN numbers must be 13 digits long. The check digit scheme for 13-digit ISBN numbers is diﬀerent. Explain why the obvious modiﬁcation to the old system won’t work. That is, ﬁnd a 12- digit string a 1 a 2 ···a 12 where the quantity (1a 1 +2a 2 +···+12a 12 )mod14 doesn’t change after changing a single digit. *36. Will the “obvious modiﬁcation” in Exercise 32 detect the error of switch- ing two adjacent digits? 2.5 Partial Orderings Most of the relationships modeled in the previous section express sameness; an equivalence relation is a mathematical way of describing how two objects are similar. However, there are many situations in which we would like to quantify how objects of a set are diﬀerent from each other. The relations in this section will give us a mathematical way to analyze comparisons and rankings. 2.5.1 Deﬁnition and Examples In addition to equivalence relations, there is another type of relation that is worth studying as a special case. Compare the following with Deﬁnition 2.7. Deﬁnition 2.8 A relation R on a set S is a partial ordering if it satisﬁes all three of the following properties. 1. Reﬂexivity. For any a∈S, aRa. 2. Transitivity. For any a,b,c∈S,ifaRband bRc, then aRc. 3. Antisymmetry. For any a,b∈S,ifaRband bRa, then a = b. The reﬂexivity and transitivity properties are the same as in the deﬁnition of an equivalence relation, but the third property is new: it is called “antisym- metry” because it says that aRbnever happens when bRa, unless a = b. Example 2.48 If S isasetofnumbers,then≤deﬁnesapartialorderingonS. Since Example 2.48 is a natural example of a relation that is reﬂexive, antisymmetric, and transitive, we will often use the symbol precedesequal to represent a genericpartialorderingrelation(insteadofR).Thisnotationhastheadvantage of allowing us to write a≺b when aprecedesequalb and anegationslash= b.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 114 — #54 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 114 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking Example 2.49 Let S be any set, and letP(S) be the power set of S. Then⊆ deﬁnes a partial ordering on P(S). Proof Let A∈P(S). Then A⊆A, since x∈A obviously implies that x∈A. So ⊆ is reﬂexive. Let A,B,C ∈P(S), and suppose A⊆B and B ⊆C. Then for all x∈S, x∈A⇒x∈B and x∈B ⇒x∈C,sox∈A⇒x∈C.ThusA⊆C,so⊆ is transitive. Finally, let A,B ∈P(S), and suppose that A ⊆ B and B ⊆ A. Then x∈A⇔x∈B,soA = B. Therefore ⊆ is antisymmetric. square Example 2.50 The “divides” relation | deﬁnes a partial ordering on N. The proof of this is an exercise. If a set X has a partial ordering precedesequal on it, we say that (X,precedesequal) is a partially ordered set, or poset, for short. In a poset, it is possible to have elements a and b such that neither aprecedesequalb nor bprecedesequala. Such elements are called incomparable.In Example 2.50, 12 and 25 are incomparable because 12 notbar 25 and 25 notbar 12. If a poset (X,precedesequal) has no incomparable elements, it is called a total ordering. For example, the real numbers R are totally ordered by the ≤ relation. 2.5.2 Hasse Diagrams In the last section, we saw that the key fact about equivalence relations was thattheybreakasetupintopartitions.Partialorderingsareimportantbecause they deﬁne a hierarchy among the elements of a set. We use Hasse diagrams to describe this hierarchy graphically. Suppose precedesequal is a partial ordering on a set X. A Hasse diagram for (X,precedesequal) consists of a label, or node, for each element in the set, along with lines con- necting related nodes. More speciﬁcally, if x,y are distinct elements of X with xprecedesequaly, and there are no elements z such that x≺z ≺y, then there should be an upward sloping line from node x to node y in the Hasse diagram. Example 2.51 LetT ={1,2,3}andconsidertheposet(P(T),⊆).Sincethere areeightsubsetsofT,theHassediagramhaseightnodes.SeeFigure2.19.Note that by following the edges up the diagram, you move from one set to another set that contains it. And since ⊆ is transitive, every set you encounter as you move up the diagram will contain the set where you started. Like binary search trees, Hasse diagrams are graphs with extra information encoded in the way the graph is drawn. Traditionally, Hasse diagrams don’t have arrows, but the edges are, in fact, directed: in an edge between nodes x and y, x is drawn above y when yprecedesequalx.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 115 — #55 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.5 Partial Orderings 115 {1, 2, 3} {1, 3} {2, 3}{1, 2} {1} {2} {3} 0 Figure 2.19 The Hasse diagram for (P({1,2,3}),⊆). Example 2.52 Let X ={2,3,4,5,6,7,8}, and say two elements a,b∈X are related if a | b. Figure 2.20 shows the Hasse diagram for this poset. Compare this to the graph in Example 2.40, and notice that there are no edges in the Hassediagrambetweenrelatednodesthatareconnectedbyasequenceofedges. Herewedon’tneedanedgebetween2and8,sinceyoucangettherevianode4. A partial order on a set gives you a way of comparing elements and ranking them. In this ranking system, there are often least elements and greatest ele- ments. If (X,precedesequal) is a poset, we say that an element m∈X is minimal if there is no x∈X (xnegationslash= m) such that xprecedesequalm. Similarly, we say that an element M ∈X is maximal if there is no x ∈ X (x negationslash= M) such that M precedesequal x. For example, in Figure 2.20, the minimal elements are 2 and 3 and the only maximal element is 8. In Figure 2.19, ∅ is minimal and {0,1,2} is maximal. 8 4 23 6 Figure 2.20 The Hasse diagram for (X,|).

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 116 — #56 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 116 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking 2.5.3 Topological Sorting Partial orderings are useful for describing the relationships among the parts of a complex process, such as manufacturing assembly or scheduling. Suppose that some process consists of a ﬁnite set, T, of tasks. Some tasks are dependent on others being done ﬁrst. (For example, when you get dressed, you must put on your socks before putting on your shoes.) If x,y∈T are two tasks, let xprecedesequaly if x must be done before y. This is a partial ordering. In most real-world applications, (T,precedesequal) won’t be a totally ordered set. This is because some steps of the process do not depend on other steps being done ﬁrst. (You can put your watch on at any time in the process of getting dressed.) However, if we want to create a schedule in which all of the tasks in T are done in some sequential order, we need to create a total ordering on T. (At some point, we just need to decide on an order to put our clothes on.) Furthermore, thistotalorderingmustbecompatiblewiththepartialordering.Inotherwords, we need a total order relation precedesequal t such that xprecedesequaly ⇒ xprecedesequal t y for all x,y ∈ T. The technique of ﬁnding such a total ordering is known as topological sorting. Performing a topological sort involves making an ordered list of all the tasks. Represent the partial ordering on T with a Hasse diagram. Then repeat the following steps until there are no more tasks. • Choose a minimal element in your Hasse diagram. (Note that you can always ﬁnd a minimal element, but there might be more than one.) Add this element to the end of the list you are making. • Remove the element from your Hasse diagram. Example 2.53 Julia is interested in completing a Computer Science minor, and has several courses left to take. Some of the courses have prerequisite courses that must be taken ﬁrst. Courses Needed Prerequisites Calculus I Calculus II Calculus I Calculus III Calculus II Linear Algebra Calculus II Programming II Calculus I Software Development Programming II 3D Computer Graphics Calculus III, Linear Algebra, Programming II

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 117 — #57 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.5 Partial Orderings 117 3D Computer Graphics Linear Algebra Calc III Calc II Calc I Programming II Software Development Figure 2.21 The Hasse diagram for Example 2.53. In what order must Julia take these courses to ensure that she will satisfy the prerequisites for each course? Is this ordering unique? What is the minimum number of semesters it will take Julia to ﬁnish? Solution: Figure 2.21 shows the Hasse diagram for this poset. To perform a topological sort, we start by choosing a minimal element in the Hasse diagram. The only minimal element is Calculus I, so that must be Julia’s ﬁrst class. We then remove Calculus I from the diagram. After Calculus I has been removed, there are two minimal elements: Cal- culus II and Programming II. Julia could take either of these next, so the ordering of courses is not unique. Let’s choose Calculus II as the second course, and remove it from the diagram. This leaves Linear Algebra, Calculus III, and Programming II as minimal elements. Julia needs to take all three before she takes 3D Computer Graphics, and she needs to take Programming II before she takes software development. Again, the ordering is not unique. One allow- able order for the remaining classes is Calculus III, Programming II, Software Development, Linear Algebra, and, ﬁnally, 3D Computer Graphics. Ifwearetryingtominimizethenumberofsemesters,werepeattheprocess, exceptateachstagewechoose all theminimalelements,soJuliatakesasmany courses as she is allowed to take each semester. This would yield the following schedule. Semester Courses 1 Calculus I 2 Calculus II, Programming II 3 Calculus III, Linear Algebra, Software Development 4 3D Computer Graphics ♦

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 118 — #58 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 118 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking Topological sorting is a pretty simple technique, once you have written the dependencies in the form of a Hasse diagram. This simplicity illustrates the power of a graphical approach to a discrete problem. 2.5.4 Isomorphisms Sometimes two problems are so closely related that solving one gives a solution to the other. When two mathematical objects are fundamentally the same in every aspect of structure and function, we can deﬁne a map called an isomor- phism to describe the similarity. Example 2.54 LetF ⊆Nbethesetofallfactorsof30,andconsidertheposet (F,|) given by the “divides” relation. As in Example 2.52, we can construct the Hasse diagram for this partially ordered set. See Figure 2.22. NoticehowthisHassediagramhasthesamestructureastheHassediagram for (P({1,2,3}),⊆) in Example 2.51. These two posets are the same in a very speciﬁc way. Deﬁnition 2.9 Let (X 1 ,precedesequal 1 ) and (X 2 ,precedesequal 2 ) be partially ordered sets. Then (X 1 ,precedesequal 1 )isisomorphic to (X 2 ,precedesequal 2 ) if there is a one-to-one correspondence f: X 1 −→ X 2 such that aprecedesequal 1 b ⇔ f(a)precedesequal 2 f(b) for all a,b ∈ X 1 . In this case, we say that f is an isomorphism and we write (X 1 ,precedesequal 1 ) ∼ = (X 2 ,precedesequal 2 ) to denote that these posets are isomorphic. 1 2 3 10 30 6 15 5 Figure 2.22 The Hasse diagram for (F,|).

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 119 — #59 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.5 Partial Orderings 119 Thefollowingtabledeﬁnesaone-to-onecorrespondencef: P({1,2,3})−→ F that describes the isomorphism between (F,|) and (P({1,2,3}),⊆). X ∅ {1} {2} {3} {1,2} {1,3} {2,3} {1,2,3} f(X) 1 2 3 5 6 10 15 30 Since every element of F appears exactly once in this table, f is a one-to- one correspondence. To see that X ⊆ Y if and only if f(X) | f(Y) for all X,Y ⊆{1,2,3}, it is suﬃcient to observe that the edges in the the Hasse diagram for (F,|) correspond exactly to the edges in the Hasse diagram for (P({1,2,3}),⊆), and that this correspondence is given by f. This shows that (F,|) ∼ = (P({1,2,3}),⊆). At this point it is natural to wonder whether this isomorphism is a happy coincidence, or perhaps there is something deeper going on. Are the partial orders given by⊆and|related in some fundamental way? In the exercises, you will have the opportunity to check that the Hasse diagrams for these relations agree when applied to the factors of 210 = 2·3·5·7 and the set {1,2,3,4}. But will this always happen? Let’s take a closer look at the relationship between the posets (F,|) and (P({1,2,3}),⊆).Since30 = 2·3·5,everyfactorof30canbewritten(uniquely) as a product of the form    2 or 1       3 or 1       5 or 1   . Choosing a factor k ∈ F amounts to choosing whether or not to include each prime2,3,or5inthisproduct.Similarly,choosingasubsetX oftheset{1,2,3} amounts to choosing which of the three members 1,2,3 to include in X. This explains why the above function f is a one-to-one correspondence. The number 3·5 corresponds to the subset {2,3}, for example. Furthermore, under this one-to-one correspondence, the | relation plays exactlythesameroleasthe⊆relation.Checking,forexample,that3·5 |2·3·5 is the same as checking that all of the factors on the left are included on the right, while checking that {2,3}⊆{1,2,3} involves checking that all of the elements on the left are included on the right. This explains why f is order- preserving. The proof of the following theorem generalizes this observation. Theorem 2.3 Let q = p 1 p 2 ···p n be the product of the ﬁrst n primes, and let F ⊆N be the set of all factors of q. Then (F,|) ∼ = (P({1,2,···,n}),⊆).

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 120 — #60 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 120 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking Proof Deﬁne a function f: P({1,2,...,n})−→ F by setting f(X)tobethe product of all the p i ’s with i∈X. For example, f({1,3})=p 1 p 3 =2·5=10. Also, deﬁne f(∅) = 1. In product notation, f(X)= productdisplay i∈X p i expresses the fact that f(X) is the product of all the p i ’s having i ∈ X.We claim that f is a one-to-one correspondence. Proof that f is a one-to-one correspondence Let k ∈ F be a factor of q. Since q is a product of distinct primes, any factor of q must be a product of these primes. Therefore k = producttext i∈X p i for some X ∈P({1,2,...,n}). So f is onto. Toshowthatf isone-to-one,supposethatX andY aresubsetsof{1,2,...,n} with f(X)=f(Y), that is, productdisplay i∈X p i = productdisplay i∈Y p i . Since the prime factorization of a number is unique, X and Y must have the same elements, so X = Y. square To show that f is an isomorphism, we also need to show that X ⊆ Y if and only if f(X)|f(Y). This property of isomorphisms is called “preserving” the partial ordering. Proof that f is order-preserving Suppose that X ⊆ Y for some X,Y ⊆ {1,2,...,n}. Then Y consists of two parts: those elements in X and those not in X. In symbols, Y = X∪(Y \X) is a union of disjoint sets. Therefore productdisplay i∈Y p i = parenleftBigg productdisplay i∈X p i parenrightBigg   productdisplay i∈Y\X p i   = parenleftBigg productdisplay i∈X p i parenrightBigg ·k where k∈N. In other words, f(Y)=k·f(X), so f(X)|f(Y). Conversely, suppose f(X)|f(Y) for some X,Y ⊆{1,2,...,n}. Then productdisplay i∈Y p i = k parenleftBigg productdisplay i∈X p i parenrightBigg

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 121 — #61 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.5 Partial Orderings 121 for some k ∈ N. Since prime factorizations are unique, every p i factor on the right side of this equation must also be on the left side. Therefore, X ⊆ Y. square square The above theorem tells us that these posets will always be isomorphic, and the proof tells us why they are isomorphic. In short, choosing a factor of q amounts to choosing a list of prime numbers, and this choice corresponds to a choice of a subset of{1,2,...,n}. The whole proof is based on this observation. 2.5.5 Boolean Algebras ‡ TheisomorphicposetsdescribedbytheHassediagramsinFigures2.20and2.22 are examples of a special kind of partially ordered set called a Boolean algebra. Thesemathematicalstructureshighlightabeautifulconnectionbetweenpartial orders and propositional logic. Let (X,precedesequal) be a poset. For any elements a,b∈X, deﬁne the meet of a and b (denoted a∧b) to be the greatest lower bound of a and b,ifsuchalower bound exists. Formally, a∧b is an element of X with the following properties. 1. a∧bprecedesequala and a∧bprecedesequalb. 2. If some x∈X satisﬁes xprecedesequala and xprecedesequalb, then xprecedesequala∧b. It follows from property 2 that if the meet of two elements exists, then it is unique. Similarly, we can deﬁne the join of a,b∈X to be the element a∨b∈X satisfying 1. aprecedesequala∨b and bprecedesequala∨b. 2. If some x∈X satisﬁes aprecedesequalx and bprecedesequalx, then a∨bprecedesequalx. if such an element exists. Example 2.55 In Example 2.52, 4∧6=2,2∨3 = 6, but 4∨6 does not exist. In Example 2.51, {1}∨{2,3}={1,2,3} and {1}∧{2,3}=∅. If every pair of elements a,b∈X has both a meet and a join, then (X,precedesequal) is called a lattice. The notation for meet and join is the same as the notation for “and” and “or” in propositional logic, and this is no accident. In a lattice, meet and join satisfy the following properties, for all a,b,c∈X. Commutativity: a∧b = b∧a and a∨b = b∨a. Associativity: a∨(b∨c)=(a∨b)∨c and a∧(b∧c)=(a∧b)∧c. Absorption: a∨(a∧b)=a and a∧(a∨b)=a.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 122 — #62 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 122 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking If, in addition, a lattice has the following three properties, it is called a Boolean algebra. Distributivity: a∨(b∧c)=(a∨b)∧(a∨c) and a∧(b∨c)=(a∧b)∨(a∧c). Boundedness: There exist elements 0,1∈X such that xprecedesequal1 and 0precedesequalx for all x∈X. Complements: For any x ∈ X there exists an element ¬x ∈ X such that x∧¬x = 0 and x∨¬x = 1. From our study of set theory, we know that the poset (P({1,2,...,n}),⊆) satisﬁesallthepropertiesofaBooleanalgebra.Thecorrespondenceissuggested by the set notation: meet is ∩, join is ∪, 0 is ∅, 1 is {1,2,...,n}, and ¬ is the set complement. The next theorem states that this is the only ﬁnite Boolean algebra, up to isomorphism. Theorem 2.4 Let X be a ﬁnite set. Suppose that the poset (X,precedesequal) is a Boolean algebra. Then |X|=2 n for some n∈N, and (X,precedesequal) ∼ = (P({1,2,...,n}),⊆). The proof of this theorem is beyond the scope of this book, as are the theories of lattices and Boolean algebras. But the above deﬁnitions are still worth knowing, because they illustrate the rich connections between set theory, propositional logic, and partial orders. Exercises 2.5 1. Refer to Deﬁnition 1.10. Show that the divisibility relation | makes the set N of natural numbers a partially ordered set. 2. Explain why the divisibility relation | does not deﬁne a partial ordering on the set Z of integers. 3. Consider the poset (N,|). Are there any minimal elements? Are there any maximal elements? Explain. 4. Let A = {a,b,c,... ,z}. In the poset (P(A),⊆), ﬁnd a pair of incompa- rable elements. 5. Let W be the set of all web pages. For x,y ∈ W, let xRyif you can navigate from x to y by following links. (Let’s say it is always possible to “navigate” from a page to itself; just do nothing.) Explain why R is not a partial ordering.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 123 — #63 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.5 Partial Orderings 123 6. Explain why the relation R on {0,1,2,3} given by R ={(0,0),(1,1),(2,2),(3,3),(0,1),(1,2),(2,3),(0,2),(1,3)} is not a partial ordering on {0,1,2,3}. Be speciﬁc. 7. Explain why the relation R on {0,1,2,3} given by R ={(0,0),(1,1),(2,2),(3,3),(0,1),(1,2),(0,2),(2,1)} is not a partial ordering on {0,1,2,3}. Be speciﬁc. 8. Thedividesrelation“|”deﬁnesapartialorderingontheset{1,2,3,6,8,10}. Draw the Hasse diagram for this poset. What are the maximal elements? 9. Let X be a set of diﬀerent nonzero monetary values (in US or Canadian cents). In other words, X ⊆N. Deﬁne a relation |=onX as follows. For a,b∈X, a|= b if b can be obtained from a by adding a (possibly empty) collection of dimes (10 cents) and quarters (25 cents). So, for example, 25|= 35, but 25negationslash|= 30. Prove that |= is a partial ordering on X. 10. Let X ={5,10,15,20,25,30,35,40}, and let |= be as in Problem 9. (a) Draw the Hasse diagram for the poset (X,|=). (b) List all minimal elements of (X,|=). (c) Give a pair of incomparable elements in (X,|=). 11. Let X be the following set (of sets of letters). X ={{b},{b,e},{b,r},{b,e,r},{a,r},{b,a,r},{b,e,a,r,s}} Then X is a partially ordered set under the ⊆ relation. (a) Draw the Hasse diagram for this partial ordering. (b) Name all minimal elements, if any exist. (c) Name a pair of incomparable elements, if any exist. 12. Let A ={a,b,c}. Use Hasse diagrams to describe all partial orderings on A for which a is a minimal element. (There are 10.) 13. Suppose you want to write a program that will collect information on a customer’s tastes and customize web content accordingly. By monitoring onlineshoppinghabits,youareabletocollectasetofpairwisepreferences on a set X of products. If x,y∈X are two diﬀerent products, we say that x precedesequal y if the customer prefers y over x. (In order to satisfy the reﬂexive property, we stipulate that xprecedesequalx for all x∈X.) Suppose you know the following things about your customer.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 124 — #64 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 124 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking Customer prefers: Over: lettuce broccoli cabbage broccoli tomatoes cabbage carrots cabbage carrots lettuce asparagus lettuce mushrooms tomatoes corn tomatoes corn carrots eggplant carrots eggplant asparagus onions mushrooms onions corn Inorderfor(X,precedesequal)tobeaposet,wemustalsoassumethatthecustomer’s preferences are transitive. (a) Draw the Hasse diagram for (X,precedesequal). (b) What is/are the customer’s favorite vegetable(s)? [i.e., what are the maximal element(s)?] What is/are the least favorite? (c) Use topological sorting to rank order these vegetables according to the customer’s preferences. Is the ranking unique? 14. Apartition ofapositiveintegernisalistofpositiveintegersa 1 ,a 2 ,...,a k such that a 1 +a 2 +···+a k = n. For example, the following are distinct partitions of 5. 51,1,1,21,2,21,1,1,1,1 The order of the list doesn’t matter; 1,2,2 is the same partition as 2,1,2. There is a natural partial ordering on the set of partitions of n:ifP 1 and P 2 arepartitions,deﬁneP 1 precedesequalP 2 ifP 1 canbeobtainedbycombiningparts of P 2 . For example, 1,2,2precedesequal1,1,1,1,1 because 1,2,2=1,1+1,1+1. On the other hand, 2,3 and 1,4 are incomparable elements in this poset. (a) Writethepartitionsof6inaHassediagram.(Thereare11partitions of 6.) (b) Is this a total ordering? Why or why not? 15. Let X ={1,2,3,4}. Draw the Hasse diagram for the poset (P(X),⊆).

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 125 — #65 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.5 Partial Orderings 125 16. Let F ⊆N be the set of all factors of 210. Draw the Hasse diagrams for (F,|) and (P({1,2,3,4}),⊆) in a way that shows these two posets are isomorphic. 17. Let A ⊆ N be the set of all factors of 12, and let B ⊆ N be the set of all factors of n. Find a natural number n negationslash= 12 so that (A,|) ∼ = (B,|). Give a table of values for the one-to-one correspondence that describes the isomorphism. 18. Let B be the set of all four-digit binary strings, that is, B ={0000,0001,0010,0011,...,1110,1111}. Deﬁne a relation triangleleft on B as follows: Let x,y ∈ B, where x = x 1 x 2 x 3 x 4 and y = y 1 y 2 y 3 y 4 . We say that xtriangleleftyif x i ≤y i for i =1,2,3,4. In other words, xtriangleleftyif y has a 1 in every position where x does. So, for example, 0101triangleleft0111 and 0000triangleleft0011, but 1010negationslashtriangleleft0111. The relation triangleleft is called the bitwise ≤. Show that (B,triangleleft) is a poset. 19. Prove that (B,triangleleft) ∼ = (P({1,2,3,4}),⊆). 20. In (B,triangleleft), give a counterexample to show that 0000,0001,0010,0011,0100,0101,0110,0111,1000,1001,1010,0011,1100, 1101,1110,1111 is not a valid topological sort of the elements of B. 21. Perform a topological sort on the elements of B. 22. Let F ⊆ N be the set of all factors of 210. In the poset (F,|), ﬁnd the following. (a) 30∧21, the meet of 30 and 21. (b) 35∨15, join of 35 and 15. (c) 2∧7. (d) 2∨7. (e) ¬30, the complement of 30.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 126 — #66 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 126 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking 23. Let W ={a,b,c,d,e,f,g,h,i,j,k,l}. Deﬁne a partial order on W by the Hasse diagram in Figure 2.23. jkl fghi cde ab Figure 2.23 Hasse diagram for Exercise 23. (a) Find two elements of W whose meet exists but whose join does not exist. (b) Find two elements of W whose join exists but whose meet does not exist. (c) Find two elements of W whose meet and join both do not exist. 24. Let m,n ∈ Z and suppose m ≤ n. In the poset (Z,≤), what are m∧n and m∨n? 25. Let T be the set of all two-digit ternary strings, that is, T ={00,01,02,10,11,12,20,21,22}. Consider the poset (T,triangleleft), where triangleleft is the bitwise≤. Let F ⊆N be the set of all factors of 36. Draw Hasse diagrams to show that (T,triangleleft) ∼ = (F,|). 26. Consider the poset (T,triangleleft) of the previous problem. This poset is, in fact, a lattice. (a) Theorem2.4canbeusedtoshowthat(T,triangleleft)isnotaBooleanalgebra. How? (b) Find an element of (T,triangleleft) that has no complement. Explain why. 27. Let P be a set of posets. Prove that ∼ = is an equivalence relation on P.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 127 — #67 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.6 Graph Theory 127 2.6 Graph Theory We began this chapter with an informal introduction to graphs, and we have seen several ways to model mathematical relationships with them. We have also studied how sets, functions, and relations express these ideas in formal mathematical language. Now that we have developed this new machinery, we can revisit graphs from a more rigorous perspective. In this section we explore how to prove theorems about graphs. Some of the topics in this section—in particular, some of the proofs—will be quite challenging, because the viewpoint here will be more theoretical than in preceding sections. Fasten your seat belts. 2.6.1 Graphs: Formal Deﬁnitions In Section 2.1, we gave an informal description of a graph in terms of dots and lines. Now that we have discussed sets and functions, we can give a mathemat- ical deﬁnition. Warning: giving a deﬁnition of a graph is tricky; choices need to be made, and other books might make diﬀerent choices. Deﬁnition 2.10 A directed graph G is a ﬁnite set of vertices V G and a ﬁnite setofedgesE G ,alongwithafunctioni: E G −→ V G ×V G .Foranyedgee∈E G , if i(e)=(a,b), we say that edge e joins vertex a to vertex b. Note that this deﬁnition allows for loops (when a = b) and multiple edges (when i(e 1 )=i(e 2 ) for e 1 negationslash= e 2 ). 4 The deﬁnition of an undirected graph diﬀers only in the way the word “join” is deﬁned. Deﬁnition 2.11 An undirected graph G is a ﬁnite set of vertices V G and a ﬁnite set of edges E G , along with a function i: E G −→ V G ×V G . For any edge e ∈ E G ,ifi(e)=(a,b), we say that vertices a and b are joined by edge e,or equivalently, e joins a to b and e joins b to a. (Here it is possible that a = b;if i(e)=(a,a), then e is a loop joining a to itself.) While these deﬁnitions are mathematically rigorous, they can be hard to conceptualize. It is still important to think of a graph as a picture: each vertex corresponds to a dot, and each edge corresponds to an arrow (for directed graphs) or a line (for undirected graphs). 2.6.2 Isomorphisms of Graphs What really matters about a graph is the relationship it describes among its vertices. You can draw a given graph any way you choose, as long as you connect the vertices correctly. Two graphs that share the same fundamental structurearecalledisomorphic.Theprecisedeﬁnitionissimilartothedeﬁnition 4.Someauthorscallthisa“multigraph.”

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 128 — #68 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 128 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking of isomorphic posets. Note that, since Deﬁnitions 2.10 and 2.11 both stipulate the meaning of the word “join,” the following deﬁnition can apply to directed and undirected graphs simultaneously. Deﬁnition 2.12 Let G be a graph with vertex set V G and edge set E G , and let H be a graph with vertex set V H and edge set E H . Then G is isomorphic to H if there are one-to-one correspondences α : V G −→ V H and β : E G −→ E H such that, for any edge e∈E G , e joins vertex v to vertex w ⇔ β(e) joins vertex α(v) to vertex α(w). In this case, we write G ∼ = H. For example, the graphs in Figure 2.24 are isomorphic. The one-to-one correspondence of vertices is given by α(x i )=y i , and the correspondence of edges is given by β(a i )=b i . By inspecting the graphs, it is evident that the criterion a i joins vertex x j to vertex x k ⇔ b i joins vertex y j to vertex y k holds for all i, j, and k. x 2 x 3 x 1 x 5 x 4 a 2 a 4 a 1 a 3 y 3 y 1 y 5 y 2 y 4 a 5 a 6 b 6 b 2 b 1 b 3 b 5 b 4 Figure 2.24 Two isomorphic graphs. Deﬁnition 2.12 is quite complicated, but it applies to any graph. For graphs without multiple edges, the following theorem gives a simpler condition to check. Theorem 2.5 Let G and H be graphs without multiple edges, with vertex sets V G and V H , respectively. For vertices x and y, write xRyif an edge joins x to y. If there is a one-to-one correspondence f: V G −→ V H with the property that xRy⇔ f(x) Rf(y) for all x,y∈V G , then G ∼ = H.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 129 — #69 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.6 Graph Theory 129 Proof We need to check that all the conditions of Deﬁnition 2.12 are satis- ﬁed. Let α be the given one-to-one correspondence f: V G −→ V H . We deﬁne β: E G −→ E H as follows. Given an edge e ∈ E G , let x and y be the vertices that e joins, so xRy. Deﬁne β(e)∈E H to be the edge between f(x) and f(y). We know there is an edge joining f(x)tof(y) because xRy⇒f(x) Rf(y). Since H has no multiple edges, there is only one such edge. So β is well-deﬁned. To show that β is onto, let a ∈ E H be an edge of H, and let v and w be the vertices that a joins. Then there exist p,q ∈ V G such that f(p)=v and f(q)=w, since f is onto. Furthermore, there is an edge joining p to q, since f(p) Rf(q). So this edge in E G maps to a via β. To show that β is one-to-one, suppose e 1 ,e 2 ∈E G with β(e 1 )=β(e 2 ). Let x 1 ,y 1 and x 2 ,y 2 be the vertices joined by e 1 and e 2 , respectively. Then β(e 1 ) joins f(x 1 )tof(y 1 ), and it also joins f(x 2 )tof(y 2 ). Therefore f(x 1 )=f(x 2 ) and f(y 1 )=f(y 2 ), so x 1 = y 1 and x 2 = y 2 , since f is one-to-one. Since G has no multiple edges, e 1 = e 2 . We have shown that β is a one-to-one correspondence. By the way we deﬁned β, e joins vertex v to vertex w ⇔ β(e) joins vertex α(v) to vertex α(w). so G ∼ = H. square It is usually tricky to prove that two graphs are isomorphic, but it is less tricky to use Theorem 2.5 than Deﬁnition 2.12. To check that the two graphs in Figure 2.24 are isomorphic using the theorem, we only need to deﬁne a function f on on vertices by f(x i )=y i . Since each pair of vertices deﬁnes at most one edge, there is no need for a separate function on edges. Of course, we must also check that f is a one-to-one correspondence, and that an edge joins x i to x j whenever an edge joins y i to y j . It follows immediately from the deﬁnition that isomorphic graphs must have the same number of vertices and the same number of edges. It is also true, buthardertoshow,thatcorrespondingverticesofisomorphicgraphsmusthave the same degree. This is left as Exercise 1. In fact, an isomorphism between two graphs guarantees that the graphs share any property having to do with the structure of the graph. For example, if G ∼ = H, and G has an Euler circuit, then so does H.IfG is planar, so is H. The only diﬀerences between isomorphic graphs lie in the way they are labeled and drawn. 2.6.3 Degree Counting In Section 2.1, we stated several observations of Euler, which we now make precisewithmodernstatementsandproofs.Theﬁrsttheoremdescribesauseful

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 130 — #70 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 130 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking condition on the degrees of the vertices in any graph. First we must be precise about the meaning of “degree.” Deﬁnition 2.13 Let G be an undirected graph, and let x ∈ V G be a vertex. Let D 1 be the set of all edges e∈E G such that i(e)=(x,b) for some b, and let D 2 be the set of all edges e∈E G such that i(e)=(a,x) for some a. Then the degree of x is |D 1 |+|D 2 |. Inotherwords,inanundirectedgraph,thedegreeofavertexisthenumber of edges that join to it, where loops are counted twice. It is left as an exercise to write down similar deﬁnitions for the indegree and outdegree of a vertex in a directed graph. Theorem 2.6 Let G be an undirected graph. The sum of the degrees of the vertices of G equals twice the number of edges in G. Proof Since each edge joins two vertices (or possibly a single vertex to itself), each edge contributes 2 to the sum of the degrees of the vertices. square This simple theorem is surprisingly useful. In the discussion of the K¨onigs- berg bridges, it tells us that it is impossible to have exactly one island with an odd number of bridges to it: if one vertex had odd degree and the rest even, the sum of the degrees would be odd, contradicting the theorem. By the same reasoning, the number of odd-degree vertices must be even. Example 2.56 Thereare11teamsinabroomballleague.Theleagueorganizer decidesthateachteamwillplayﬁvegamesagainstdiﬀerentopponents.Explain why this idea won’t work. Solution: The situation can be modeled by a graph. The 11 teams are the ver- tices, and the edges join pairs of teams that will play each other. Since the organizer wants each team to play ﬁve games, the degree of each vertex is 5. This means that the sum of the degrees of the vertices is 55, contradicting Theorem 2.6. ♦ One thing to notice about this problem is that we were able to model and solve this problem using graphs, but we never had to actually try to draw the graph. Theorems (like 2.6) that tell you when you can’t do something can save you a lot of work. 2.6.4 Euler Paths and Circuits Recall the deﬁnitions of paths and circuits.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 131 — #71 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.6 Graph Theory 131 Deﬁnition 2.14 Let G be a graph. A path in G is a sequence v 0 ,e 1 ,v 1 ,e 2 ,v 2 ,...,v n−1 ,e n ,v n ofvertices v i andedges e i suchthatedge e i joinsvertex v i−1 tovertex v i ,where n ≥ 1. A circuit is path with v 0 = v n . A path or a circuit is called simple if e 1 ,e 2 ,...,e n are all distinct. Recall that a graph is connected if there is a path connecting any two pairs of vertices. An Euler path (resp. Euler circuit) in a graph G is a simple path (resp. simple circuit) using all the edges of G. Euler’s theorems on these constructions are interesting because they describe local conditions (the degrees of vertices) that completely determine the existence of a global object (an Euler path or circuit). Such theorems should surprise us; they are amazing in the same way that taking the temperature of the area under our tongue can tell us that our immune system is ﬁghting oﬀ a virus. Euler managed to discover the perfect “symptom” to test. Theorem 2.7 If all the vertices of a connected graph G have even degree, then G has an Euler circuit. Proof Choose any vertex v of G. Follow a sequence of contiguous edges and vertices, starting with v, without repeating any edges. Since every vertex has even degree, this sequence will never get stuck at any vertex w negationslash= v, because any edge we follow in to w will have another edge to follow out from w. Since there are a ﬁnite number of edges, this sequence must end, so it must produce a circuit ending at v. Call this circuit C 1 . IfC 1 containsalltheedgesofG,wearedone.Ifnot,removetheedgesofC 1 fromG.TheresultinggraphG prime willstillhaveallverticesofevendegree,because every edge in C 1 going in to a vertex had a matching edge going out. Now repeat the construction of the previous paragraph on G prime to get another circuit C 2 . Continue repeating this construction, producing circuits C 3 ,C 4 ,...,C k , until all the edges have been used. By construction, every edge of G appears exactly once in the list of circuits C 1 ,C 2 ,...,C k . Since G is connected, every circuit C i must share a vertex with someothercircuit C j .WecanthereforecombineanysuchpairC i ,C j ofcircuits into a new circuit by starting at this common vertex, following circuit C i , and thenfollowingC j .Thiscombiningprocessreducesthenumberofcircuitsonour list by one. Continue until one circuit remains. By construction, this remaining circuit is an Euler circuit. square The preceding is an example of a constructive proof; it describes how to construct the hypothesized object. As such, this proof has added value because it gives us a way to tell a computer how to produce an Euler circuit. The kind

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 132 — #72 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 132 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking of exact language required to write a proof is similar to the kind of instructions you need to give to a computer to get it to do what you want. The converse of Theorem 2.7 is also true, and easier to prove. Theorem 2.8 If a graph G has an Euler circuit, then all the vertices of G have even degree. Proof Let v be a vertex in G. If the degree of v is zero, there is nothing to prove. If the degree of v is nonzero, then some edges on the Euler circuit touch it, and since the Euler circuit contains all of G’s edges, the number of touches by these edges equals the degree of v. If we traverse the circuit, starting and ending at v, we must leave v the same number of times as we return to v. Therefore the number of touches by an edge in the Euler circuit is even. square Euler’s observations about paths have related proofs. These are left as exercises. 2.6.5 Hamilton Paths and Circuits Euler’s theorems tell us just about all there is to know about the existence of paths and circuits that visit every edge of a graph exactly once. So it is natural to ask the same questions about paths and circuits that visit every vertex of a graph exactly once. These constructions are named in honor of the nineteenth-century Irish mathematician William Rowan Hamilton. Deﬁnition 2.15 A Hamilton path in a graph G is a path v 0 ,e 1 ,v 1 ,e 2 ,...,e n ,v n such that v 0 ,v 1 ,...,v n is a duplicate-free list of all the vertices in G. A Hamil- ton circuit is a circuit v 0 ,e 1 ,v 1 ,e 2 ,...,e n ,v n ,e n+1 ,v 0 , where v 0 ,e 1 ,v 1 ,e 2 ,..., e n ,v n is a Hamilton path. Although it is easy to tell whether a given graph has an Euler circuit, it is actuallyquitediﬃcult,ingeneral,todeterminewhetheragraphhasaHamilton circuit. For graphs without too many vertices, it usually isn’t hard to ﬁnd a Hamilton circuit when it is possible to do so. However, for graphs that don’t have Hamilton circuits, it is often very tricky to prove that this is the case. The next two examples illustrate this phenomenon. Example 2.57 Find a Hamilton circuit in the graph in Figure 2.25. Solution: One possible Hamilton circuit can be found as follows. (Try this with a piece of tracing paper.) Starting at vertex a, travel counterclockwise around

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 133 — #73 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.6 Graph Theory 133 bc d a e f o n m tr s pq h g j i l k Figure2.25 CanyouﬁndaHamiltoncircuitinthisgraph?SeeExample2.57. the outer ring. Notice that you can’t go back to a until you have visited all the vertices, so you will need to change direction when you get to e. Go from e to f, and then go around clockwise from there, but you must change direction again at i in order to leave room to get back to a. Then it is easy to see how to ﬁnish. The sequence of vertices a,b,c,d,e,f,o,n,m,l,k,j,i,r,s,t,p,q,g,h,a forms a Hamilton circuit. ♦ Example 2.58 Prove that the graph in Figure 2.26 has no Hamilton circuit. Proof Notice that this graph has ﬁve vertices of degree 2: f,h,j,l,n.Any Hamilton circuit must pass through these vertices, so it must include the edges that touch these vertices. But this makes it impossible to leave the outer ring: wecan’taddedgestothoseforcedbytheverticesf,h,j,l,nbecausethatwould f o n m tr s pq h g j i l k Figure 2.26 Why is there no Hamilton circuit in this graph? See Exam- ple 2.58.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 134 — #74 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 134 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking involve including three edges at some vertex, which can’t happen in a Hamilton circuit: if a single vertex touches three edges in a path, the vertex must occur twice in that path. square The previous two arguments are ad hoc; they don’t generalize well to other examples the way Euler’s theorems do. There are existence theorems about Hamilton circuits, but they are quite diﬃcult to prove, and they don’t give a complete characterization of graphs containing Hamilton circuits. In fact, the problem of ﬁnding a Hamilton circuit in a graph belongs to a famous class of problems called NP-complete. Roughly speaking, these are problems that are diﬃcult to solve, but whose solutions are easy to check. 5 It may not be clear whether a given graph has a Hamilton circuit, but it is really easy to check the answer of a student who claims to have found one. Euler and Hamilton circuits raise interesting mathematical questions, but they also have several important applications. For example, consider a graph model of a network of roads (edges) connecting various points of interest (ver- tices). A street cleaner would be interested in an Euler circuit, because it would provide a way to go down every street without having to retrace any steps. On the other hand, a salesperson wanting an eﬃcient route through each point of interest might ﬁnd a Hamilton circuit more useful. 2.6.6 Trees InSection2.1,wesawhowtoorganizedatausingabinarysearchtree.Infuture chapters, we will see several other uses for trees of various types. We wrap up our look at the mathematical theory of graphs with some theorems about trees in general. Deﬁnition 2.16 A tree is a graph T with a speciﬁed vertex r, called the root, with the property that, for any vertex v in T (vnegationslash= r), there is a unique simple path from r to v. This deﬁnition works for directed or undirected graphs. Usually we draw trees as undirected graphs, but we often draw the tree with the root at the top and an implicit downward direction on all the edges. The next theorem gives an alternate characterization of a tree. Theorem 2.9 Let G be an undirected graph, and let r ∈G. Then G is a tree with root r if and only if G is connected and has no simple circuits. 5.WewillsaymoreaboutNP-completenessinChapter5.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 135 — #75 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.6 Graph Theory 135 Proof (⇒) Suppose that G is an undirected tree with root r. Let a,b be two vertices in G. By Deﬁnition 2.16, there are paths from r to a and r to b. Therefore, there is a path from a to b via r,soG is connected. Suppose, to the contrary, that v 0 ,e 1 ,v 1 ,e 2 ,...,v k−1 ,e k ,v 0 is a simple circuit in G. We can relabel this circuit, if necessary, so that v 0 negationslash= r. If r = v i for some i, then v 0 ,e 1 ,...,r and r,e i+1 ,...,e k ,v 0 are two diﬀerent simple paths from v 0 to r, contradicting the deﬁnition of a tree. If rnegationslash= v i for any i, then there is a simple path from r to v 0 , and combining this path with the sequence e 1 ,v 1 ,e 2 ,...,v k−1 ,e k ,v 0 yields another simple path from r to v 0 , a contradiction. (⇐) Now suppose that G is a connected undirected graph with no simple circuits. Let vnegationslash= r be a vertex in G. Since G is connected, there is a path from r to v. If this path does not repeat any vertices, then it does not repeat any edges, so it is simple. If this path has the form r,e 1 ,...,e i ,a,e i+1 ,...,e k ,a,e k+1 ,...,e n ,v for some vertex a, then we can replace it with a shorter path r,e 1 ,...,e i ,a,e k+1 ,...,e n ,v thatstillgoesfromr tov.Furthermore,wecanrepeatthisshorteningprocedure until there are no repeated vertices. So there is a simple path from r to v.To show that G is a tree with root r, we need to show that this path is unique. But if there were two distinct simple paths r,e 1 ,v 1 ,...,v n−1 ,e n ,v and r,d 1 ,w 1 ,...,w m−1 ,d m ,v from r to v, we could combine them to form a circuit r,e 1 ,v 1 ,...,v n−1 ,e n ,v,d m ,w m−1 ,...,w 1 ,d 1 ,r in G. While this circuit may not be simple, it must contain a simple circuit, since there is at least one d i that diﬀers from all the e j ’s. (This detail is left as Exercise 19.) This contradicts that G has no simple circuits. square AnimportantconsequenceofTheorem2.9isthatyoucanchooseanyvertex tobetherootofanundirectedtree.Figure2.27showsthesameundirectedtree

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 136 — #76 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 136 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking r 2 r 2 r 2 r 1 r 1 r 1 (a) (b) (c) Figure 2.27 You can choose the root in an undirected tree. drawn three diﬀerent ways: ﬁrst (a) without a root, then (b) with root r 1 , and ﬁnally (c) with root r 2 . Imagine that the graph is made of beads and string. In graph (a), pick up the bead that you want to be the root (r 1 or r 2 ), and let the rest of the beads hang down to get graphs (b) or (c). This process is intuitively obvious, but the previous proof gives us a solid mathematical justiﬁcation: if a graph G is connected and has no simple circuits, it is a tree with root r, for any vertex r in G. And any undirected tree is a connected graph with no simple circuits, so any vertex can be the root. A corollary follows from this observation. Corollary 2.1 In an undirected tree, there is a unique simple path between any two vertices in the tree. Proof Let a,b be two vertices in an undirected tree T. Then T can be viewed as a tree with root a, so by Deﬁnition 2.16 there is a unique simple path from a to b. square ThecharacterizationoftreesinDeﬁnition2.16impliesquitealotaboutthe structure of these graphs. Let v be a nonroot vertex of a tree T. Since there is a unique simple path from the root r of T to v, there is a well-deﬁned natural number d(v) that equals the number of edges in this path. Call the number d(v) the depth of the vertex v. By convention, d(r) = 0. The height of the tree T is the maximum value of d(v) over all the vertices v in T. For example, the tree in Figure 2.27(c) has height 4, and d(r 1 ) = 2 in this tree. Of course, the depth function and the height of a tree depend on the choice of root; the tree in Figure 2.27(b) has height 3. Another implication of the deﬁnition is that we can make an undirected tree into a tree in a well-deﬁned way, by choosing a direction on each edge away from the root. More precisely, start at the root, and direct each edge outward. These edges will end in vertices of depth 1, and all the vertices of depth 1 will now have directed edges to them. Repeat this process, forming directed edges

Unknown

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 137 — #77 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.6 Graph Theory 137 to all the vertices of depth 2, then 3, etc., until all the vertices (and hence all the edges) have been covered. Thus, every edge will point from a vertex of depth i to a vertex of depth i+1. This construction explains why it isn’t really necessary to draw the directions on the edges of a tree, as long as we designate a root. It also helps us prove the following fact. Theorem 2.10 Let T be a tree with n vertices. Then T has n−1 edges. Proof Suppose T is a tree with n vertices, and let r be the root of T. By the above construction, we can make T into a directed tree, if necessary, without changing the number of edges and vertices. Every edge must point to a nonroot vertex.Furthermore,everynonrootvertexhasasingleedgepointingtoit,since there is a unique path to each vertex from the root. So the number of edges equals the number of nonroot vertices: n−1. square Exercises 2.6 1. See Deﬁnitions 2.12 and 2.13. Let G and H be isomorphic, undirected graphs with vertex bijection α and edge bijection β. Let x ∈ V G be a vertex in G. Prove that the degree of x equals the degree of α(x). 2. Draw two nonisomorphic, undirected graphs, each having four vertices and four edges. Explain how you know they are not isomorphic. 3. Findapair,G and H,ofisomorphicgraphsamongthefourgraphsbelow, and give the one-to-one correspondence α: V G −→ V H of vertices. (For each vertex of G, tell which vertex of H to which it corresponds.) bcd aeif ghp o j r u s t q nmlk 4. Give a rigorous deﬁnition for the indegree and outdegree of a vertex in a directed graph. (Model your deﬁnition on Deﬁnition 2.13.) 5. Let X be a ﬁnite set, and let P(X) be the power set of X. Let G be the graph whose vertices represent the elements of P(X), where A and

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 138 — #78 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 138 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking B are joined by an edge if A∩B =∅. Similarly, let H be the graph with a vertex for each element of P(X), but where A and B share an edge if A∪B = X. Prove that G is isomorphic to H. 6. Let (X 1 ,R 1 ) and (X 2 ,R 2 ) be isomorphic partial orders. Let G 1 and G 2 be their respective associated graphs, as deﬁned in Deﬁnition 2.5. Prove that G 1 and G 2 are isomorphic graphs. 7. Let R 1 and R 2 be relations on a set X. Give a reasonable deﬁnition for an isomorphism of relations. 8. Between 1970 and 1975, the National Football League was divided into two conferences, with 13 teams in each conference. Each team played 14 games in a season. Would it have been possible for each team to play 11 games against teams from its own conference and 3 games against teams from the other conference? Use a graph model to answer this question (without drawing the graph). 9. A league of 10 teams is playing a “round-robin” style tournament, where each team plays every other team exactly once. How many games total need to be played? Justify your answer using a graph model—say what theverticesandedgesofyourgraphrepresent,andwhat(ifany)theorems you use. 10. The complete graph on n vertices (denoted K n ) is the undirected graph with exactly one edge between every pair of distinct vertices. Use Theo- rem 2.6 to derive a formula for the number of edges in K n . 11. A truncated icosidodecahedron (also known as a “great rhombicosidodec- ahedron” or “omnitruncated icosidodecahedron”) is a polyhedron with 120 vertices. Each vertex looks the same: a square, a hexagon, and a decagon come together at each vertex. How many edges does a truncated icosidodecahedron have? Explain how you arrive at your answer. (Note: the picture in Figure 2.28 doesn’t show the vertices or edges on the back of the polyhedron.) Figure 2.28 A truncated icosidodecahedron. See Exercises 11 and 14.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 139 — #79 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 2.6 Graph Theory 139 12. Prove the following theorem of Euler. Theorem 2.11 If a connected graph has exactly two vertices v and w of odd degree, then there is an Euler path from v to w. Hint: Add an edge, and use Theorem 2.7. 13. Prove the following theorem of Euler. Theorem 2.12 If a graph has more than two vertices of odd degree, it does not have an Euler path. Hint:Tryaproofbycontradiction,andmodelyourargumentontheproof of Theorem 2.8. 14. Is there an Euler path on the graph formed by the vertices and edges of a truncated icosidodecahedron? Why or why not? 15. Prove that K n , the complete graph on n vertices, has a Hamilton circuit for all n≥3. 16. For what values of n does K n have an Euler circuit? Explain. 17. Find a Hamilton circuit in the following graph. 18. Explain why the following graph does not have a Hamilton circuit. abc de fgh 19. FinishtheproofofTheorem2.9byprovingthat,ifagraphGhasacircuit with some edge e that diﬀers from all the other edges in the circuit, then G has a simple circuit. (Hint: Focus on the sequence of vertices in the given circuit.) 20. Copy the three graphs from Figure 2.27 and label the vertices to show that the graphs are isomorphic.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH02˙Hunter” — 2008/10/15 — 5:03 — page 140 — #80 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 140 Chapter 2 a73 Relational Thinking 21. Let G be a graph with vertex set V G and edge set E G .Asubgraph of G is a graph with vertex set V H ⊆V G and edge set E H ⊆E G . Write down all the subgraphs of the following graph. 22. Let G be a graph with vertex set V G and edge set E G . Let V ⊆V G and E ⊆ E G . Is there always a subgraph of G with vertex set V and edge set E? Explain. 23. Let G be a connected, undirected graph. Prove that there is a subgraph T of G such that T contains all the vertices of G, and T is a tree. (Such a subgraphiscalledaspanning tree.)Giveaconstructiveproofthatexplains how to construct a spanning tree of a graph.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 141 — #1 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ Chapter 3 Recursive Thinking The branches of a blue spruce tree (Figure 3.1) follow an interesting pattern. The trunk of the tree is a large central stem, with branches coming oﬀ each side. These branches also have thinner stems coming oﬀ them, and so on, until you Figure 3.1 A recursive blue spruce. 141

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 142 — #2 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 142 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking reach the level of the needles. A branch looks like a smaller copy of the whole tree, and even a small twig looks like a miniature branch. This is a picture of recursion. The natural phenomenon of recursion pervadesmany areasof mathematics. In this chapter, you will learn how to work with recursive structures. You will develop the ability to see recursive patterns in mathematical objects. And you will study mathematical induction, a powerful tool for proving theorems about recursive structures. 3.1 Recurrence Relations 3.1.1 Deﬁnition and Examples The simplest and most concrete type of recursive object in mathematics is a recurrence relation. Suppose we wish to deﬁne a function P: N −→ Z that inputsa natural number and returnsan integer. The easiest way to do thisisto give an explicit formula: P(n)= n(n+1) 2 . (3.1.1) To evaluate P(n) for some given n, you just plug n into the formula. It isalwaysnice to have an explicit formula for a function, but sometimes these are hard to come by. Sometimesa function comesup in mathematicsthat isnatural to deﬁne recursively. Here isa second way of deﬁning our function P(n): P(n)= braceleftBigg 1ifn=1 n+P(n−1) if n>1. (3.1.2) Thisisa recursive deﬁnition because P isdeﬁned in termsof itself: P occurs in the formula that deﬁnes P. This may seem a little sneaky, but it is perfectly legal. For any n ∈ N, we can use the deﬁnition in Equation 3.1.2 to compute P(n). Example 3.1 Use Equation 3.1.2 to compute P(5). Solution: We’ll compute P(5) two diﬀerent ways. The ﬁrst approach is called ‘‘bottom-up” because we start at the bottom with P(1) and work our way up to P(5). By the ﬁrst part of the deﬁnition, P(1) = 1. By the second part of the deﬁnition, with n= 2, we get P(2)=2+P(1) = 2 + 1 = 3. Again, by the second part with n =3,P(3) = 3 +P(2) = 3 + 3 = 6. Repeating this process, P(4) = 4 + 6 = 10, and ﬁnally, P(5) = 5 + 10 = 15.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 143 — #3 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.1 Recurrence Relations 143 Alternatively, we can do a ‘‘top-down” computation. Whenever n>1, we can apply the second part of the function deﬁnition to replace “P(n)” with “n+P(n−1).” This replacement justiﬁes the ﬁrst four uses of the = sign. P(5) = 5 +P(4) =5+4+P(3) =5+4+3+P(2) =5+4+3+2+P(1) =5+4+3+2+1 =15. The second-to-last = sign is the result of applying the ﬁrst part of the deﬁnition to replace “P(1)” with “1.” ♦ Note that the equation P(n)=n+P(n−1) by itself would not deﬁne a recurrence relation, because the bottom-up calcu- lation could never get started, and the top-down calculation would never stop. A well-deﬁned recurrence relation needsa nonrecursive base case that givesat least one value of the function explicitly. 3.1.2 The Fibonacci Sequence One of the earliest examples of recursive thinking is the famous Fibonacci se- quence. In the early 13 th century, the Italian mathematician Leonardo Pisano 1 Fibonacci proposed the following problem. [10] A certain man put a pair of rabbits in a place surrounded on all sides by a wall. How many pairsof rabbitscan be produced from that pair in a year if it is supposed that every month each pair begets a new pair which from the second month on becomes productive? LetF(n) represent the number of pairs of rabbits present on monthn. Assuming that it takestwo monthsfor the ﬁrst pair of rabbitsto become productive, we have F(1) =F(2) = 1 as a base case, and the ﬁrst pair of oﬀspring show up on the third month, so F(3) = 2. Every month, the number of new pairsof rabbitsequalsthe number of rabbitspresent two monthsbefore. So we can deﬁne a recurrence relation as follows. 1. “Pisano” means “of Pisa.” In fact, if you visit Pisa, Italy, you will ﬁnd a statue of Fibonacci in the Camposanto, near the famous leaningtower.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 144 — #4 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 144 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking Deﬁnition 3.1 The Fibonacci numbers F(n) satisfy the following recurrence relation: F(n)= braceleftBigg 1ifn=1orn=2 F(n−1) +F(n−2) if n>2. The sequence F(1),F(2),F(3),... iscalled the Fibonacci sequence. The second part of this deﬁnition, F(n)=F(n−1)+F(n−2), isthe recursive part. The F(n− 1) term represents the number of rabbit pairs present the previousmonth. The F(n−2) term represents the number of new rabbit pairs— equal to the number of rabbit pairspresent two monthsago. Therefore the sum of these two termsisthe total number of rabbit pairspresent for month n, the current month. The ﬁrst few terms of the famous Fibonacci sequence are then 1,1,2,3,5,8,13,21,34,.... Despite its somewhat whimsical origins, the Fibonacci sequence has a re- markable number of applications. Thissequence of numbersisfound in a vari- ety of contexts, including plant growth, stock prices, architecture, music, and drainage patterns. Example 3.2 The pine cone in Figure 3.2 containsFibonacci numbers. No- tice the spiral patterns emanating out from the center, both in clockwise and counterclockwise directions. There are F(6) = 8 counterclockwise spirals and F(7) = 13 clockwise spirals. This isn’t merely coincidental; Fibonacci patterns are often found in nature where growth occurs in stages, with each successive stage dependent on previous stages. The recursive nature of plant growth is reﬂected in the presence of recursively deﬁned sequences. The study of leaf pat- ternsin plantsiscalled phyllotaxis, and the more general study of how shapes form in living thingsiscalled morphogenesis. These studies apply recursive ideas. 3.1.3 Modeling with Recurrence Relations Fibonacci’srabbit example showshow to think recursively about a problem by describing it with a recurrence relation. Remember that any recurrence relation has two parts: a base case that describes some initial conditions, and a recursive case that describes a future value in terms of previous values. Armed with this way of thinking, we can model other problems using recurrence relations. Example 3.3 Ursula the Usurer lends money at outrageous rates of interest. She demandsto be paid 10% interest per week on a loan, compounded weekly. Suppose you borrow $500 from Ursula. If you wait four weeks to pay her back, how much will you owe?

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 145 — #5 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.1 Recurrence Relations 145 Figure 3.2 Fibonacci numbersappear in many diﬀerent kindsof plant growth, including this pine cone. Image courtesy of Pau Atela and Christophe Gol´e. [3] Solution: Let M(n) be how much money you owe Ursula on the nth week. Initially, you owe $500, so M(0) = 500. Each subsequent week, the amount you owe increases by 10%. Therefore, we have the following recurrence relation: M(n)= braceleftBigg 500 if n=0 1.10·M(n−1) if n>0. Then the amount you owe after four weeksis M(4) = 1.10·M(3) =1.10·1.10·M(2) =1.10·1.10·1.10·M(1) =1.10·1.10·1.10·1.10·M(0) =1.10·1.10·1.10·1.10·500 = $732.05. ♦ Example 3.4 If you have ever tried making patternswith a collection of coins, you have probably noticed that you can make hexagonsin a natural way by packing circlesastightly aspossible. Figure 3.3 showshow 19 circlesﬁt into a hexagonal shape with 3 circles on each edge. Let H(n) be the number of circles you need to form a hexagon with n circleson each edge. From Figure 3.3, it is clear that H(2) = 7 and H(3) = 19. Find a recurrence relation for H(n). Solution: The base case of the recurrence relation could be H(2) = 7, or we could agree thatH(1) = 1, representing a “trivial” hexagon with just one circle.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 146 — #6 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 146 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking Figure 3.3 Circlespacked to form a hexagon. For the recursive case, we need to describe how to make a hexagonal pattern of edge size n from a hexagonal pattern of edge size n− 1. We would need to add six edges, each made up of n circles, but each circle on a vertex of the new hexagon will be included in two edges. Thusthe number of circlesadded will be 6n− 6; subtracting 6 accounts for double-counting the circles on the vertices. Thisgivesthe following recurrence relation: H(n)= braceleftBigg 1ifn=1 H(n−1)+6n−6ifn>1. If you don’t quite believe in this formula, try some calculations:H(2) =H(1)+ 6·2−6=7,H(3) =H(2)+6·3−6 = 19, etc. ♦ To construct a recurrence relation, it often helps to see how successive casesof the problem are built on previousones, like the layersof an onion. The recurrence relation describeshow to count the next layer in termsof the previousone(s). If P(n) is the function we want to describe recursively, think of P(n) asthe general case of the problem, while P(n−1) represents the next simplest case. The recursive part of the recurrence relation is then an equation of the form P(n) = some function of P(n−1) and n that describes how to add a layer to your onion. The next few examples illus- trate thisparadigm. Example 3.5 LetX be a ﬁnite set withnelements. Find a recurrence relation C(n) for the number of elementsin the power set P(X). Solution: The base case is when n = 0 and X is the empty set, in which case P(X)={∅},soC(0) = 1. Now suppose |X| = n for some n>0. Choose some element x ∈ X and let X prime = X \{x}. Then X prime has n− 1 elements, so |P(X prime )| =C(n−1). Furthermore, every subset of X is either a subset of X prime ,or

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 147 — #7 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.1 Recurrence Relations 147 a subset of the form U∪{x}, where U ⊆X prime , and these two cases are mutually exclusive. Therefore P(X) hastwice asmany elementsas P(X prime ). So C(n)= braceleftBigg 1ifn=0 2·C(n−1) if n>0 isa recurrence relation for |P(X)|. ♦ Recall that the depth d(v) of a vertex v in a binary tree isthe number of edgesin the path from the root to v. The height of a binary tree isthe maximum value of d(v) over all the verticesin the tree. Example 3.6 Call a binary tree complete if every leaf hasdepth n and every nonleaf node hastwo children. For example, isa complete binary tree of height 3. Let T be a complete binary tree of height n. Find a recurrence relation V(n) for the number of nodesin T. Solution: Notice that a complete tree of height n hastwo complete treesof height n−1 inside of it. T 1 T 2 In addition to the nodesin T 1 and T 2 , there isone more node: the root. There- fore a complete binary tree of height n has V(n)= braceleftBigg 1ifn=0 2·V(n−1)+1 ifn>0 nodes. ♦ Example 3.7 Recall that the complete graph K n on n verticesisthe undi- rected graph that hasexactly one edge between every pair of vertices. Find a recurrence relation E(n) for the number of edgesin K n . Solution: Given a complete graph on n− 1 vertices, we can add a vertex and edgesto make a complete graph on n vertices. We need to add n− 1 new edges, because the new vertex needs to be connected to all of the vertices of

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 148 — #8 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 148 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking the original given graph. For example, the following ﬁgure shows how to make K 5 from K 4 . v The new vertex islabeled v, and the four new edgesare dashed. A complete graph on one vertex has no edges, so we obtain the following recurrence relation: E(n)= braceleftBigg 0ifn=1 E(n−1) +n−1ifn>1. ♦ Look back at these last three examples, and see if you can recognize the recursive way of thinking. A power set contains all the elements of a smaller power set, and more. A complete binary tree has two smaller complete binary treesinside it. And a complete graph on n− 1 verticescan be augmented to form a complete graph on n vertices. The hard part of these problems was identifying the recursive structure in these objects; this structure made writing down the recurrence relation a fairly straightforward task. Exercises 3.1 1. Refer to the recurrence relation for the Fibonacci sequence in Deﬁni- tion 3.1. (a) Answer Fibonacci’s question by calculating F(12). (b) Write F(1000) in termsof F(999) and F(998). (c) Write F(1000) in termsof F(998) and F(997). 2. In Fibonacci’smodel, rabbitslive forever. The following modiﬁcation of Deﬁnition 3.1 accountsfor dying rabbits: G(n)=      0ifn≤ 0 1in=1orn=2 G(n−1) +G(n−2)−G(n−8) if n>2.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 149 — #9 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.1 Recurrence Relations 149 (a) Compute G(n) for n=1,2,...,12. (b) In thismodiﬁed model, how long do rabbitslive? 3. Consider the following recurrence relation: H(n)=      0ifn≤ 0 1in=1orn=2 H(n−1) +H(n−2)−H(n−3) if n>2. (a) Compute H(n) for n=1,2,...,10. (b) Using the pattern from part (a), guess what H(100) is. 4. The Lucas numbers L(n) have almost the same deﬁnition as the Fibonacci numbers: L(n)=      1ifn=1 3in=2 L(n−1) +L(n−2) if n>2. (a) How isthe deﬁnition of L(n) diﬀerent from the deﬁnition of F(n)in Deﬁnition 3.1? (b) Compute the ﬁrst 12 Lucas numbers. 5. Compute the ﬁrst seven terms of the following recurrence relations: (a) C(n) of Example 3.5. (b) V(n) of Example 3.6. (c) E(n) of Example 3.7. 6. Consider the recurrence relation deﬁned in Example 3.3. Suppose that, as in the example, you borrow $500, but you pay her back $100 each week. Each week, Ursula charges you 10% interest on the amount you still owe, after your $100 payment istaken into account. (a) Write down a recurrence relation for M(n), the amount owed after n weeks. (b) How much will you owe after four weeks? 7. Every year, Alice getsa raise of $3,000 plus5% of her previousyear’s salary. Her starting salary is $50,000. Give a recurrence relation for S(n), Alice’ssalary after n years, for n≥ 0. 8. Suppose that today (year 0) your car is worth $10,000. Each year your car loses10% of itsvalue, but at the end of each year you add customizations to your car which increase its value by $50. Write a recurrence relation to model thissituation.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 150 — #10 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 150 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking 9. Refer to Example 3.4. Calculate H(7). 10. Circlescan be packed into the shape of an equilateral triangle. Let T(n) be the number of circlesneeded to form a triangle with n circleson each edge. From Figure 3.3 (or by experimenting with coins), it is easy to see that T(2) = 3 and T(3) = 6. Write down a recurrence relation for T(n). 11. Let H(n) be asin Example 3.4, and let T(n) be asin Exercise 10. Write H(n) in termsof T(n−1). Explain your reasoning. (Hint: use Figure 3.4.) Figure 3.4 Hint for Exercise 11. 12. Recall that the factorial function isdeﬁned as n!=1·2·3·····(n−1)·n and, by convention, 0! = 1. Give a recurrence relation for n!. 13. Let S(n)=1 2 +2 2 + ···+n 2 be the sum of the ﬁrst n perfect squares. Find a recurrence relation for S(n). 14. The ancient Indian game of Chaturanga—from which the modern game of chesswasapparently derived—wasplayed on a board with 64 squares. A certain folktale tells the story of a Raja who promised a reward of one grain of rice on the ﬁrst square of the board, two grains on the second square, four on the third, and so on, doubling the number of grains on each successive square. (a) Write a recurrence relation for R(n), the number of grainsof rice on the nth square. (b) ComputeR(64). Assuming a grain of rice weighs 25 milligrams, how many kilogramsof rice must be placed on the 64 th square? 15. Find recurrence relations that yield the following sequences: (a) 5,10,15,20,25,30,... (b) 5,11,18,26,35,45,...

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 151 — #11 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.1 Recurrence Relations 151 16. Let f: N −→ R be any function on the natural numbers. The sum of the ﬁrst n valuesof f(n) iswritten as n summationdisplay k=1 f(k)=f(1) +f(2) +···+f(n) in sigma notation. (a) Write 1 2 +2 2 +···+n 2 in sigma notation. (b) Give a recurrence relation for n summationdisplay k=1 f(k). 17. Let f: N −→ R be any function on the natural numbers. The product of the ﬁrst n valuesof f(n) iswritten as n productdisplay k=1 f(k)=f(1)·f(2)·····f(n) in product notation. (a) Write n! in product notation, for n>0. (b) Give a recurrence relation for n productdisplay k=1 f(k). 18. Calculus required. Use the reduction formula integraldisplay x n e x dx=x n e x −n integraldisplay x n−1 e x dx to give a simple (noncalculus) recurrence relation for I(n)= integraldisplay 1 0 x n e x dx where n≥ 0. Make sure that your recurrence relation has a base case. 19. Suppose we model the spread of a virus in a certain population as follows. On day 1, one person is infected. On each subsequent day, each infected person gives the cold to two others. (a) Write down a recurrence relation for thismodel. (b) What are some of the limitationsof thismodel? How doesit fail to be realistic? 20. Let X be a set with n elements. Let E ⊆P(X) be the set of all subsets of X with an even number of elements, and let O⊆P(X) be the subsets of X with an odd number of elements. Let E(n)=|E| and O(n)=|O|.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 152 — #12 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 152 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking (a) Find a recurrence relation forE(n) in termsof O(n−1) andE(n−1). (b) Find a recurrence relation forO(n) in termsof O(n−1) andE(n−1). (c) Find the ﬁrst ﬁve values of E(n) and O(n). 21. The complete bipartite graph K m,n isthe simple undirected graph with m+nvertices split into two setsV 1 andV 2 (|V 1 | =m, |V 2 | =n) such that vertices x,y share an edge if and only in x∈V 1 and y∈V 2 . For example, K 3,4 isthe following graph. (a) Find a recurrence relation for the number of edgesin K 3,n . (b) Find a recurrence relation for the number of edgesin K n,n . 3.2 Closed-Form Solutions and Induction Although recurrence relationshave a certain elegant quality, it can be tediousto compute with them. For example, armed only with Deﬁnition 3.1, it would take 998 steps to compute the Fibonacci number F(1000). In thissection we will explore ways to ﬁnd a nonrecursive closed-form solution to a recurrence relation. Much more than appears here could be said about solving recurrence relations. The essential concept in this section is the idea of mathematical induction, the method by which we verify the correctness of a closed-form solution. 3.2.1 Guessing a Closed-Form Solution Suppose thatP(n) isa function deﬁned by a recurrence relation. We would like to have an expression P(n) = a nonrecursive function of n because then we could just calculate P(n) by plugging n into the formula, rather than by using the recurrence relation over and over. A formula like this iscalled a closed-form solution to the recurrence relation. Recall Example 3.1: we found that the ﬁrst ﬁve values of the recurrence relation P(n)= braceleftBigg 1ifn=1 n+P(n−1) if n>1

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 153 — #13 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.2 Closed-Form Solutions and Induction 153 were 1,3,6,10, and 15. A closed-form solution to this recurrence relation is P(n)= n(n+1) 2 . We can check that the valuesof P(n) given by thisnonrecursive formula match the valuesgiven by the recurrence relation: n 1 2 3 4 5 n(n+1) 2 1 3 6 10 15 . Thistable of valuesispretty convincing evidence that we have found the right closed-form solution, but it is not a proof. Later in this section we will see how to verify that such a solution is correct, but ﬁrst we will consider the problem of ﬁnding closed-form solutions. Given a recurrence relation, the most general way of ﬁnding a closed-form solution is by guessing. Unfortunately, this is also the hardest technique to master. Example 3.8 Find a closed-form solution for the recurrence relation from Ex- ample 3.3: M(n)= braceleftBigg 500 if n=0 1.10·M(n−1) if n>0. (3.2.1) Solution: It almost alwayshelpsto write out the ﬁrst few valuesof M(n). In this case, it also helps to leave things unsimpliﬁed: the pattern is easier to see if you don’t multiply out the terms. M(0) = 500 M(1) = 500·1.10 = 500(1.10) 1 M(2) = 500·1.10·1.10 = 500(1.10) 2 M(3) = 500·1.10·1.10·1.10 = 500(1.10) 3 M(4) = 500·1.10·1.10·1.10·1.10 = 500(1.10) 4 . The evident pattern in these calculations suggests that M(n) = 500(1.10) n (3.2.2) is a closed-form solution to the recurrence relation. ♦ Please note: this only a guess. We haven’t proved that Equation 3.2.2 rep- resents the same function as Equation 3.2.1. There is still more work to do. Stay tuned.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 154 — #14 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 154 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking 3.2.2 Polynomial Sequences: Using Diﬀerences ‡ Finding a closed-form solution forP(n) can be thought of as guessing a formula for the sequence P(0),P(1),P(2),.... If we knew that P(n) = a polynomial function of n then it would be easier to guess at a formula. One way to detect such a sequence is to look at the diﬀerences between terms. Given any sequence a 0 ,a 1 ,a 2 ,a 3 ,...,a n−1 ,a n the diﬀerences a 1 −a 0 ,a 2 −a 1 ,a 3 −a 2 ,...,a n −a n−1 form another sequence, called the sequence of diﬀerences. A linear sequence will have a constant sequence of diﬀerences (because a line has constant slope). From calculus, we know that a quadratic sequence will have a linear sequence of diﬀerences, a cubic sequence will have a quadratic sequence of diﬀerences, etc. Given a sequence, we can calculate its sequence of diﬀerences, then calculate the sequence of diﬀerences of that, and so on. If we eventually end up with a constant sequence, then we have reason to believe that the original sequence isgiven by a polynomial function. The degree of the conjectured polynomial is the number of times we had to calculate the sequence of diﬀerences. The next example illustratesthistechnique. Example 3.9 Find a closed-form solution for the recurrence relation from Ex- ample 3.4: H(n)= braceleftBigg 1ifn=1 H(n−1)+6n−6ifn>1. (3.2.3) Solution: Calculate the ﬁrst few terms, and then look at sequences of diﬀerences: 1 7 19 37 61 91 logicalortextlogicalortextlogicalortextlogicalortextlogicalortext 612182430 logicalortextlogicalortextlogicalortextlogicalortext 6666 The second sequence of diﬀerences is constant. This suggests that the sequence may have a formula of the form H(n)=An 2 +Bn+C,

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 155 — #15 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.2 Closed-Form Solutions and Induction 155 so all we need to do is ﬁnd A, B, and C. Using H(1)=1,H(2) = 7, and H(3) = 19, we get a system of three equations in three variables: 1=A+B+C 7=4A+2B+C 19 = 9A+3B+C. Solving this system is a simple—but somewhat lengthy—exercise in algebra. (Add/subtract equations to eliminate variables, etc. We’ll omit the details.) The solution is A=3,B = −3, and C =1,so H(n)=3n 2 −3n+ 1 (3.2.4) is a good candidate for a closed-form solution. ♦ The technique of using sequences of diﬀerences is more of a “brute force” approach than pure guessing; there are certain mechanical procedures you go through in order to arrive at a formula. But the result of these procedures is still only a guess. To be sure that our guess is right, we need to prove that the formula matchesthe recurrence relation for all n. 3.2.3 Inductively Verifying a Solution If we use Equation 3.2.4 to calculate the ﬁrst six values ofH(n), we get 1, 7, 19, 37, 61, and 91. These numbers match the values given by the recurrence relation in Equation 3.2.3 perfectly. Thisispretty good evidence that Equation 3.2.4 is the correct closed-form solution for the recurrence relation. But this is not a proof. For all we know, the 7 th value won’t match, or the 8 th , or the 739 th . Without a proof, we can’t be sure. The general template for verifying a solution to a recurrence relation fol- lows. We have R(n) = some recurrence relation f(n) = hypothesized closed-form formula, and we would like to show thatR(n)=f(n) for all valuesof n. For the purposes of this discussion, let’s say that the ﬁrst value of n for which R(n) isdeﬁned is n = 1. As we have seen, recurrence relations usually start at n =1orn =0, but any starting value of n is possible. To prove that R(n)=f(n) for all n ≥ 1, we need to use the technique of mathematical induction. The idea of thiskind of proof isanalogousto climbing a staircase. Going up a staircase is a fairly repetitive task; if you know how to ascend one stairstep, you know how to ascend a staircase of any height. Of course, you need to start at the bottom of the staircase. In the proof, this is the base case.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 156 — #16 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 156 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking Base Case: Verify that R(1) =f(1). Checking the base case is usually fairly easy. After all, you probably wouldn’t have chosen f(n) as a candidate solution if it didn’t at least match for the case n=1. Next, you must be able to take one step up the staircase. Note that it doesn’t matter where on the staircase you are; taking one step up requires the same amount of skill, whether you are at the bottom, top, or somewhere in the middle. So let’s suppose, for the sake of the argument, you are standing on the (k−1)th stair. This is the inductive hypothesis. Inductive Hypothesis: Let k>1 be some (unspeciﬁed) integer. Suppose as inductive hypothesis that R(k−1) =f(k−1). The inductive hypothesis will be a crucial part of our proof. Any valid proof by induction must use the inductive hypothesis somewhere in its argument. Finally, you need to be able to go up to the next stairstep. See Figure 3.5. Inductive Step: Prove that R(k)=f(k). To do this, use the recurrence relation to compute the kth value. When you need to plug in the (k − 1)th value, use the inductive hypothesis. Then use algebra to show that the answer matches the closed form solution. k k – 1 1 2 3 Figure 3.5 The inductive step shows that you can climb up one stairstep. Why doesthiswork? An induction argument provesthe following assertion: Let k>1. If the recurrence relation matches the closed-form solution for n = k− 1, then the recurrence relation matches the closed-form solution for n=k. In other words, R(k−1) =f(k−1) ⇒ R(k)=f(k).

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 157 — #17 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.2 Closed-Form Solutions and Induction 157 Since our proof supposed an arbitrary value of k, we are allowed to apply this assertion for any particular value of k>1. Using k = 2, we get the assertion If the recurrence relation matches the closed-form solution forn= 1, then the recurrence relation matches the closed-form solution for n=2. But we know that the recurrence relation matches the closed-form solution for n = 1; this was the base case. Therefore the above assertion (and modus ponens) tellsusthat they match for n= 2. Now apply the assertion again, with k =3: If the recurrence relation matches the closed-form solution forn= 2, then the recurrence relation matches the closed-form solution for n=3. So we know they match for n = 3. By repeating thisargument, we can verify the cases n =4,5,6,..., up to whatever number we wish. In other words, the recurrence relation matches the closed-form solution for any value of n. Thisis exactly what we needed to show. In the symbols of logic, an induction argument establishes the following chain of implications: R(1) =f(1) ⇒R(2) =f(2) ⇒R(3) =f(3) ⇒R(4) =f(4) ⇒R(5) =f(5) ⇒···. The base case gets this chain of implications started, and since the inductive step works for any value of k, we are allowed to continue the chain of implica- tionsindeﬁnitely to conclude that R(n)=f(n) for any n ≥ 1. The following example shows what a typical proof by induction should look like. Example 3.10 Let H(n) be deﬁned by the following recurrence relation: H(n)= braceleftBigg 1ifn=1 H(n−1)+6n−6ifn>1. Let f(n)=3n 2 −3n+ 1. Prove that H(n)=f(n) for all n≥ 1. Proof We use induction on n. Base Case: If n = 1, the recurrence relation says that H(1) = 1, and the formula says that f(1) = 3·1 2 −3·1 + 1, which is1, so they match.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 158 — #18 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 158 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking Inductive Hypothesis: Suppose as inductive hypothesis that H(k−1) = 3(k−1) 2 −3(k−1)+1 for some k>1. Inductive Step: Using the recurrence relation, H(k)=H(k−1) + 6k−6, by the second part of the recurrence relation =3(k−1) 2 −3(k−1)+1+6k−6, by inductive hypothesis =3k 2 −6k+3−3k+3+1+6k−6 =3k 2 −3k+1. So, by induction, H(n)=f(n) for all n≥ 1. square The solution of Example 3.10 makes a good proof template for verifying a closed-form solution to a simple recurrence relation; such a proof almost always should look like this. The next example establishes a closed-form solution to the recurrence relation of Example 3.5 for the number of elementsin a power set. The proof is very similar to Example 3.10, but the induction starts atn=0 instead of n=1. Example 3.11 Let C(n) be deﬁned by the following recurrence relation: C(n)= braceleftBigg 1ifn=0 2·C(n−1) if n>0. Prove that C(n)=2 n for all n≥ 0. Proof We use induction on n. Let f(n)=2 n . Base Case: If n = 0, the recurrence relation says that C(0) = 1, and the formula says that f(0) = 2 0 =1,soC(0) =f(0). Inductive Hypothesis: Let k>0. Suppose as inductive hypothesis that C(k−1) = 2 k−1 . Inductive Step: Using the recurrence relation, C(k)=2·C(k−1), by the second part of the recurrence relation =2·2 k−1 , by inductive hypothesis =2 k . So, by induction, C(n)=2 n for all n≥ 0. square

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 159 — #19 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.2 Closed-Form Solutions and Induction 159 Take a moment to compare the proofsin Examples3.10 and 3.11. In the exercises at the end of this section, you should mimic these examples when you are asked to prove that a given recurrence relation has a given closed-form solution. It is important to master this standard type of proof. Mathematical induction isa diﬃcult topic. In thissection we have taken a very narrow view of the subject: verifying a closed-form solution. There are many other uses of mathematical induction, and these proofs can be quite challenging to write. The methodsin thissection will provide a foundation for more complicated inductive proofs. We end thissection with an example that showswhy proofsare important. Example 3.12 Let P(n) be deﬁned by the following recurrence relation: P(n)= braceleftBigg 1ifn=0 3·P(n−1)−(n−1) 2 if n>0. Does P(n)=(n+2)·2 n−1 for all n≥ 0? Solution: In order to show that (∀n≥ 0)(P(n)=(n+2)·2 n−1 ) isfalse, we need to show that its negation, (∃n≥ 0)(P(n) negationslash=(n+2)·2 n−1 ), istrue. That is, we need to ﬁnd a value of n for which the closed-form formula does not match the recurrence relation. Using the recurrence relation, a 0 =1 a 1 =3·1−(1−1) 2 =3 a 2 =3·3−(2−1) 2 =8 a 3 =3·8−(3−1) 2 =20 and using the closed-form formula, (0+2)·2 0−1 =1 (1+2)·2 1−1 =3 (2+2)·2 2−1 =8 (3+2)·2 3−1 =20, then the recurrence relation matches the closed-form solution for the ﬁrst four valuesof n. Remember that we have alwayssaid that, while thismay be good evidence that these two ways of calculating P(n) will alwaysagree, it isnot a proof. Indeed, if we persist in our calculations, we ﬁnd that a 4 =3·20−(4−1) 2 =51 while (4+2)·2 4−1 =48,

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 160 — #20 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 160 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking so the results do not match for n = 4. Therefore it isnot the case that P(n)=(n+2)·2 n−1 for all n≥ 0. ♦ Once you have found a counterexample to a statement, you know that the statement is false in general. But failure to ﬁnd a counterexample to a statement doesnot mean that the statement istrue. In the previousexample, we had to calculate ﬁve valuesof each formula to ﬁnd a mismatch, but it could have taken 50, or 500, or any number of valuesto ﬁnd our counterexample. Thisiswhy you will never know for sure that a closed-form formula matches a recurrence relation unless you prove it. Exercises 3.2 1. Prove that the closed form solution in Equation 3.2.2 matches the recur- rence relation in Equation 3.2.1. (See Example 3.8.) 2. Prove that the closed form solution in Equation 3.1.1 matches the recur- rence relation in Equation 3.1.2. (See page 142.) 3. Consider the following recurrence relation: B(n)= braceleftBigg 2ifn=1 3·B(n−1)+2 ifn>1. Use induction to prove that B(n)=3 n −1. 4. Consider the following recurrence relation: P(n)= braceleftBigg 0ifn=0 5·P(n−1)+1 ifn>1. Prove by induction that P(n)= 5 n −1 4 for all n≥ 0. 5. Consider the following recurrence relation: C(n)= braceleftBigg 0ifn=0 n+3·C(n−1) if n>0. Prove by induction that C(n)= 3 n+1 −2n−3 4 for all n≥ 0.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 161 — #21 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.2 Closed-Form Solutions and Induction 161 6. Guess a closed-form solution for the following recurrence relation: K(n)= braceleftBigg 1ifn=0 2·K(n−1)−n+1 ifn>0. Prove that your guess is correct. 7. Guess a closed-form solution for the following recurrence relation: P(n)= braceleftBigg 5ifn=0 P(n−1)+3 ifn>0. Prove that your guess is correct. 8. Consider the following recurrence relation: P(n)= braceleftBigg 1ifn=0 P(n−1) +n 2 if n>0. (a) Compute the ﬁrst eight values of P(n). (b) Analyze the sequences of diﬀerences. What does this suggest about the closed-form solution? (c) Find a good candidate for a closed-form solution. (d) Prove that your candidate solution is the correct closed-form solu- tion. 9. Consider the following recurrence relation: G(n)= braceleftBigg 1ifn=0 G(n−1)+2n−1ifn>0. (a) Calculate G(0), G(1), G(2), G(3), G(4), and G(5). (b) Use sequences of diﬀerences to guess at a closed-form solution for G(n). (c) Prove that your guess is correct. 10. Find a polynomial function f(n) such that f(1),f(2),...,f(8) isthe following sequence: 2,7,12,17,22,27,32,37. 11. Find a polynomial function f(n) such that f(1),f(2),...,f(8) isthe following sequence: 1,1,2,4,7,11,16,22.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 162 — #22 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 162 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking 12. Analyze the sequence 1,6,15,100,501,1746,4771,11040,22665,42526,74391 using sequences of diﬀerences. From what degree polynomial does this sequence appear to be drawn? (Don’t bother ﬁnding the coeﬃcients of the polynomial.) 13. Refer to Example 3.6. Guess at a closed-form solution to the recurrence relation for the number of nodesin a complete binary tree of height n. Prove that your guess is correct. 14. Refer to Example 3.7. Guess at a closed-form solution to the recurrence relation for the number of edgesin K n , the complete graph on n vertices. Prove that your guess is correct. 15. Guess a closed-form solution for the following recurrence relation: P(n)= braceleftBigg 1ifn=0 P(n−1) + 2 n if n>0. (Hint: Consider powersof 2.) Prove that your guessiscorrect. 16. Recall that n!=1·2·3···(n−1)·n for n>0, and by deﬁnition, 0! = 1. Prove that F(n)=n! for all n≥ 0, where F(n)= braceleftBigg 1ifn=0 n·F(n−1) if n>0. 17. Consider the following recurrence relation: H(n)= braceleftBigg 0ifn=0 n·H(n−1)+1 ifn>0. Prove that H(n)=n!(1/1!+1/2!+1/3! +···+1/n!) for all n≥ 1. 18. Is1+ 17 6 n−2n 2 + 7 6 n 3 a closed-form solution for the following recurrence relation? P(n)= braceleftBigg 1ifn=0 4·P(n−1)−n 2 if n>0. Prove or disprove. 19. Recall the Fibonacci numbersdeﬁned in Deﬁnition 3.1 on page 144. Recall also that ceilingleftxceilingright isthe least integer k such that k ≥ x, called the ceiling of x. Isit true that F(n)= ceilingleftBig e ( n−2 2 ) ceilingrightBig for all n≥ 1? Prove or disprove.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 163 — #23 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.3 Recursive Deﬁnitions 163 *20. Recall the deﬁnition of Fibonacci numbersin Deﬁnition 3.1. (a) Compute the sequence of diﬀerences of the ﬁrst nine Fibonacci num- bers. What seems to be true about this sequence? (b) Prove your assertion in part (a). (c) Explain why a closed-form formula for the Fibonacci numbers cannot be a polynomial function. *21. Suppose you are given a sequence of numbers a 1 ,a 2 ,a 3 ,...,a k . Explain how to construct a polynomial p(x) such that p(n)=a n for all n = 1,2,3,...,k. (Note that this fact, along with Exercise 20, shows that it is possible for a closed-form formula to match a recurrence relation for arbitrarily many terms, without being a valid closed-form solution.) 3.3 Recursive Deﬁnitions The deﬁnition of a recurrence relation is self-referential—we state a rule for calculating the valuesof a function in termsof itself. Recurrence relationshave two parts: a base case that describes the simplest case of the function and a recursive step that describes the function in terms of a simpler version of itself. This is the essence of recursive thinking. In this section, we will apply this idea to an assortment of diﬀerent objects. 3.3.1 Deﬁnition and Examples We will use the term object somewhat loosely—an object could be a number, a mathematical structure, a function, or almost anything else we want to describe. A recursive deﬁnition of a given object hasthe following parts: B. a base case, which usually deﬁnes the simplest possible such object, and R. a recursive case, which deﬁnes a more complicated object in terms of a simpler one. The best way to understand recursive deﬁnitions is to see some examples. Example 3.13 Any recurrence relation isa recursive deﬁnition of a function. For example, the recurrence relation H(n)= braceleftBigg 1ifn=1 H(n−1)+6n−6ifn>1

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 164 — #24 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 164 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking for the hexagonal numbers(Example 3.4) can be written asa recursive deﬁni- tion with a base case and a recursive case: B. H(1)=1. R. For any n>1, H(n)=H(n−1)+6n−6. Example 3.14 Let X be a set of actors and actresses, deﬁned as follows. B. Kevin Bacon ∈X. R. Let x be an actor or actress. If, for some y ∈X, there hasbeen a movie in which both x and y appear, then x∈X. In other words, Kevin Bacon is in X, and anyone who hasbeen in some movie with someone in X isalso in X. For example, in order to show that Arnold Schwarzenegger ∈X, we note that Arnold Schwarzenegger appeared in Conan the Barbarian with JamesEarl Jones, who appeared in Clear and Present Danger with Harrison Ford, who appeared in The Fugitive with Tommy Lee Jones, who appeared in JFK with Kevin Bacon. Although this example might seem silly, it illustrates an important way to think about how things are connected. It is not hard to see how the same deﬁnition could describe the set of all computers exposed to a certain virus, or the collection of people who have heard about a tornado warning, etc. For more on the Kevin Bacon example and itsrelation to graph theory, see Hopkins[15]. A sequence of symbols written together in some order is called a string. The next example gives a useful recursive deﬁnition. Note that there are two base cases in this example. Example 3.15 Given a list of symbolsa 1 ,a 2 ,...,a m ,astring of these symbols is: B 1 . the empty string, denoted by λ,or B 2 . any symbol a i ,or R. xy, the concatenation of x and y, where x and y are strings. Since λ represents the empty string, we do not write λ after it hasbeen con- catenated with another string. For example, cubsλ = cubs. It shouldn’t be hard to convince yourself that this deﬁnition describes any possible “word” in the given symbols. Example 3.16 A special kind of string called a palindrome can be deﬁned as follows. B 1 . λ isa palindrome.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 165 — #25 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.3 Recursive Deﬁnitions 165 B 2 . Any symbol a isa palindrome. R. If x and y are palindromes, then yxy isa palindrome. Note that any word that isthe same forward asbackward isa palindrome, such as racecar or HANNAH. We can build up the palindrome racecar from the deﬁnition asfollows. 1. Since it isa symbol, e isa palindrome, by B 2 , the second part of the deﬁnition. 2. Similarly, c isa palindrome. 3. Using R, cec isa palindrome. 4. By B 2 , a isa palindrome. 5. By R, aceca isa palindrome. 6. By B 2 , r isa palindrome. 7. By R, racecar isa palindrome. Asan exercise, think about why we have to deﬁne λ asa palindrome. The next example has one base case and two recursive cases. Example 3.17 The set X of all binary strings (strings with only 0’s and 1’s) having the same number of 0’sand 1’sisdeﬁned asfollows. B. λ isin X. R 1 . If x isin X, so are 1x0 and 0x1. R 2 . If x and y are in X,soisxy. Notice that both recursive cases preserve the property of having the same num- ber of 1’s as 0’s. Both of these cases form new strings from old by adding 0’s and 1’s, and they always add the same amount of each. Strings can be useful in a number of contexts: text in word processing, genetic sequences in bioinformatics, etc. Thinking recursively can help us deﬁne operationsthat manipulate the symbolsin a string. For example, the next recursive deﬁnition describes how to reverse the order of a string. Example 3.18 If s isa string, deﬁne its reverse s R asfollows. B. λ R = λ. R. If s has one or more symbols, write s = ra where a isa symbol and r is a string (possibly empty). Then s R =(ra) R =ar R .

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 166 — #26 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 166 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking In other words, you reverse a string by moving the last symbol to the front and reversing the rest of the string. To see how this deﬁnition works, consider the string pit. Itsreverse, ( pit) R , iscalculated asfollows: (pit) R = t(pi) R by part R = ti(p) R by part R = ti(λp) R (insertion of empty string) = tipλ R by part R = tipλ by part B = tip (removal of empty string). Most of the work in reversing pit wasdevoted to showing that ( p) R = p. The deﬁnition doesn’t say that the reversal of a one-symbol string is the same one- symbol string, but this fact follows from the deﬁnition by the above argument. It isa good idea to state such factsastheorems. Theorem 3.1 If a is a symbol, then a R =a. Proof Asabove, a R =(λa) R =aλ R =aλ=a. square Example 3.19 Deﬁne a line map asfollows. B. A blank rectangle isa line map. R. A line map with a straight line drawn all the way across it is a new line map. The recursive deﬁnitions of strings and line maps are similar: the base case is a blank object, and the recursive case deﬁnes how to add a new piece to an object to make it more complex. Thisisa useful way to think about objects that are built from identiﬁable pieces. Figure 3.6 A line map.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 167 — #27 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.3 Recursive Deﬁnitions 167 3.3.2 Writing Recursive Deﬁnitions Just as some functions are easy to deﬁne using recurrence relations, some ob- jects have natural recursive deﬁnitions. The trick to writing a recursive deﬁni- tion is to see the desired object as being built out of levels. The recursive case of the deﬁnition must describe a level in terms of the next simplest level. The base case should describe the simplest possible such object. Some examples will make thisidea lessabstract. Example 3.20 Suppose you start browsing the Internet at some speciﬁed page p. Let X be the set of all pages you can reach by following links, starting at p. Give a recursive deﬁnition for the set X. Solution: Observe that if you can reach some page x, then you can reach any page to which x hasa link. Thisgivesthe recursive part of the deﬁnition: R. If x∈X and y is some page such that x linksto y, then y∈X. The base case is the page where you start: B. p∈X. Notice the similarity to Example 3.14. ♦ The reasoning in this last example was “top-down.” We thought about the recursive part ﬁrst: what pages can you get to from any given page? The next example uses “bottom-up” thinking: start with the simplest case, and think about how to build up a slightly more complicated case. Example 3.21 Give a recursive deﬁnition for the set of all odd natural num- bers. Solution: To ﬁnd the base case, think about the simplest possible case of an odd natural number. A reasonable choice for the simplest odd number is 1. For the recursive case, think about how to get a new odd number from an old odd number. Observe that, if x isodd, then x+ 2 isodd also. So we can deﬁne the set X of odd numbersasfollows. B. 1isinX. R. If x isin X,soisx+2. ♦ At thispoint you should object: we already have a deﬁnition for odd num- bers(Deﬁnition 1.6). According to thisdeﬁnition, the set of odd natural num- bersshould be {n∈ N |n=2k+ 1 for some integer k}.

Unknown

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 168 — #28 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 168 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking Fair enough. Deﬁnition 1.6 doesstipulate what odd numbersare, once and for all. We should therefore view the recursive deﬁnition in Example 3.21 as an equivalent way to describe the set of odd natural numbers. Of course, we need to prove that these two deﬁnitionsare equivalent; we’ll do thisin the next section. Example 2.5 illustrated how to organize data into a binary search tree. More generally, any graph with thistype of structure iscalled a binary tree. These graphs have a natural recursive deﬁnition. Example 3.22 Give a recursive deﬁnition for the set of all binary trees. Solution: For convenience, let’s allow the “empty tree” consisting of no vertices and no edges to be a simple case of a binary tree. A single vertex could also be considered to be a binary tree. Using these two building blocks, a new tree can be formed from two existing treesby joining the two treesunder a common root node. So we can write the following deﬁnition for a binary tree. Note that thisdeﬁnition also deﬁnesthe root of the binary tree. B 1 . The empty tree isa binary tree. B 2 . A single vertex is a binary tree. In this case, the vertex is the root of the tree. R. If T 1 and T 2 are binary treeswith roots r 1 and r 2 , respectively, then the tree T 1 T 2 r 2 r 1 r isa binary tree with root r. Here the circlesrepresent the binary trees T 1 and T 2 . If either of these trees T i (i =1,2) isthe empty tree, then there isno edge from r to T i . ♦ As we saw in Section 3.1, seeing the recursive structure to an object can be the key to deﬁning a recurrence relation. In Example 3.6, we observed that a complete binary tree is made of two smaller complete binary trees. The deﬁ- nition in Example 3.22 generalizesthisobservation. 3.3.3 Recursive Geometry We can think of a recurrence relationR(n) as a rule for constructing a sequence of numbers R(1),R(2),R(3),.... For example, the recurrence relation R(n)= braceleftBigg 2ifn=1 radicalbig R(n−1) if n>1

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 169 — #29 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.3 Recursive Deﬁnitions 169 producesthe sequence 2,1.414,1.189,1.091,1.044,1.022,1.011,1.005,... to three decimal places. We say that the limit of this sequence is 1 because the numbers in this sequence get closer and closer to 1 as n getslarger. Similarly, we can consider the limit of a recursive deﬁnition of geometric patterns. This is one way to construct fractals, a special type of shape with inﬁnite layers of self-similarity. The following examples illustrate this process. Example 3.23 Deﬁne a sequence of shapes as follows. B. K(1) isan equilateral triangle. R. For n>1, K(n) isformed by replacing each line segment of K(n−1) with the shape such that the central vertex points outwards. Figure 3.7 showsthe ﬁrst three termsof thissequence. The limit of this sequence of shapes is a fractal known as the Koch snowﬂake, shown in Figure 3.8. K(3)K(2)K(1) Figure 3.7 The curves K(1), K(2), and K(3).

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 170 — #30 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 170 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking Figure 3.8 The Koch snowﬂake fractal. The next example illustrates how to ﬁnd a recursive structure, given a fractal. Example 3.24 The fractal model for the Badda-Bing axiomatic system of Example 1.17 is shown in Figure 3.9. Notice that the pattern starts with a Figure 3.9 A fractal model for the Badda-Bing geometry. central square in the middle, with smaller squares on each vertex of this square, and smaller squares on all those vertices, and so on. Each time the squares get smaller, they do so by a factor of 1/2. These observations lead to a deﬁnition for a sequence of shapes B(1),B(2),B(3),... whose limit is the Badda-Bing fractal. B. B(1) isa square. R. For n>1, B(n) isformed from B(n− 1) by adding squares to every vertex v that lieson only one square S. Such a new square must have v

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 171 — #31 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.3 Recursive Deﬁnitions 171 asa vertex, be oriented the same way as S, touch S at v only, and have side length 1/2 the side length of S. Figure 3.10 showsthe ﬁrst three termsof thissequence. B(1) B(2) B(3) Figure3.10 The ﬁrst three terms of a sequence whose limit is the Badda-Bing fractal. The above deﬁnition deﬁnes a sequence of shapesB(1),B(2),B(3),...that approximate the Badda-Bing fractal. None of these shapes is the fractal, ex- actly. The actual fractal consists of inﬁnitely many squares, while each approx- imating shape B(n) contains ﬁnitely many. However, it is possible to deﬁne the fractal as a recursive set, following the idea in Example 3.21. The following statements deﬁne a set B of pointsin the plane. B. isin S. R. If isin S (in any orientation), so are . Thisdeﬁnition issomewhat informal, but it helpsusthink about the recur- sive nature of the fractal. If you were to draw the fractal using this deﬁnition, you would start with the ﬁve squares in the base case, then you would apply the recursive case to the four squares on the corners, then you would apply the recursive case to the twelve little squares on the corners, and so on. This hypothetical “bottom-up” construction continues forever, with the squares be- coming arbitrarily small and numerous, accounting for the fractal nature of the set B. Of course, we haven’t proved that the limit of the sequence B(1),B(2), B(3),... isthe set B; we aren’t going to study limits in enough detail to make such claims. The purpose of this example is get us thinking recursively. The mathematical study of fractals is relatively new; most of the important discoveriesin thisﬁeld weren’t made until the second half of the 20 th century, when computers became widely available to mathematicians. While these ob- jects can be fascinating in themselves, their self-similar structure can help us visualize the concept of recursion. In a fractal, you can see copies of the fractal

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 172 — #32 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 172 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking one layer down; each arm of the snowﬂake in Figure 3.8 has smaller, identically shaped arms coming oﬀ of it. This is the sort of observation you must make when you write recursive deﬁnitions. How does a string contain a smaller string on the inside? How can we build up a greater odd number from a lesser one? Fractals are pretty, but they are important because they show us a picture of recursive thinking. 3.3.4 Recursive Jokes One measure of how well you understand a certain concept is whether you understand humor based on the concept. Here are some recursive jokes. Maybe these aren’t very funny, but hopefully you don’t need them explained to you. In order to understand recursion, you must understand recursion. It isn’t unusual for the following to be in the index of a book: Recursion, see Recursion. Some acronyms are recursive jokes: VISA (VISA International Service As- sociation), GNU (GNU’s Not Unix), and PHP (PHP Hypertext Protocol). An early spin-oﬀ of the text editor EMACS wasnamed EINE (EINE IsNot EMACS), and one of its successors was called ZWEI (ZWEI Was EINE Ini- tially). Certain well-known camp songs have recursive deﬁnitions, for example, “99 bottlesof beer on the wall ....” Thissong isa good example of top-down thinking. Exercises 3.3 1. Write the recurrence relation for the Fibonacci numbers(Deﬁnition 3.1) in the form of a recursive deﬁnition, with two base cases and one recursive case. 2. See Example 3.16. Why is the ﬁrst part of the deﬁnition necessary? (In other words, why must λ be deﬁned asa palindrome?) 3. Give a recursive deﬁnition for the setX of all binary strings with an even number of 0’s. 4. See Example 3.17. Give a recursive deﬁnition for the set Y of all binary strings with more 0’sthan 1’s. 5. Use the deﬁnition of the reverse of a string in Example 3.18 to compute (cubs) R . Justify each step using the deﬁnition.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 173 — #33 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.3 Recursive Deﬁnitions 173 6. Refer to Example 3.15. Suppose that the symbols can be compared, so for anyiandj withinegationslash=j, eithera i <a j ora j <a i . Modify the deﬁnition so that it deﬁnes the set of all strings whose symbols are in increasing order. 7. Let K be the set of all cities that you can get to from Toronto by taking ﬂights (or sequences of ﬂights) on commercial airlines. Give a recursive deﬁnition of K. 8. Create your own example of an object or situation whose recursive deﬁ- nition isthe same asthe Kevin Bacon movie club in Example 3.14. 9. Deﬁne a set X of numbersasfollows. B. 2 ∈X. R 1 . If x∈X,sois 10x. R 2 . If x∈X,soisx+4. (a) List all the elements of X that are less than 30. (b) Explain why there are no odd numbersin X. 10. Give a recursive deﬁnition for the set of even integers (including both positive and negative even integers). 11. Give a recursive deﬁnition for the set of all powers of 2. 12. Deﬁne a set X recursively as follows. B. 3 and 7 are in X. R. If x and y are in X,soisx+y. (Here it is possible that x=y.) Decide which of the following numbersare in X. Explain each decision. (a) 24 (b) 1,000,000 (c) 11 13. Deﬁne a set X recursively as follows. B. 12 ∈X. R 1 . If x∈X and x iseven, then x/2 ∈X. R 2 . If x∈X and x isodd, then x+1∈X. List all the elements of X. 14. Give a recursive deﬁnition for the set X of all natural numbersthat are one or two more than a multiple of 10. In other words, give a recursive deﬁnition for the set {1,2,11,12,21,22,31,32,...}.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 174 — #34 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 174 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking 15. In Example 3.22, we gave a recursive deﬁnition of a binary tree. Suppose we modify thisdeﬁnition by deleting part B 1 , so that an empty tree is not a binary tree. A tree satisfying this revised deﬁnition is called a full binary tree. (a) Give an example of a full binary tree with ﬁve nodes. (b) Give an example of a binary tree with ﬁve nodesthat isnot a full binary tree. 16. LetGbe an undirected graph, possibly not connected. The diﬀerent pieces that make upGare called the connected components ofG. More precisely, for any vertex v in G, the connected component G v containing v isthe graph whose vertices and edges are those that lie on some path starting at v. Give a recursive deﬁnition for G v . (Hint: Mimic Example 3.14.) 17. Refer to Example 3.23. Suppose that the perimeter of K(1) is3. Give a recurrence relation for the perimeter P(n)ofthenth shape K(n) in the sequence. Guess at a closed-form solution to P(n). What doesthissay about the perimeter of the Koch snowﬂake fractal? 18. The Sierpinski gasket fractal is shown in Figure 3.11. In the ﬁrst part of Example 3.24, we saw how to deﬁne a sequence of shapes to approximate a given fractal. Using thisexample asa guide, give a recursive deﬁnition for S(n), where the limit of the sequenceS(1),S(2),S(3),...isthe Sierpinski gasket. Figure 3.11 The Sierpinski gasket.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 175 — #35 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.3 Recursive Deﬁnitions 175 19. In the second part of Example 3.24, we saw an informal way to deﬁne a fractal as a recursively deﬁned set. Using this example as a guide, give an informal deﬁnition of the Sierpinski gasket as a recursively deﬁned set. 20. Give a recursive deﬁnition forT(n), where the sequenceT(1),T(2),T(3),... is the fractal tree shown in Figure 3.12. Figure 3.13 shows the ﬁrst three termsof thissequence. 21. Given an informal deﬁnition of the fractal tree in Figure 3.12 asa recur- sively deﬁned set. Figure 3.12 A fractal tree. The “buds” at the top are actually tiny branches whose shape is similar to the larger branches lower in the tree. These branches become smaller and smaller (and more numerous) as you move up the tree. T(1) T(2) T(3) Figure 3.13 The ﬁrst three terms of a sequence whose limit is the fractal in Figure 3.12. 22. Give a recursive deﬁnition forC(n), where the sequenceC(1),C(2),C(3),... is the fractal shown in Figure 3.14. (Hint: Figure 3.15 shows the ﬁrst and

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 176 — #36 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 176 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking third termsof thissequence. In Figure 3.15, if the largest circle hasradius 4, then the other circleshave radii 2 and 1.) 23. Give an informal deﬁnition of the shape in Figure 3.14 as a recursively deﬁned set. Figure 3.14 A fractal composed of circles. C(1) C(3) Figure 3.15 The ﬁrst and third terms of a sequence whose limit is the fractal in Figure 3.14. 3.4 Proof by Induction In Section 3.2, we used induction to verify a closed-form solution to a recurrence relation. There are lotsof other statementsin mathematicsthat lend themselves to proofs by induction. Here are some examples.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 177 — #37 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.4 Proof by Induction 177 • The sum of the ﬁrst n natural numbersis n(n+1) 2 . • A binary tree of height n haslessthan 2 n+1 nodes. • A convex n-gon has n(n−3) 2 diagonals. What do these examples have in common? They are all statements containing the variablen, and in each case,nstands for some natural number—each state- ment takesthe form “Statement(n)” for all n. Furthermore, these statements all involve objects that have some sort of recursive structure. In this section we extend the technique of induction to prove factsabout recursively deﬁned objects. 3.4.1 The Principle of Induction To prove that a closed form solution f(n) matchesa recurrence relation R(n), we had to prove the following: For all n≥ 1, R(n)=f(n). We did this by ﬁrst checking the base case R(1) =f(1), and then proving that R(k)=f(k) followsfrom the inductive hypothesis R(k−1) =f(k−1), for any k>1. The principle of mathematical induction generalizesthisapproach. The Principle of Mathematical Induction. To prove the statement “Statement(n), for all n≥ 1,” it suﬃces to prove 1. Statement(1), and 2. Statement(k−1) ⇒ Statement(k), for k>1. This principle is plausible by the same reasoning used in Section 3.2: Step 2 establishes a chain of implications: Statement(1) ⇒ Statement(2) ⇒ Statement(3) ⇒···, while step 1 gets the chain of implications started. It follows that these two steps, taken together, establish Statement(n) for all n≥ 1. We label this a “principle” because, strictly speaking, we can’t prove it asa theorem. In advanced treatmentsof the foundationsof mathematics, this statement is usually assumed as an axiom. 2 Recall that part 1 of the princi- ple iscalled the base case and part 2 iscalled the inductive step. In proving the inductive step, the assumption that Statement(k− 1) istrue iscalled the inductive hypothesis. 2. Often an equivalent condition called the well-ordering principle is assumed as an axiom: every nonempty set of positive integers contains a least element.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 178 — #38 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 178 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking 3.4.2 Examples Mathematical induction isoften the technique to use when you can think about a problem recursively. The discussion of the next result illustrates how to take a recursive viewpoint. Theorem 3.2 For any n≥ 1, 1+2+3+···+n= n(n+1) 2 . Let S n =1+2+3+···+n be the sum of the ﬁrst n natural numbers. Then S n hasa recursive deﬁnition: B. S 1 =1. R. S n =S n−1 +n for n>1. Understanding thisdeﬁnition isthe key to following the inductive argument. Before digesting the proof, notice how we use the notation of the Principle of Mathematical Induction. Statement(n): 1+2+3+···+n= n(n+1) 2 . Statement(1): 1 = 1(1+1) 2 . Statement(k−1): 1+2+3+···+(k−1) = (k−1)(k−1+1) 2 . Statement(k): 1+2+3+···+k = k(k+1) 2 . Proof (Induction on n.) Base Case: If n= 1, then the sum of the ﬁrst n natural numbersis1, and n(n+1)/2=1·2/3 = 1, so Statement(1) is true. Inductive Hypothesis: Suppose as inductive hypothesis that 1+2+···+(k−1) = (k−1)(k−1+1) 2 for some k>1. Inductive Step: Adding k to both sidesof thisequation gives 1+2+···+(k−1) +k = (k−1)(k−1+1) 2 +k = (k−1)(k)+2k 2 = k 2 +k 2 = k(k+1) 2 asrequired. square

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 179 — #39 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.4 Proof by Induction 179 The recursive deﬁnition of S n guidesthisproof: to move up one level from S k−1 to S k , the deﬁnition says you just add k. Thisisexactly what we did to move from Statement(k−1) to Statement(k) in the inductive step of the proof. Theorem 3.2 is basically the statement that a certain recurrence relation has a certain closed-form solution, so the proof should remind you of those in Section 3.2. The next result looksdiﬀerent, but the underlying logic isthe same, and we follow the same basic template. Theorem 3.3 Let K(1),K(2),K(3),... be the sequence of shapes whose limit is the Koch Snowﬂake of Example 3.23. Then K(n), the nth term in this se- quence, is composed of 4 n−1 ·3 line segments. The recursive deﬁnition of this sequence is important: B. K(1) isan equilateral triangle. R. For n>1, K(n) isformed by replacing each line segment of K(n−1) with the shape such that the central vertex points outward. The base case and the inductive steps of the following proof correspond to the base case and the recursive part of the deﬁnition, respectively. Proof (Induction on n.) Base Case: The base case of the deﬁnition states that K(1) consists of three line segments, and 3 = 4 1−1 ·3, so the theorem is true when n=1. Inductive Hypothesis: Suppose as inductive hypothesis that K(k − 1) is composed of 4 k−1−1 ·3=4 k−2 ·3 line segments, for some k>1. Inductive Step: By the recursive part of the deﬁnition, K(k) isformed by replacing each line segment with four others, so the number of line segmentsismultiplied by four. Therefore K(k) iscomposed of 4 ·4 k−2 ·3= 4 k−1 ·3 line segments, as required. square The preceding proof closely resembles the proofs in Section 3.2 because Statement(n) waswritten in termsof a numerical formula, much like a closed- form solution. The next example is a little diﬀerent because the claim is stated completely in the language of strings.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 180 — #40 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 180 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking Theorem 3.4 The string reversal function of Example 3.18 works. In other words, for any n≥ 1, (a 1 a 2 ···a n−1 a n ) R =a n a n−1 ···a 2 a 1 . Proof (Induction on n.) Base Case: If n= 1, then a R =a by Theorem 3.1, so the reversal function correctly reverses a one-element string. Inductive Hypothesis: Suppose as inductive hypothesis that the reversal function worksfor any string of length k−1, for some k>1. Inductive Step: Given a string a 1 a 2 a 3 ···a k of length k, (a 1 a 2 a 3 ···a k−1 a k ) R = a k (a 1 a 2 a 3 ···a k−1 ) R by deﬁnition of R , part R = a k (a k−1 ···a 3 a 2 a 1 ) by inductive hypothesis = a k a k−1 ···a 3 a 2 a 1 asrequired. square Take another look at thislast proof. It followsthe template of the veri- ﬁcation of a closed-form solution to a recurrence relation, but the recurrence relation is replaced by the recursive deﬁnition of the string reversal function. Otherwise, all the components are the same: check the base case, state the in- ductive hypothesis, use the recursive deﬁnition, apply the inductive hypothesis, and simplify to show the desired result. Proofsinvolving recursive deﬁnitionsoften require induction. The next ex- ample isquite diﬀerent; it indicatesthe diversity of resultsthat can be proved using this technique. Mathematicianssay that a map can be N-colored if there isa way to color all of the regionsof the map using only N colorsso that no two regionswith a common border share the same color. Recall the deﬁnition of a line map given in Example 3.19. Notice that the line map in Figure 3.6 can be two-colored. Figure 3.16 shows a possible two-coloring. The next theorem says that this was no accident. Figure 3.16 A two-coloring of a line map.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 181 — #41 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.4 Proof by Induction 181 Theorem 3.5 Any line map can be two-colored. Proof (Induction on the number of lines.) Base Case: If a line map contains 0 lines, then it is just a blank rectangle, so it can be two-colored trivially using a single color. Inductive Hypothesis: Suppose as inductive hypothesis that any line map with k−1 linescan be two-colored, for some k>0. Inductive Step: LetM be a line map withklines. Remove one line fromM, call it l. By inductive hypothesis, the resulting map can be two-colored, so two-color it. Now put back l, and reverse the colors of all the regions on one side of the line l. Each side will still be correctly two-colored, and any regionshaving l as a border will be opposite colors. Hence the map M iscorrectly two-colored. square In this proof, we started our induction at 0 instead of 1. We could have started at 1, and then the base case would read as follows. If a line map contains just 1 line, then one side of the line can be colored white and the other black, so the map can be two-colored. The rest of the proof would be exactly the same. Sometimes there is a choice of where to start the base case of an inductive argument. Figure 3.17 illustrates the reasoning in the inductive step of the proof of Theorem 3.5. To construct a line map, remove a line l, apply the inductive hypothesis, put l back, and reverse the colors. We have been following the same basic template for proofs by induction since Example 3.10, where we ﬁrst veriﬁed the closed-form solution of a re- currence relation. Since then we have seen several examples. Although these examples diﬀer in a variety of ways, they all match a basic pattern, which we can now state with more generality. In the following template, [object] stands for some sort of recursively deﬁned object with “levels” for each natural num- ber, and [property P] stands for the property of the [object] we are trying to justify. l replace l remove l apply inductive hypothesis reverse top side Figure 3.17 The reasoning of the inductive step in the proof of Theorem 3.5.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 182 — #42 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 182 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking Template for Inductive Proofs. An inductive proof of the statement “All [object]shave [property P]” should have the following components. Base Case: Prove that [property P] holds for the simplest [object]. Inductive Hypothesis: Suppose as inductive hypothesis that [property P] holdsfor an [object] of level k−1, for some k. Inductive Step: Suppose as given an [object] of levelk. Use the induc- tive hypothesis and the recursive deﬁnition of [object] to conclude that the given level k [object] has[property P]. For example, thisishow the template ﬁtsthe proof of Theorem 3.5. Base Case: Prove that a line map with 0 linescan be two-colored. Inductive Hypothesis: Suppose as inductive hypothesis that a line map with k−1 linescan be two-colored, for some k>0. Inductive Step: Suppose as given a line map with k lines. Follow the reasoning in Figure 3.17. If you are having trouble getting started with an inductive proof, try following thistemplate. 3.4.3 Strong Induction So far, in all of the inductive proofs we have considered, the inductive step involved shows something about a levelkobject using a hypothesis about a level k−1 object. However, there are times when we will need to use several previous levels( k−1,k−2,...,etc.) to justify the inductive step. The veriﬁcation of a closed-form solution for the Fibonacci sequence is a simple example. Recall that the recurrence relation for these numbers, F(n)= braceleftBigg 1ifn=1orn=2 F(n−1) +F(n−2) if n>2, isa little more complicated than the other recurrence relationswe have studied, since the recursive part refers to two previousvaluesof F. Observe how the proof diﬀersaccordingly. Theorem 3.6 For n≥ 1, the nth Fibonacci number is F(n)= α n −β n α−β (3.4.1) where α= 1+ √ 5 2 and β = 1− √ 5 2 .

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 183 — #43 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.4 Proof by Induction 183 Proof It iseasy to check that α and β are the solutions to the following equation: x 2 =x+1. (3.4.2) Thuswe can use thisequation asan identity for both α and β. We proceed by induction on n. Base Case: If n =1orn = 2, the recurrence relation says that F(1) = 1=F(2). Formula 3.4.1 gives F(1) = α 1 −β 1 α−β = α−β α−β =1 and F(2) = α 2 −β 2 α−β = (α+1)−(β+1) α−β , using Equation 3.4.2 = α−β α−β =1, so the closed-form solution is correct for n= 1 and n=2. Inductive Hypothesis: Let k>2. Suppose as inductive hypothesis that F(i)= α i −β i α−β for all i such that 1 ≤i<k. Inductive Step: Using the recurrence relation, F(k)=F(k−1) +F(k−2) = α k−1 −β k−1 α−β + α k−2 −β k−2 α−β , by inductive hypothesis = α k−2 (α+1)−β k−2 (β+1) α−β = α k−2 (α 2 )−β k−2 (β 2 ) α−β , using Equation 3.4.2 = α k −β k α−β asrequired. square

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 184 — #44 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 184 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking Look back at thisproof. The inductive step requiresusto use two previ- ousvaluesof F(n). That’swhy the inductive hypothesisneedsto be stronger. Instead of assuming “Statement(k− 1), for some k,” the inductive hypothesis hasthe form “Statement( i), for all i<k, for some k.” Thisisknown asstrong induction; we state thisasanother principle. The Second Principle of Mathematical Induction. To prove the state- ment “Statement(n), for all n≥ 1,” it suﬃces to prove 1. Statement(1), and 2. Statement(1) ∧ Statement(2) ∧···∧Statement(k− 1) ⇒ Statement(k), for k>1. In other words, strong induction takes as its inductive hypothesis all pre- vious cases, not just the immediate predecessor. As with simple induction, we are establishing a chain of implications that demonstrate Statement(n) for any value of n. Statement(1) ⇒ Statement(2) Statement(1)∧Statement(2) ⇒ Statement(3) Statement(1)∧Statement(2)∧Statement(3) ⇒ Statement(4) ···⇒··· Asbefore, each implication isof the form P ⇒ Q, but thistime P isthe conjunction of all previously established cases. In other words, P isa stronger assumption. This can make proving the inductive step easier, because you have more to work with. The form of an inductive proof is the same with strong induction as it was with simple induction: prove the base case, state the inductive hypothesis, and use the recursive deﬁnition to prove the next case. Only the inductive hypothesis is diﬀerent. Example 3.25 Theorem 2.9 states that a connected graph with no simple circuits is a tree. We can use strong induction to show that binary trees (as deﬁned in Example 3.22) are connected and have no simple circuits. Proof (Strong induction on the height of the tree.) Base Case: A binary tree of height 0 consists of only a single vertex, so thisgraph isconnected and hasno simple circuits. Inductive Hypothesis: Suppose as inductive hypothesis that any binary tree with height less than k is connected and has no simple circuits, for some k>1.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 185 — #45 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.4 Proof by Induction 185 Inductive Step: Suppose as given a binary tree T with height k. By the deﬁnition in Example 3.22, T consists of a root node r with edgesgoing to two subtrees T 1 and T 2 , each having height less than k. By inductive hypothesis, T 1 and T 2 are each connected and have no simple circuits. Since T 1 and T 2 are connected, there isa path from r to any vertex in T 1 and T 2 , and therefore there isa path from any vertex in T to any other vertex. So T isconnected, asrequired. Since T 1 and T 2 have no simple circuits, any simple circuit in T must pass through r. But in order for a circuit to begin and end in T 1 (or T 2 ), the circuit must pass through r twice—once to get out of T 1 , and once to get back in. Such a circuit is not simple. So T has no simple circuits, as required. square In the following example, notice that we must suppose that all previous primesare productsof primesin the inductive step. If we made only the weaker hypothesis that the preceding prime was a product of primes—as with simple induction—the argument wouldn’t work. Theorem 3.7 Every integer n≥ 2 is either prime or the product of primes. Proof (Strong induction on n.) Base Case: The only factorsof 2 are 1 and 2, so 2 isprime. Inductive Hypothesis: Let k>2 be given. Suppose as inductive hypothesis that every i issuch that 2 ≤ i<kiseither prime or the product of primes. Inductive Step: If k isprime, we are done. If k isnot prime, then k = pq for some p ≥ 2 and q ≥ 2. And since k = pq, p and q are both less than k. By inductive hypothesis, p and q are both either prime or productsof primes, so k =pq isthe product of primes. square 3.4.4 Structural Induction In all of the previous examples, induction has been “on” some discrete quantity: proofsinvolving formulasof ntend to use use induction onn; proofsabout line maps use induction on the number of lines, etc. In some cases, however, it can be awkward to specify this quantity. Example 3.26 Deﬁne a set X ⊆ Z recursively as B. 4 ∈X. R 1 . If x∈X then x−12 ∈X. R 2 . If x∈X then x 2 ∈X. Prove that every element of X isdivisible by 4.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 186 — #46 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 186 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking Before looking at the proof, notice that the two recursive cases move in op- posite directions: changingxtox−12 returnsa smaller number, while changing x to x 2 returns a larger number. So it isn’t natural to write the statement we are trying to prove in termsof n, for n ≥ 1. The point of a structural induc- tion proof is that the recursive case of the deﬁnition maintains the property of divisibility by 4. Proof of Example 3.26 (Induction on the recursive deﬁnition of X.) Base Case: Since 4 = 1·4, 4 | 4, so the claim holds for the base case of the deﬁnition. Inductive Hypothesis: Suppose as inductive hypothesis that some x∈X is divisible by 4. Then x=4a for some integer a. Inductive Step: Nowx−12 = 4a−12=4(a−3), andx 2 =(4a) 2 = 4(4a 2 ), so both x− 12 and x 2 are divisible by 4. Therefore cases R 1 and R 2 alwaysproduce integersthat are divisible by 4 (given that 4 |x), and the base case B givesan integer that isdivisible by 4. So, by induction, all elementsof X are divisible by 4. square Pay particular attention to the inductive hypothesisin thisproof: it is supposing that some element x∈X has the desired property. In earlier proofs, we thought ofxasan “object of level k−1,” and we proved something about all “objectsof level k.” Here we avoid the issue of how many levels an object has, focusing on the base and recursive cases of the deﬁnition. We call this “induction on the recursive deﬁnition” because we are really doing induction on the number of times the recursive part of the deﬁnition is used to obtain an element of X. We show that zero uses of the recursive part of the deﬁnition produces an element with the desired property, and then we suppose as inductive hypothesis that k−1 uses of the recursive deﬁnition yields an element x with the desired property. Finally, we show that one more use of the recursive deﬁnition produces an element with the desired property. All this while, the variable k operatesin the background, so it isn’t really necessary to mention it in the proof. This type of induction is also called “structural induction,” because it uses the recursive structure of an object to guide the inductive argument. Example 3.27 Theorem 3.5 states that any line map can be two-colored. Here is an alternate version of the proof of this theorem using structural induction. Proof (Induction on the deﬁnition of a line map [Example 3.19].) Base Case: The base case of a line map is a blank rectangle, which can be two-colored because it can be one-colored.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 187 — #47 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.4 Proof by Induction 187 Inductive Hypothesis: Suppose as inductive hypothesis that some line map M prime can be two-colored. Make a two-coloring of M prime . Inductive Step: The recursive part of the deﬁnition says that a new line map M can be formed from M prime by drawing some line l all the way across M prime . Now reverse the colors of all the regions on one side of the line l. Each side will still be correctly two-colored, and any regions having l asa border will be opposite colors. Hence the mapM iscorrectly two-colored. So by induction, the recursive deﬁnition of a line map always gives a two-colorable map. square Remember that mathematical induction is a recursive technique; self- reference occursin the inductive step of the proof. Thisiswhy many of the examples in this section make use of the recursive deﬁnitions from Section 3.3. Often the presence of a recursive deﬁnition indicates the need for an induc- tive proof, and the key to constructing an inductive argument lies in thinking recursively about the problem. Exercises 3.4 1. Prove that the sum of the ﬁrst n odd natural numbersis n 2 . 2. You may already have a notion of what a convex region is, but here’s a mathematical deﬁnition. Deﬁnition 3.2 A region R is convex if the line segment connecting any two pointsin R liesin R. A polygon isconvex if it and itsinterior form a convex region. A consequence of thisdeﬁnition isthat all the diagonalsof a convex polygon lie inside the polygon. Use induction to prove that a convex n- gon has n(n− 3)/2 diagonals. (Hint: Think of an n-gon ashaving an (n−1)-gon inside of it.) 3. Use induction to prove that the sum of the angles of a convex n-gon is 180(n−2) degrees. 4. Prove that any palindrome with an even number of letterscan be con- structed using the deﬁnition in Example 3.16. Use induction on n, where 2n isthe length of the palindrome. So you need to prove that the string a n a n−1 ···a 2 a 1 a 1 a 2 ···a n−1 a n can be constructed, for all n≥ 1.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 188 — #48 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 188 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking 5. Prove that any palindrome with an odd number of letterscan be con- structed using the deﬁnition in Example 3.16. 6. Prove by induction that all of the hexagonal numbersare odd. (See Ex- ample 3.4.) 7. Recall the deﬁnition of a line map (Example 3.19). (a) Prove by induction that a line map with n distinct lineshasat least n+ 1 regions. (b) Prove by induction that a line map with n distinct lines has at most 2 n regions. (c) Part (a) givesa lower bound on the number of regionsin a line map. For example, a line map with ﬁve lines must have at least six regions. Give an example of a line map that achievesthislower bound, that is, draw a line map with ﬁve lines and six regions. (d) Part (b) saysthat a line map with three linescan have at most eight regions. Can you draw a line map with three linesthat achievesthis upper bound? Do so, or explain why you can’t. 8. Let the following deﬁnitionsbe given, where s isa string. Deﬁnition 1. Deﬁne the number l(s) asfollows. B 1 . l(s)=0ifs isthe empty string. B 2 . l(s)=1ifs is a single symbol. R. l(s)=l(x)+l(y)ifs=xy. Deﬁnition 2. Letnbe a natural number. Deﬁne the stringnsasfollows: B. 1s=s. R. ns=(n−1)s if n>1. Use these deﬁnitions to prove that l(ns)=nl(s) for all n≥ 1. 9. Use the recursive deﬁnition in Example 3.22 to prove that a binary tree with height n haslessthan 2 n+1 nodes. 10. Refer to Exercise 15 of Section 3.3 for the deﬁnition of a full binary tree. (a) Use strong induction to prove that a full binary tree has an odd number of nodes. (b) Prove that a full binary tree hasan even number of edges.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 189 — #49 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.4 Proof by Induction 189 11. In Exercise 3 of Section 3.1, we deﬁned the following recurrence relation: H(n)=      0ifn≤ 0 1in=1orn=2 H(n−1) +H(n−2)−H(n−3) if n>2 . Prove that H(2n)=H(2n−1) =n for all n≥ 1. 12. The LucasnumbersL(n) are deﬁned in Exercise 4 of Section 3.1, and the Fibonacci numbers F(n) are given by Deﬁnition 3.1. Prove that L(n)= F(n−1) +F(n+ 1) for all n≥ 2. 13. Prove that B(n), the nth term in the sequence of shapes whose limit is the Badda-Bing fractal of Example 1.17, has4 · 3 n−1 free vertices(i.e., verticesthat lie on only one square) for all n≥ 1. 14. Prove that B(n), the nth term in the sequence of shapes whose limit is the Badda-Bing fractal of Example 1.17, consists of 2·3 n−1 −1 squares, for n≥ 1. 15. Prove that K(n), the nth term in the sequence of shapes whose limit is the Koch snowﬂake fractal of Example 3.23, has perimeter 3 · (4/3) n−1 , where the equilateral triangle in K(1) hasside length of 1 unit. 16. Find a formula for the area of (the black part of) S(n), the nth term in the sequence of shapes whose limit is the Sierpinski gasket fractal in Figure 3.11 on page 174. Assume that S(1) isa black equilateral triangle with area 1. Prove that your formula iscorrect. 17. Let X be the set deﬁned in Example 3.21. (a) Prove, by induction onn, that 2n+1∈X for alln≥ 0. (Thisshows that X containsall the odd natural numbers.) (b) Prove by induction that every element inX isodd. (Thisshowsthat the set of all odd natural numbers contains X.) (c) Together, what do (a) and (b) show? 18. Deﬁne a set X recursively as follows. B. 2 ∈X. R. If x∈X,soisx+ 10. Use induction to prove that every element of X iseven.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 190 — #50 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 190 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking 19. Deﬁne a set X recursively as follows. B. 3 and 7 are in X. R. If x and y are in X,soisx+y. (Here it is possible that x=y.) Prove that, for every n≥ 12, n∈X. (Hint: For the base case, show that 12, 13, and 14 are in X.) 20. In the game of chess, a knight moves by jumping to a square that is two unitsaway in one direction and one unit away in another. For example, in Figure 3.18, the knight at K can move to any of the squares marked with an asterisk ∗. Prove by induction that a knight can move from any square to any other square on an n×n chessboard via a sequence of moves, for all n≥ 4. K * * * * * * * * Figure 3.18 A knight can move to a square with a 2×1 L-shaped jump. 3.5 Recursive Data Structures In this section we will see how thinking recursively about how to organize data can lead to elegant solutions. We will give recursive deﬁnitions for lists and trees, and we will use these deﬁnitions to deﬁne useful functions on these structures. Moreover, we will prove that these functions do what they are supposed to do. Since the deﬁnitions and functions are recursive, most of these proofs will use induction. 3.5.1 Lists Almost every computer application uses some kind of list object. A list isa set of data elements in some sequential order x 1 ,x 2 ,x 3 ,...,x n

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 191 — #51 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.5 Recursive Data Structures 191 where all of the x i ’s are of the same type (e.g., integers, strings, etc.). You can make a list of n elementsby adding an element to the end of a list of n− 1 elements; this observation inspires the following recursive deﬁnition. Deﬁnition 3.3 Let X be a set. A list of elementsof X is: B. x where x∈X. R. L,x where x∈X and L isa list of elementsof X. Notice that, unlike a set, a list may repeat the same element several times, and the order of the elements matters. Every symbol in this deﬁnition is im- portant; the commasbetween the list elementsare part of the structure of a list. For example, we can build up the list of strings cubs,bears,bulls,cubs in a bottom-up fashion using this deﬁnition. L 1 = cubs by part B L 2 = L 1 ,bears = cubs,bears by part R L 3 = L 2 ,bulls = cubs,bears,bulls by part R L 4 = L 3 ,cubs = cubs,bears,bulls,cubs by part R One advantage to deﬁning lists recursively is that it makes it possible to deﬁne recursive functions that tell us something about the data in the list. For example, we can use recursion to add up all the elements in a list of integers. Deﬁnition 3.4 Let L be a list as deﬁned by Deﬁnition 3.3, where X = R, the real numbers. Deﬁne a function Sum(L) recursively as follows. B. If L=x, a single number, then Sum(L)=x. R. If L=L prime ,xfor some list L prime , then Sum(L) = Sum(L prime )+x. Notice how the base and recursive cases of this deﬁnition match the base and recursive cases of Deﬁnition 3.3. The recursive structure of a list determines the way we write recursive functions. Example 3.28 To evaluate the Sum function on the list 3,1,4,2, it isnatural to take a top-down approach. Sum(3,1,4,2) = Sum(3,1,4) + 2 by part R = Sum(3,1)+4+2 bypart R = Sum(3)+1+4+2 bypart R = 3+1+4+2 bypart B =10.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 192 — #52 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 192 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking The Sum function returns the correct answer for the list 3,1,4,2, but will it always work? We can prove that it does, using induction. Theorem 3.8 Let L be the list x 1 ,x 2 ,x 3 ,...,x n , where the x i ’s are numbers. Then Sum(L)=x 1 +x 2 +x 3 +···+x n for all n≥ 1. Proof (Induction on the size of the list.) Base Case: If L containsonly a single number x, then the base case of the deﬁnition stipulates that Sum(L)=x, asrequired. Inductive Hypothesis: Let k>1. Suppose as inductive hypothesis that Sum(L prime )=x 1 +x 2 +x 3 +···+x k−1 for any list L prime containing k−1 elements. Inductive Step: Suppose as given a list L=x 1 ,x 2 ,x 3 ,...,x k with k elements. Then, by Deﬁnition 3.3, L=L prime ,x k , where L prime isa list of k−1 elements. Therefore, Sum(L) = Sum(L prime )+x k by part R =(x 1 +x 2 +x 3 +···+x k−1 )+x k by inductive hypothesis = x 1 +x 2 +x 3 +···+x k asrequired. square The next recursive deﬁnition is for educational purposes only; the object it deﬁnes is simple and somewhat limited. The point is to help us study ways to search for an element in a list. Deﬁnition 3.5 An SList is B. x where x∈ R, the real numbers. R. (X,Y) whereX andY are SLists having the same number of elements, and the last number in X is less than the ﬁrst number in Y. For example, (((1,3),(8,9)),((12,16),(25,30))) isan SList. Notice that SListsalwayshave 2 p elements, for some p ≥ 0. (The proof of thisfact is left asan exercise.) The number p countsthe depth of parentheses of the SList,

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 193 — #53 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.5 Recursive Data Structures 193 or more simply, the depth of the SList; every number in the list will be inside p pairs of parentheses. So the example SList above has depth 3 and contains 2 3 elements. Also notice that if L=(X,Y) isan SList of depth p, then X and Y must have depth p−1. What’sthe “S” for? The elementsof an SList must be sorted in order from left to right. That’sanother exercise. Suppose we want to deﬁne a function that will tell us whether or not a given number is in the list. Since the list is deﬁned recursively, it is natural to deﬁne the function recursively as well. Note that the base and recursive cases of the following function correspond to the base and recursive cases of Deﬁnition 3.5. Deﬁnition 3.6 Deﬁne a true or false function Search(t,L), wheretisa number (the “target”) and L is an SList, as follows. B. Suppose L=x, a list of depth 0. Then Search(t,L)= braceleftBigg true if t=x false if tnegationslash=x. R. Suppose the depth of L isgreater than 0, so L=(X,Y). Then Search(t,L) = Search(t,X)∨Search(t,Y). . The Search function is supposed to tell if a given element is in the list. For example, let L = (((1,3),(8,9)),((12,16),(25,30))). The following calculation showshow to calculate the Search function on thislist, with a target value of 8: Search[8,L] = Search[8,((1,3),(8,9))]∨Search[8,((12,16),(25,30))] = Search[8,(1,3)]∨Search[8,(8,9)]∨Search[8,(12,16)] ∨ Search[8,(25,30)] = Search[8,1]∨Search[8,3]∨Search[8,8]∨Search[8,9] ∨ Search[8,12]∨Search[8,16]∨Search[8,25]∨Search[8,30] = false∨false∨true∨false∨false∨false∨false∨false = true. Notice how to evaluate a recursive function: rewrite the function in terms of itself using the recursive step, until (hopefully) you are able to evaluate the function using the base case. Once the recursion “bottoms out,” you can evalu- ate the function because there are no more recursive references to the function. Search[8,L] worked, because it returned “true” and 8 was indeed in the list. Here is a proof that the Search function works in general. Theorem 3.9 Search(t,L) ⇐⇒ t is in L.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 194 — #54 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 194 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking Proof (Induction on p, the depth of the SList L.) Base Case: If p = 0, the list L contains only a single number, say L = x. The base case of the Search function will set Search(t,L) = true if and only if t=x. Therefore Search(t,L) ⇐⇒ t=x ⇐⇒ t isin L when the depth of the list is 0. Inductive Hypothesis: Suppose as inductive hypothesis that the Search function worksfor any list L prime of depth k − 1, for some k>0. That is, if L prime hasdepth k−1, then we suppose that Search(t,L prime ) ⇐⇒ t isin L prime . Inductive Step: Given a list L of depth k, we know that L =(X,Y) for some X and Y of depth k−1. So Search(t,L) = Search(t,X)∨Search(t,Y) by the recursive part of the function deﬁnition. Now t isin L ⇐⇒ (t isin X)∨(t isin Y) by the deﬁnition of SList ⇐⇒ Search(t,X)∨Search(t,Y) by inductive hypothesis ⇐⇒ Search(t,L) by the deﬁnition of Search. So for any SList of any depth, the Search function will be true if and only if the target isin the list. square This Search function isn’t very clever: it does not use the fact that an SList hasto be in order. Let’slook at another function designed to test whether a given number isin an SList. Deﬁnition 3.7 Deﬁne a true or false function BSearch(t,L), wheretisa num- ber and L isan SList, asfollows. B. Suppose L=x, a list of depth 0. Then BSearch(t,L)= braceleftBigg true if t=x false if tnegationslash=x. R. Suppose L hasdepth p>0, so L =(X,Y). Let r be the last element of X. Then BSearch(t,L)= braceleftBigg BSearch(t,Y)ift>r BSearch(t,X)iftnegationslash>r.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 195 — #55 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.5 Recursive Data Structures 195 For example, letL= (((1,3),(8,9)),((12,16),(25,30))), and try ﬁnding the number 8 using BSearch. Compare this calculation to the same search using the old (not smart) Search function: BSearch[8,L] = BSearch[8,((1,3),(8,9))] since 8 negationslash>9 = BSearch[8,(8,9)] since 8>3 = BSearch[8,8] since 8 negationslash>8 = true since 8 = 8. BSearch appearsto be a more clever function. It lookslike the BSearch function takeslesswork (and time) to evaluate than the Search function. 3.5.2 Eﬃciency If these two search functions were implemented on a computer, we would prob- ably expect BSearch to run more eﬃciently. How much better isit? To answer this question, we can try to count the number of operations each function does. In practice, instead of counting every single operation, computer scientists try to count the number of occurrences of the most time-consuming operation. For our functions, assume that these are the comparisons t ? =x and t ? >r. First consider the Search function. Let C(p) be the number of timesthe comparison t ? = x is done when searching a list of depth p.Ifp = 0, then the list contains only a single item, so the base case B of the deﬁnition getsused and one comparison is made. Therefore C(0) = 1. Now suppose the Search function is evaluated on a list of depthp, for some p>0. Then the recursive case R of the deﬁnition getsused, and the Search function isexecuted twice on listsof depth p− 1. Each of these two recursive callsuses C(p − 1) comparisons. Therefore C(p) must satisfy the following recurrence relation: C(p)= braceleftBigg 1ifp=0 2C(p−1) if p>0. (3.5.1) This recurrence relation is easy to solve: C(p)=2 p . Since an SList of depth p contains2 p elements, the number of comparisons made by the Search function equalsthe number of elementsin the list. Similarly, we can derive a recurrence relation for the BSearch function. For a list containing a single item, the base case of the function requires one comparison. On a list of depthp,p>0, the recursive part of the deﬁnition ﬁrst makesone comparison, and then callsthe BSearch function on a list of depth

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 196 — #56 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 196 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking p− 1. If we use D(p) to represent the number of comparisons needed, we get the following recurrence relation: D(p)= braceleftBigg 1ifp=0 1+D(p−1) if p>0. (3.5.2) Thisrecurrence relation iseven easier to solve: D(p)=p+1. So you only need p+1 comparisons to ﬁnd an element in a list of size 2 p . In other words, to ﬁnd anumberinalistofN elementsusing BSearch, you need to make log 2 N +1 comparisons. Asthe size of the list getslarge, BSearch becomesa much better alter- native to Search. For example, a list containing 1,048,576 elements requires 1,048,576 comparisons using Search, but only 21 comparisons using BSearch. Such considerations are important when writing computer programs that use these functions. We will study these issues in more depth in Chapter 5. Here’s one more recursive function that will be used in the exercises. Example 3.29 Deﬁne a numerical function Sum(L), where L isan SList, as follows. B. If L=n, then Sum(L)=n. R. If L=(X,Y), then Sum(L) = Sum(X) + Sum(Y). Thisversion of the Sum function diﬀersfrom Deﬁnition 3.4 in exactly the ways that SLists diﬀer from lists; the recursive deﬁnition of the object guides the recursive deﬁnition of the function. 3.5.3 Binary Search Trees Revisited We have already considered recursive deﬁnitions for binary trees in general (Ex- ample 3.22). Now that we are used to thinking recursively about data struc- tures, it is natural to write down the following recursive deﬁnition for a binary search tree. (Compare this deﬁnition with the discussion in Example 2.5 on page 68.) Deﬁnition 3.8 Let S be a set that is totally ordered by ≤.Abinary search tree on S is B 1 . The empty tree, or B 2 . a single vertex r∈S. In thiscase, r isthe root of the tree. R. IfT 1 andT 2 are binary search trees with rootsr 1 andr 2 respectively, and if a≤r for all nodes a∈T 1 and r≤b for all nodes b∈T 2 , then the tree

Unknown

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 197 — #57 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.5 Recursive Data Structures 197 T 1 T 2 r 2 r 1 r isa binary search tree with root r. You should convince yourself that the procedure outlined in Example 2.5 always produces a binary search tree. The key observation is that part R of the recursive deﬁnition is satisﬁed. Given a binary search tree, we would like to be able to produce a listing of its nodes in order. We can deﬁne such a listing, separated by commas, as a recursive function. Deﬁnition 3.9 Deﬁne a function InOrder(T), whereT isa binary search tree, 3 asfollows. B 1 . If T isthe empty tree, InOrder( T) = “” (the empty listing). B 2 . If T isa single node r, then InOrder(T)=“r”. R. If T hasroot r and subtrees T 1 and T 2 , then InOrder(T) = “InOrder(T 1 ),r,InOrder(T 2 )” where the commas are part of the listing unless T 1 or T 2 isempty. Let’sstep through thisdeﬁnition for the binary search tree in Figure 2.7 on page 69. Let T represent the whole tree, let L represent the subtree on the left containing complexify, clueless, and jazzed, and letR be the subtree on the right containing poset, phat, and sheaﬁfy. Then InOrder(T) = InOrder(L),macchiato,InOrder(R) = InOrder(clueless),complexify,InOrder(jazzed), macchiato, InOrder(phat),poset,InOrder(sheaﬁfy) = clueless, complexify, jazzed, macchiato, phat, poset, sheaﬁfy. So InOrder produces a listing of the words in alphabetical order. To see that InOrder alwaysdoesthis, observe that part R of Deﬁnition 3.9 alwaysproduces wordsthat are in order, provided part R of Deﬁnition 3.8 holds. 3. Observethatthisdeﬁnitionappliestoagenericbinarytree.Wewilldiscussthisandsimilar deﬁnitions further in Chapter 5.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 198 — #58 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 198 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking Exercises 3.5 1. Let L be a list, as in Deﬁnition 3.3. Deﬁne a numerical function f as follows. B. If L=x, a single element, then f(L)=1. R. If L=L prime ,xfor some list L prime , then f(L)=f(L prime )+1. (a) Show the stepsof a “top-down” computation, asin Example 3.28, to ﬁnd the value of f(veni,vidi,vici). (b) What doesthe value of f(L) tell you about the list L, in general? (c) Prove your assertion in part (b), using induction. 2. Consider the following function p, where L isa list. B. If L=x, a single element, then p(L)=“x”. R. If L=L prime ,xfor some list L prime , then p(L)=“x,p(L prime )”. (a) If L= john,paul,george,ringo, what is p(L)? (b) What doesthe function p do, in general? (c) Prove your assertion in part (b), using induction. 3. Deﬁne a function max: R×R −→ R by max(a,b)= braceleftBigg a if a>b b if b≥a. (a) Use this function to write a recursive function LMax(L) that returns the greatest value in L, where L is a list of numbers. (b) Prove that your LMax function works. In other words, prove that LMax(L) returns the greatest value in the list L. 4. Prove that the number of elementsin any SList of depth p is2 p . (Use induction on p.) 5. Prove that the elements of an SList are in strictly increasing order from left to right. That is, if x 1 ,x 2 ,x 3 ,...,x 2 p are the elementsof the list, show that x 1 <x 2 <x 3 <···<x 2 p. (Use induction on p.)

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 199 — #59 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.5 Recursive Data Structures 199 6. Prove that the BSearch function (Deﬁnition 3.7) works. In other words, prove that BSearch(t,L) ⇐⇒ t isin L. 7. Prove that the Sum function of Example 3.29 works. In other words, prove, for any p ≥ 0, that if a 1 ,a 2 ,...,a 2 p are the elementsof L, then Sum(L)=a 1 +a 2 +···+a 2 p. 8. Suppose L isan SList of depth p. Find a recurrence relation for A(p), the number of timestwo numbersare added when evaluating Sum( L). 9. Write a recursive function d(L) that returnsthe depth of an SList L. 10. Write a recursive function a(L) that computesthe average of an SList L. Use the fact that the average of a list is the average of the averages of each half. 11. Let L= ((10,20),(30,40)) be an SList. (a) Compute Search(15,L), showing all steps. (b) Compute BSearch(15,L), showing all steps. 12. Let L= (((15,25),(35,45)),((50,60),(70,80))) be an SList. (a) Compute Search(15,L), showing all steps. (b) Compute BSearch(15,L), showing all steps. 13. Modify the InOrder function (Deﬁnition 3.9) so that it lists the items in a binary search tree in reverse order. *14. Write a recursive search function for ﬁnding an element in a binary search tree. You should use the notion of a left or right subtree of a node in your deﬁnition. (In Deﬁnition 3.8, the left and right subtrees are T 1 and T 2 , respectively.) Make sure you account for empty nodes. 15. Deﬁne a UList asfollows. A UList is B. a number x,or R. a pair (X,Y), where X and Y are ULists. (a) Use induction to prove that, for any n ≥ 1, a UList containing n numberscan be constructed. (b) Write a deﬁnition of a recursive function Product(L) that inputsa UList and returnsthe product of all the numbersin the UList.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 200 — #60 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 200 Chapter 3 a73 Recursive Thinking (c) Deﬁne a USearch function that tellswhether a given number isin the list. (d) Prove that your USearch function works. 16. Deﬁne a NumberSquare as B. A single number x. R. A diagram bracketleftBigg S 1 S 2 S 3 S 4 bracketrightBigg where S 1 ,S 2 ,S 3 ,S 4 are NumberSquareseach containing the same amount of numbers. Here are three examplesof NumberSquares: 4, bracketleftBigg 417 13 1 bracketrightBigg ,       bracketleftBigg 312 11 7 bracketrightBiggbracketleftBigg 51 24 bracketrightBigg bracketleftBigg 610 73 bracketrightBiggbracketleftBigg 417 13 1 bracketrightBigg       . Deﬁne a recursive function Trace(S) that returnsthe sum of the upper- left/lower-right diagonal of the NumberSquareS. (For the examplesabove, the Trace function should return 4, 5, and 15, respectively.) 17. Refer to the deﬁnition of NumberSquare in Exercise 16. The depth of a NumberSquare isthe number of pairsof bracketsneeded to write the square. (So the given examples have depth 0, 1, and 2, respectively.) Prove, using induction on p, that a NumberSquare of depth p has4 p numbersin it. 18. Deﬁne a TGraph asfollows. B. Thisisa TGraph: R. If G isa TGraph and v isa vertex of G, then thisisalso a TGraph: G v Draw an example of a TGraph with seven vertices.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 201 — #61 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ 3.5 Recursive Data Structures 201 19. Refer to Exercise 18. Prove, by induction, that every vertex in a TGraph haseven degree. 20. Refer to Exercise 18. Prove, by induction, that any TGraph can be three- colored.

✐ ✐ “48927˙CH03˙Hunter” — 2008/10/20 — 15:18 — page 202 — #62 ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐ ✐